<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dialogues containing all the most vsefull vvords of the Latine tongue And a Latine oration concerning the way of learning, and teaching the Latine and Greeke tongues. Written by Iohn Posselius. And word for word for the most part construed out of Latine into English.</title>
            <title>Oikeōn dialogōn biblion hellēnisti kai Rōmaisti. English</title>
            <author>Posselius, Johannes, 1565-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100868</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836695</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836695</idno>
            <idno type="VID">980</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09865)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 980)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1182:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Dialogues containing all the most vsefull vvords of the Latine tongue And a Latine oration concerning the way of learning, and teaching the Latine and Greeke tongues. Written by Iohn Posselius. And word for word for the most part construed out of Latine into English.</title>
                  <title>Oikeōn dialogōn biblion hellēnisti kai Rōmaisti. English</title>
                  <author>Posselius, Johannes, 1565-1623.</author>
                  <author>Reeve, Edmund, d. 1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 74 [i.e. 66] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edward Allde, and are to be sold by [Edmund Reeve at] Christ-Church greater South doore,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Edmund Reeve, of Oikeōn dialogōn biblion hellēnisti kai Rōmaisti, published in 1622 (STC 20128.3).</note>
                  <note>Pages 28,29 and 30 misnumbered 29-28 and 22; 31-38 missing in number only.</note>
                  <note>Publisher's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Latin language --  Conversation and phrase books --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:980:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>DIALOGVES CONTAINING ALL THE MOST VSEFVLL VVORDS of the Latine tongue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> A LATINE ORATION CONCERNING THE way of learning, and teaching the Latine and Greeke tongues.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Iohn Poſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And word for word for the moſt part conſtrued out of Latine into Engliſh.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Edward Allde,</hi> and are to be ſold by Chriſt-Church greater South doore. 1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:980:2"/>
            <p>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:980:2"/>
               <hi>LIbellus</hi> a little booke <hi>familiarium</hi> of familiar <hi>colloquiorum</hi> dialogues (or communications) <hi>graecè</hi> in gréeke <hi>et</hi> and <hi>Latínè</hi> in Latine, <hi>auctus</hi> increaſed, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>recognitus</hi> reuiſed. <hi>Acceſſit</hi> there hath béene added <hi>et</hi> alſo <hi>vtìlis</hi> a profitable <hi>dialògus</hi> dialogue <hi>de</hi> of <hi>rectè</hi> rightly <hi>inſtituenda</hi> ordering <hi>ratióne</hi> the manner (or way) <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diórum</hi> of ſtudies. <hi>Item</hi> and alſo <hi>oratio</hi> an oration <hi>de</hi> of <hi>ratione</hi> the way (or manner) <hi>diſcendae</hi> of learning <hi>ac</hi> and <hi>docendae</hi> of teaching <hi>latinae</hi> the latine <hi>et</hi> and <hi>graecae</hi> the gréeke <hi>linguae</hi> tongue. <hi>Iohanne</hi> John <hi>Poſſelio</hi> Poſſelius <hi>authóre</hi> being the author. <hi>Excúſum</hi> printed <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>díni</hi> at London <hi>in</hi> in <hi>officína</hi> in the ſhop <hi>ſocietátis</hi> of the company <hi>bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliopolárum</hi> of the booke fellers (or Stationers.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>FOrmùlae</hi> faſhions (or manners or litle formes) <hi>ſalutandi</hi> of ſaluting <hi>et</hi> and <hi>precandi</hi> of praying for (or wiſhing) <hi>benè</hi> wel. <hi>Obſeruande</hi> O reuerend <hi>Doctor</hi> teacher <hi>Salue</hi> haile you (or be you ſafe, or God ſpéed you.) <hi>Ornatìſsìme</hi> O moſt adorned (or very honourable) <hi>vir</hi> man <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve</hi> haile you. <hi>Clariſsìme</hi> O moſt ren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wned <hi>domìne</hi> ſir, <hi>ſalve</hi> haile you. <hi>Frater</hi> O brother <hi>ſalve</hi> haile you <hi>plurìmum</hi> very much (or moſt of all.) <hi>Condiſcipùle</hi> O ſchoole-fellow (or fellow learner) <hi>ſalve</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le you. <hi>Condiſcipùli</hi> O ſchoole-fellowes <hi>ſalvéte</hi> haile yée. <hi>Reſponſio</hi> the anſwer. <hi>Et</hi> and <hi>salve</hi> hailo tu you. <hi>Salve</hi> haile you <hi>ſimilìter</hi> likewiſe. <hi>Gaudeo</hi> I am glad <hi>te</hi> that you <hi>adveniſſe</hi> haue come (or approached) <hi>ſalvum</hi> ſafe. <hi>Iucundus</hi> pleaſant, <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>tuus</hi> your (or thy) <hi>adventus</hi> comming, <hi>redìtus</hi> returne. <hi>Habeo</hi> I haue (or giue) <hi>gratiam</hi> thankes <hi>tibi</hi> to you. <hi>Precor</hi> I pray <hi>Deum</hi> God <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>reddat</hi> he make <hi>hanc</hi> this <hi>diem</hi> day <hi>foelícem</hi> happie <hi>tibi</hi> to you. <hi>Reſponſio</hi> the anſwer. <hi>Et</hi> and <hi>precor</hi> I wiſh <hi>idem</hi> the ſame thing <hi>tibi</hi> to you. <hi>Precor</hi> I wiſh <hi>tibi</hi> to you <hi>foelícem</hi> an happy <hi>noctem</hi> night. <hi>Precor</hi> I wiſh <hi>tibi</hi> to you <hi>placìdam</hi> quiet (or gentle) <hi>quiétem</hi> reſt, <hi>Reſpouſio</hi> the anſwer. <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsìme</hi> O moſt deare <hi>Paule</hi> Paul <hi>precor</hi> I wiſh <hi>et</hi> alſo <hi>talem</hi> ſuch <hi>tibi</hi> to you. <hi>Proſit</hi> let profit (or would that may profit) <hi>tibi</hi> you <hi>Balneum</hi> the Bath. <hi>Deus</hi> God <hi>fortúnet</hi> proſper <hi>tuam</hi> your <hi>lavatiónem</hi> waſhing. <hi>Reſponſio</hi> the anſwer. <hi>Habeo</hi> I giue (or yéeld) <hi>tibi</hi> to you <hi>gratiam</hi> thankes. <hi>Tua</hi> your <hi>precatio</hi> prayer (or wiſhing) <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>grata</hi> accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>mihi to me. Vale</hi> farewell <hi>felicìter</hi> happily. <hi>Et</hi> and <hi>tu</hi> you <hi>benè</hi> well <hi>optìmè</hi> very well (or beſt of all) <hi>feliciter</hi> happily <hi>vale</hi> farewell. <hi>Valéte</hi> fare yée well. <hi>Formùlae</hi> faſhions (or rules) <hi>invitandi</hi> of inuiting <hi>ad</hi> to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:980:3"/>
               <hi>convivium</hi> a banquet. <hi>Salve</hi> hatle <hi>Praeceptor</hi> Maſter. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> the maſter. <hi>Salve</hi> hatle <hi>et</hi> alſo tu thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> O my <hi>puer</hi> boy. <hi>diſcipùle</hi> ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. <hi>Petre</hi> Peter. <hi>puer</hi> the boy. <hi>Meus</hi> my <hi>pater</hi> father <hi>rogat</hi> requeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>te</hi> you <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>apud</hi> with <hi>ſe</hi> him <hi>prandeas</hi> you dine <hi>coenes</hi> you ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>hora</hi> at (or in) the houre <hi>decìma</hi> tenth <hi>vodecìma</hi> eleuenth, <hi>quinta</hi> fift, <hi>ſexta</hi> ſixth, (or at ten a clocke <hi>&amp;c.) Meus</hi> my <hi>domìnus</hi> maſter <hi>petit</hi> traueth or deſireth <hi>a</hi> of <hi>te</hi> you, <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>ſis</hi> you be <hi>ſuus</hi> his <hi>convívs</hi> gueſt <hi>in</hi> in (or at) <hi>prandio</hi> dinner <hi>coena</hi> ſupper. <hi>Pater</hi> the father, <hi>abi</hi> goe (or depart) thou <hi>advocátum</hi> to call; <hi>adductum</hi> to bring <hi>convívas</hi> the gueſts <hi>Puer</hi> the boy. <hi>Abeo</hi> I goe (or depart) <hi>Pater</hi> O. father. <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> Maſter (or ur) <hi>vado.</hi> I goe. <hi>Fiet</hi> it ſhall be done. <hi>Curabitur</hi> it ſhall be regarded (or cared for.) <hi>Sis ſalvus</hi> be ſafe (or haile) <hi>humaniſsìme</hi> moſt courteous <hi>domine</hi> ſir <hi>praeceptor</hi> maſter or teacher. <hi>Reſponſio</hi> the anſwer. <hi>Mi</hi> my <hi>puer</hi> boy <hi>ſis</hi> bee <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>ſalvus</hi> ſafe <hi>quoque</hi> alſo. <hi>Puer</hi> the boy. <hi>Meus</hi> my <hi>pater</hi> father <hi>herus</hi> Lord (or maſter) <hi>expectat</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecteth <hi>tuam</hi> your <hi>humanitátem</hi> gentleneſſe. <hi>Ea</hi> it, <hi>vbi</hi> when as <hi>volet</hi> it ſhall pleaſe (or be willing) <hi>veniat</hi> let (or may) come <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>pran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> dinner <hi>caenam</hi> ſupper. <hi>Eximie</hi> excellent <hi>domine</hi> maſter <hi>Doctor</hi> Doctour <hi>omnes</hi> all <hi>convívae</hi> the gueſts <hi>jam</hi> now (or already) <hi>adſunt</hi> are preſent <hi>expectant</hi> they ſtay for <hi>te</hi> you <hi>vnum</hi> only <hi>et</hi> and <hi>niſi</hi> vnleſſe <hi>expectárent</hi> they did tarry for <hi>te</hi> you <hi>jam</hi> now (or forthwith) <hi>accum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bèrent</hi> they would ſit downe. <hi>Ideo</hi> therefore <hi>rogant</hi> they requeſt <hi>te</hi> you <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>accédas</hi> you come <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>prandium</hi> dinner, <hi>comum</hi> ſupper. <hi>Immìnet</hi> there is very nie <hi>inſtat</hi> there is at hand <hi>hora</hi> the hours <hi>quinta</hi> fifth, <hi>ſexta</hi> ſixth, <hi>decima</hi> tenth <hi>vndecìma</hi> eleuenth: <hi>Tempus</hi> the time <hi>prandendi</hi> of dining, <hi>coenandi</hi> of ſupping <hi>adeſt</hi> is preſent (or at hand.) <hi>Invitáti</hi> the inuited <hi>adſunt</hi> are preſent <hi>pro</hi> before (or at) <hi>forìbus</hi> the dore (or doros.) <hi>Dac</hi> lead (or bring) <hi>intrò</hi> in <hi>convivas</hi> the gueſts. <hi>Excipìto</hi> entertaine <hi>convivas</hi> the gueſts. <hi>Filius</hi> the ſonne. <hi>Salve</hi> haile <hi>obſervande</hi> reuerend <hi>praeceptor</hi> Maſter. <hi>Facis</hi> you doe <hi>rem</hi> a thing (or matter) <hi>gratam</hi> acceptable <hi>nobis</hi> to vs, (or you doe for vs an accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter,) <hi>quòd</hi> that <hi>non dedignáris</hi> you diſdaine not (or doe vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe) <hi>eſſe</hi> to be <hi>noſter</hi> our <hi>conviva</hi> gueſt. <hi>Pater</hi> the father. <hi>Puer</hi> O boy <hi>para</hi> prepare thou <hi>prandium</hi> dinner <hi>caenam</hi> ſupper. <hi>Adorne</hi> furniſh (or ſet forth) <hi>ſterne</hi> ſpread (or lay) <hi>menſam</hi> the Table. <hi>Appóne</hi> ſet to <hi>panem</hi> the bread <hi>cochlearia</hi> the ſpoones <hi>argenteda</hi> of ſiluer (or ſiluer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne) <hi>lignea</hi> of wood (or woodden.) <hi>adfer</hi> bring <hi>panarium</hi> the bread baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket <hi>mappam</hi> the table cloth <hi>pocùla</hi> the cups. <hi>Eluc</hi> rinſe (or waſh out)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:980:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>calìcem</hi> the chalire <hi>argenteum</hi> the ſiluerne <hi>pocillum</hi> cup. <hi>Penìto</hi> put <hi>circum</hi> the rundle (to ſet diſhes on) <hi>in</hi> into <hi>medium</hi> the middle <hi>menſae</hi> of the table. <hi>Collòca</hi> ſet (or place) together <hi>ſellas</hi> the ſtooles <hi>ex</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>ordìne</hi> order, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>ſuperpóne</hi> put vpon them <hi>puluinaria</hi> bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, (or pillowes, or cuſhions.) <hi>Adfer</hi> bring <hi>aquam</hi> water <hi>ad</hi> for <hi>lauandas</hi> to waſh <hi>manus</hi> hands. <hi>Laua</hi> waſh <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>prior</hi> formoſt (or firſt.) <hi>Laua</hi> waſh thou <hi>manus</hi> the hands. <hi>Lauémus</hi> let vs waſh <hi>vnà</hi> together. <hi>Porrìge</hi> reach <hi>mihi</hi> to mee <hi>mantíle</hi> the towell <hi>ſalìnum</hi> the ſaltſellar. <hi>Abſterge</hi> wipe (or make cleane) <hi>manus</hi> hands. <hi>Quid</hi> why <hi>ſtatis</hi> doeyée ſtand? <hi>ſedéte</hi> ſit yee <hi>accumbìte</hi> ſit yée downe. <hi>Prandium</hi> the dinner <hi>coena</hi> the ſupper <hi>conuiuium</hi> the banquet <hi>corrumpitur</hi> is marred <hi>tua</hi> through your <hi>abſentia</hi> abſence <hi>mora</hi> delay <hi>tarditáte</hi> ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Cibus</hi> the meate <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>appoſìtus</hi> ſet, <hi>igìtur</hi> therefore <hi>accumbite</hi> ſit yée to. <hi>Vbi</hi> where <hi>iubes</hi> doeſt thou bid <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>ſedére</hi> to ſit? <hi>In</hi> in <hi>primo</hi> the firſt (or chiefe) <hi>loco</hi> place <hi>accumbe</hi> ſit vnto <hi>diſcumbe</hi> ſit downe. <hi>Conuíuae</hi> the gueſts <hi>accubuérunt</hi> are ſate (or haue ſitte downe.) <hi>Puer</hi> boy <hi>conſècra</hi> hallow (or conſecrate) <hi>menfam</hi> the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Puer</hi> the boy. <hi>Ocùli</hi> the eyes <hi>omnium</hi> of all things <hi>ſpectant</hi> doe looke in towards <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>Domìne</hi> O Lord <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the reſt (or ſo forth.) <hi>Adde</hi> adde <hi>etiam</hi> alſo <hi>memorabìlem</hi> a memorable <hi>ſententiam</hi> ſentence, <hi>quam</hi> which <hi>nuper</hi> of late <hi>didiciſſi</hi> thou haſt learned <hi>ex</hi> out of <hi>ſacra</hi> an holy <hi>concióne</hi> ſermon. <hi>Quicquid</hi> whatſoeuer <hi>Deus</hi> God <hi>creáuit</hi> hath created <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>bonum</hi> good, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>rejiciendum</hi> to be refuſed <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>ſumátur</hi> it be receiued <hi>cum</hi> with <hi>actióne</hi> doing (or giuing) <hi>gratiárum</hi> of thankes <hi>enim</hi> for <hi>ſanctificátur</hi> it is ſanctified <hi>per</hi> by (or through) <hi>verbum</hi> the word <hi>Dei</hi> of God <hi>et</hi> and <hi>precatiónem</hi> prayer. <hi>Adfer</hi> bring <hi>epùlas</hi> the meate (or diſhes) <hi>cibum</hi> the victuall <hi>acétum</hi> the vinegar <hi>carnes</hi> the fleſh (or péeces of fleſh) <hi>aſſas</hi> roſted <hi>elixas</hi> ſodden (or boyled.) <hi>Da</hi> giue <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>pocùlum</hi> the cup <hi>vitreum</hi> of glaſſe (or glaſſen.) <hi>Porrìge</hi> reach <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>argentea</hi> the ſiluerne <hi>pocùla</hi> cups, <hi>canthàrum</hi> the pot (or Iugge) <hi>caſeum</hi> the cheeſe; <hi>panem</hi> the bread, <hi>cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellum</hi> the little knife (or meate knife.) <hi>Chriſtus</hi> Chriſt <hi>ſoſpitet</hi> make healthfull (or ſaſe) <hi>vobis</hi> to you <hi>hunc</hi> this <hi>potum</hi> drinke, <hi>hoc</hi> this <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> wine. <hi>Haec</hi> this <hi>ceruiſia</hi> béera <hi>ſit</hi> be <hi>vobis</hi> to you <hi>ſalúti</hi> for health (or vnto health.) <hi>Deus</hi> God <hi>faxit</hi> graunt <hi>id</hi> that, <hi>chare</hi> well beloued <hi>puer</hi> boy, <hi>amen</hi> amen. <hi>Da</hi> giue <hi>mihi</hi> to mee <hi>alìquid</hi> ſomewhat (or ſome) <hi>de</hi> of <hi>Gallína</hi> the Hen, <hi>Gallo</hi> the Cocke, <hi>Piſcìbus</hi> the fiſhes, <hi>pane</hi> the bread, <hi>Vis</hi> will you <hi>alìquid</hi> any thing <hi>de</hi> of <hi>piſce</hi> the fiſh <hi>anſère</hi> the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:980:4"/>
gooſe, <hi>carne</hi> the fleſh? <hi>Etiam</hi> yea <hi>volo</hi> I will, <hi>non volo</hi> I will not. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funde</hi> powre in <hi>ceruiſiam</hi> the béere, <hi>aquam</hi> the water <hi>mulſam</hi> ſod (or mingled) with honey <hi>vinum</hi> the wine <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>bibámus</hi> we may drinke. <hi>Non vis</hi> wilt thou not <hi>bibère</hi> drinke? <hi>Cur</hi> why <hi>non bibis</hi> drinkeſt thou not? <hi>Mones me</hi> thou putteſt me in minde <hi>rectè</hi> well, <hi>enim</hi> for <hi>ſitio</hi> I am a thirſt <hi>omníno</hi> throughly. <hi>Non ſitio</hi> I thirſt not. <hi>Propíno</hi> I drinke <hi>tibi</hi> to thée. <hi>Bibi</hi> I haue drunke <hi>ſatis</hi> enough. <hi>Deus</hi> God <hi>benedícat</hi> bleſſe (it.) <hi>Accipio</hi> I take it <hi>à</hi> from (or of) <hi>te</hi> you <hi>libenter</hi> gladly. <hi>Ne ebibas</hi> drinke not vp <hi>totum</hi> the whole. <hi>Relinquam</hi> I will leaue <hi>tibi</hi> for you <hi>ſatis</hi> enough. <hi>Relinquam</hi> I will leaue <hi>tibi</hi> for you <hi>plus</hi> more <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>ſum</hi> I am <hi>bibitúrus</hi> about to drinke. <hi>Nihil</hi> no <hi>ceruiſiae</hi> béere, <hi>vini</hi> wine, <hi>aquae</hi> water <hi>mulſae</hi> ſodden (or mingled with honey) <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>relìquum</hi> left (or remaining.) <hi>Abſcinde</hi> cut off <hi>mihi</hi> for me <hi>alìquid</hi> ſome (or ſomewhat) <hi>de</hi> of <hi>Bouína</hi> the Oxes (or Cowes) <hi>carne</hi> fleſh (the béefe) <hi>induráta</hi> hardned <hi>fumo</hi> with the ſmoke. <hi>Tolle</hi> take away <hi>hanc</hi> this <hi>patìnam</hi> platter <hi>et</hi> and <hi>appóne</hi> ſet to <hi>caetèra</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>fercùla</hi> meſſes. <hi>Explédí</hi> I haue ſatisfied (or ſtinted) <hi>ſedáui</hi> I haue alayed (or quenched) <hi>famem</hi> hunger. <hi>Tu</hi> thou <hi>es</hi> art <hi>perpaúci</hi> of very little <hi>cibi</hi> meate (or diet.) <hi>Non ſum</hi> I am not <hi>edax</hi> a greateater. <hi>Bibe</hi> drinke: <hi>non ignóras</hi> thou art not ignorant of <hi>legem</hi> the law <hi>vetèrum</hi> of the olde <hi>Graecórum</hi> Gréekes: <hi>aut</hi> either <hi>bibe</hi> drinke, <hi>aut</hi> or <hi>abi</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>lex</hi> the law <hi>Chriſti</hi> of Chriſt <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>melior</hi> better: <hi>cauéte</hi> take héede <hi>vobis</hi> to your ſelues <hi>nequando</hi> leaſt at any time <hi>veſtra</hi> your <hi>corda</hi> hearts <hi>grauentur</hi> be ſurcharged <hi>crapùla</hi> with ſurfet (or ſurfet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>ebrietáte</hi> drunkenneſſe. <hi>Praebéte</hi> ſhew <hi>vos</hi> your ſelues <hi>lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tos</hi> merry <hi>hilàres</hi> chéerefull. <hi>Puer</hi> boy <hi>torre</hi> roſt (or boyle) <hi>hunc</hi> this <hi>piſcem</hi> fiſh <hi>in</hi> in (or on) <hi>craticùla</hi> the grediron, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>caue</hi> take héede <hi>ne</hi> that not <hi>adurátur</hi> it ve burnt. <hi>Cura</hi> haue a care <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>oua</hi> the egges <hi>coquantur</hi> be boyled <hi>molliuſcula</hi> ſomwhat ſoſter <hi>duriuſcùla</hi> ſomewhat harder. <hi>Oua</hi> the egges <hi>ſunt</hi> are <hi>mollia</hi> ſoft, <hi>ſunt</hi> are <hi>cruda</hi> rawe, <hi>ſunt</hi> are <hi>mollióra</hi> ſoſter <hi>iuſto</hi> than néede (or reaſon is.) <hi>Muta</hi> change thou <hi>orbes</hi> the trenchers. <hi>Tolle</hi> take vp (or away) <hi>cibum</hi> the meate, <hi>panem</hi> the bread, <hi>butyrum</hi> the butter, <hi>caſeum</hi> the chéeſs. <hi>Appóne</hi> ſet to <hi>pelium</hi> the baſon <hi>cum</hi> with <hi>mantíli</hi> the towell (or hand-wiper.) <hi>Puer</hi> boy <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> bring <hi>bellaria</hi> the banquetting diſhes. <hi>Emunge</hi> ſnuffe <hi>candélam</hi> the candle. <hi>Caue</hi> take héede <hi>ne</hi> leaſt that <hi>extinguas</hi> thou put out (or quench) <hi>lychnum</hi> the light. <hi>Appóne</hi> ſet to <hi>poma</hi> the apples, <hi>pruna</hi> the plummes, <hi>nuces auellánas</hi> the filberds, <hi>vuas</hi> the grapes, <hi>vuas paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſas</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:980:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the raiſons, <hi>pyra</hi> the peares, <hi>ceràſa</hi> the cherries, <hi>juglandes</hi> the waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts, <hi>amygdàlas</hi> the almonds, <hi>toſta</hi> the roſted <hi>pyra</hi> peares. <hi>Ego</hi> I <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eus</hi> truſting to (or relying on) <hi>veſtra</hi> your <hi>comitáte</hi> courteſie <hi>inuitáui</hi> haue inuited <hi>vos</hi> you <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>frugále</hi> à thrifty (or ſparing) <hi>prandium</hi> dinner <hi>fiugálem</hi> a thrifty (or meane) <hi>coenam</hi> ſupper. <hi>Conuíuae</hi> the gueſts. <hi>Tuum</hi> your (or thy) <hi>prandium</hi> dinner <hi>fuit</hi> hath béene <hi>ſplendì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> gorgeous (or richly decked) <hi>ſupra</hi> aboue <hi>modum</hi> meaſure. <hi>Tua</hi> your (or thy) <hi>coena</hi> ſupper <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>non</hi> not <hi>frugális</hi> ſpare (or meane) <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>ſumptuóſa</hi> ſumptuous. <hi>Tua</hi> thy <hi>coena</hi> ſupper <hi>fuit</hi> hath beene <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificentior</hi> more ſumptuous <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>aequum</hi> reaſon (or meet.) <hi>Quod</hi> becauſe <hi>excúſas</hi> thou makeſt excuſe <hi>habes</hi> thou haſt <hi>id</hi> this <hi>vnum</hi> alone (or onely) <hi>cur</hi> wherefore <hi>ſis</hi> thou maiſt be <hi>accuſandus</hi> to be accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Chariſsìmi</hi> moſt deare <hi>amíci</hi> friends <hi>quaeſo</hi> I beſeech <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulátis</hi> you accept <hi>aequi</hi> of right <hi>boníque</hi> and of good (you take in good part) <hi>noſtram</hi> our <hi>coenùlam</hi> little ſupper <hi>licèt</hi> albeit <hi>tenuem</hi> ſlender (or ſimple.) <hi>Habèo tibi gratiam</hi> I thanke you <hi>quòd</hi> becauſe <hi>vocaſti</hi> you haue called <hi>me</hi> me <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>hanc</hi> this <hi>coenam</hi> ſupper <hi>longè</hi> farre <hi>ſuauiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sìmam</hi> moſt ſweete (or pleaſant.) <hi>Non eſt</hi> there is not cauſe <hi>quòd</hi> that <hi>agas</hi> you may giue <hi>gratias</hi> thankes. <hi>Ego</hi> I <hi>agnoſco</hi> doe acknowledge <hi>me</hi> that I <hi>debére</hi> doe owe <hi>gratiam</hi> thankes <hi>tibi</hi> to you, <hi>quòd</hi> becauſe <hi>non dedignátus es</hi> you haue not diſdained <hi>venìre</hi> to come <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>hanc</hi> this <hi>tenuem</hi> flender <hi>coenam</hi> ſupper. <hi>Formùlae</hi> ſhort formes (or rules) <hi>petendi</hi> of crauing <hi>quippiam</hi> any thiug <hi>à</hi> of <hi>praeceptórc</hi> the maiſter. <hi>Obſeruande</hi> reuerend <hi>praeceptor</hi> maiſter <hi>quaeſo</hi> I beſeech <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>liceat</hi> it may be lawfull <hi>mihi</hi> for me <hi>abeſſe</hi> to be abſent <hi>ſchola</hi> from ſchoole <hi>prima</hi> at the firſt <hi>hora</hi> houre (at one a clocke) <hi>cauſsâ</hi> for the fake <hi>lauan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di</hi> of waſhing. <hi>Precor</hi> I pray <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>facias</hi> you giue (or grant) <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>facultátem</hi> leaue (or power) <hi>manendi</hi> to abide <hi>domi</hi> at home. <hi>Enim</hi> for <hi>alìquid</hi> ſomething <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>efficiendum</hi> to be done <hi>mihi</hi> of me. (Or <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiendum eſt mihi aliquid</hi> I muſt bring to effect (or paſſe) ſome matter.) <hi>Eſt mihi abeundum</hi> I muſt depart (or goe) <hi>rus</hi> to the country <hi>cum</hi> with <hi>meis</hi> my <hi>parentìbus</hi> parents <hi>oro</hi> intreate <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>id</hi> that <hi>fiat</hi> may be done <hi>tua</hi> by your <hi>pace</hi> leaue. <hi>Concédas</hi> graunt <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>poteſtátem</hi> power (or leaue) <hi>excundi</hi> to goe out <hi>cauſſa</hi> for the cauſe <hi>leuandi</hi> of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>alvum</hi> the belly <hi>ſoluendi</hi> of looſening <hi>ventrem</hi> the belly <hi>reddendae</hi> of making <hi>vrínae</hi> water (or vrine.) <hi>Liceat</hi> let it be lawfull <hi>mihi</hi> for me <hi>recurrère</hi> to runne backe <hi>domum</hi> home <hi>gratia</hi> for the ſake (or cauſe) offerendi of bringing (or fetching) <hi>cujuſpiam</hi> a certaine <hi>libeſti</hi> little
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:980:5"/>
books. <hi>Licear mihi</hi> may I <hi>exíre</hi> goe forth of <hi>Iudo</hi> the exerciſe place <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terario</hi> pertaining to learning <hi>ſchola</hi> the ſchoole <hi>ad</hi> to <hi>emendum</hi> buy <hi>papirum</hi> paper, <hi>pennam</hi> a penne, <hi>panem</hi> bread. <hi>Quiſpiam</hi> a certaine one <hi>expètit</hi> deſireth <hi>conuentum</hi> to ſpeake with <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>prae forìbus</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> doore: <hi>itàque</hi> therefore <hi>quaeſo</hi> I beſéech <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>lìceat mihi</hi> I may <hi>tua pace</hi> by your leaue <hi>exire</hi> goe forth <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>hunc</hi> him. <hi>Meus</hi> my <hi>domì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> maiſter, <hi>pater</hi> father <hi>iuſſit</hi> hath commaunded <hi>me</hi> me <hi>redíre</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne <hi>domum</hi> home <hi>decìma</hi> at the tenth <hi>prima</hi> the firſt, <hi>tertia</hi> the third <hi>bora</hi> houre <hi>oro</hi> I pray <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>mihi liceat</hi> I may <hi>facère</hi> doe <hi>id</hi> that. <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put</hi> head <hi>dolet</hi> aketh <hi>mihi</hi> to me (my head aketh) <hi>dentes</hi> téeth <hi>dolent</hi> ake <hi>mihi</hi> to mee (my téeth ake) <hi>ventricùlus</hi> the ſtomacke <hi>dolet</hi> aketh <hi>mihi</hi> to me (my ſtomacke aketh) <hi>naſus</hi> my noſe <hi>ſtillat</hi> droppeth <hi>ſanguì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> bloud. <hi>Habeo</hi> I haue <hi>malè</hi> ill (I am ill at eaſe) <hi>ideò</hi> therefore <hi>quaeſo</hi> I beſéech <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>liceat mihi</hi> I may <hi>ire</hi> goe <hi>domum</hi> home. <hi>Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsime</hi> moſt louing <hi>praeceptor</hi> maiſter <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn <hi>petit</hi> humbly aſketh <hi>veniam</hi> that pardon <hi>dari</hi> be giuen <hi>ſibi</hi> to him <hi>abſenti</hi> being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn <hi>et</hi> and <hi>Paulus</hi> Paul <hi>petunt</hi> doe humbly craue <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam</hi> that pardon <hi>dari</hi> be giuen <hi>ſibi</hi> to them <hi>abſentìbus</hi> being abſent. <hi>Chariſsime</hi> moſt dearely beloued <hi>praeceptor</hi> maiſter <hi>heri</hi> yeſterday <hi>amíſi</hi> I loſt <hi>quendam</hi> a certaine <hi>libellum</hi> little booke <hi>quem</hi> which <hi>recépi</hi> I haue gotten againe <hi>nondum</hi> not as yet. <hi>Igìtur</hi> therefore <hi>rogo</hi> I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <hi>te</hi> you <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>admoneas</hi> you admoniſh <hi>condiſcipùlos</hi> the ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellowes <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>quis</hi> any one <hi>fortè</hi> by chaunce <hi>inuènerit</hi> ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after finde (or hath ſound) <hi>eum</hi> it <hi>reſtituat</hi> hee reſtore it <hi>mihi</hi> to mee. <hi>Clariſsìme</hi> moſt famous <hi>praeceptor</hi> maiſter <hi>doce</hi> teach <hi>me</hi> me <hi>quibus</hi> with what <hi>verbis</hi> words <hi>dicam</hi> I ſhall ſay <hi>Graecè</hi> in Gréeke, <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn <hi>verberáuit</hi> hath beaten <hi>me</hi> me. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> the maiſter. <hi>Dices</hi> thou ſhalt ſay <hi>ſic</hi> thus <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn <hi>&amp;c. Puer</hi> the boy, <hi>oro</hi> I intreate <hi>te</hi> you <hi>praecéptor</hi> maiſter <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>deſcríbas</hi> you deſcribe (or write downe) <hi>mihi</hi> for me <hi>figúras</hi> the figures (or formes, or characters) <hi>Graecórum</hi> of the Gréeke <hi>elementórum</hi> elements (or letters) <hi>quas</hi> which <hi>ſcribendo</hi> by writing <hi>imìter</hi> I may imitate. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> the maiſter. <hi>Vbi</hi> where <hi>habes</hi> haſt thou <hi>archetípum</hi> the archetype (or firſt patterne) <hi>quem</hi> which <hi>praeſcripſi</hi> I preſcribed <hi>tibi</hi> to thee <hi>ante</hi> before <hi>paucos</hi> fewe <hi>dies</hi> dayes (fewe dayes agoe.) <hi>Puer</hi> the boy. <hi>Amíſi</hi> I loſt <hi>eum</hi> it <hi>per</hi> through <hi>incuriam</hi> negligence (or careleſneſſe.) <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn <hi>diſcorp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit</hi> pluckt in peeces <hi>cum</hi> it <hi>mihi</hi> from me. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> the maiſter. <hi>En</hi> behold <hi>iam</hi> now <hi>habes</hi> thou haſt <hi>alium</hi> another, <hi>caue</hi> haue a care (or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:980:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
take héed) <hi>ne</hi> leaſt that (or that not) <hi>et</hi> alſo <hi>perdas</hi> thou looſe <hi>hunc</hi> this. <hi>Puer</hi> the boy. <hi>Quaeſo</hi> I pray <hi>Praeceptor</hi> O maſter <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pàres</hi> you prepare (or make fit) <hi>hanc</hi> this <hi>pennam</hi> penne <hi>mihi</hi> for me. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> Maſter. <hi>Qualem</hi> what manner <hi>pennam</hi> pen <hi>cupis</hi> deſireſt thou? <hi>Puer</hi> the boy. <hi>Attempèra</hi> fit it <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>tuam</hi> your owne <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> hand. <hi>Doce</hi> teach <hi>me</hi> mée <hi>legère</hi> to reade <hi>haec</hi> theſe things. <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mòdo</hi> how <hi>legam</hi> ſhall I read <hi>haec</hi> theſe things? <hi>Preſcríbe</hi> preſcribe <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>quantum</hi> how much <hi>ediſcam</hi> I ſhall learne without booke <hi>hac</hi> in this <hi>hora</hi> houre. <hi>Duc</hi> draw <hi>mihi</hi> for me <hi>lineas</hi> the lines. <hi>Non habeo</hi> I haue not <hi>atramentum</hi> inke. <hi>Non eſt mihi</hi> there is not to mee (or I haue not) <hi>atramentarium</hi> an inkehorue <hi>pecunia</hi> money <hi>cultel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> a little knife (or penknife) <hi>penna</hi> a penne. <hi>Formùla</hi> little formes <hi>excuſandi</hi> of excuſing <hi>abſentiae</hi> abſence <hi>apud</hi> with (or in preſence of) <hi>praeceptórem</hi> the maſter. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> the Maſter. <hi>Cur</hi> why <hi>venis</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt thou <hi>tam</hi> ſo <hi>ſerò</hi> late? <hi>Noſtri</hi> our folke (or our people) <hi>ſeriùs</hi> too late <hi>excitavérunt</hi> wakened <hi>me</hi> mée <hi>ſomno</hi> from ſleepe. <hi>Surrexi</hi> I haue riſen <hi>ſeriùs</hi> too late <hi>praeter</hi> beſides (or againſt) <hi>voluntátem</hi> will. <hi>Seriùs</hi> too late <hi>experge factus ſum</hi> I wakened <hi>propter</hi> by reaſon of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivium</hi> a banquet <hi>caenam</hi> a ſupper <hi>prolátam</hi> prolonged <hi>in</hi> into (or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to) <hi>mediam</hi> the middeſt of <hi>noctem</hi> night (midnight.) <hi>Noſtrum</hi> our <hi>horologium</hi> clocke <hi>abberrávit</hi> hath gone amiſſe. <hi>Per</hi> through <hi>negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam</hi> negligence <hi>reliquèram</hi> I had left <hi>librum</hi> a booke <hi>domi</hi> at home, <hi>hunc</hi> this <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>afferrem</hi> I might fetch (or bring,) <hi>recurri</hi> I canne backe <hi>domum</hi> home <hi>ex itìnère</hi> out of the way (or jorney.) <hi>Adjúvi</hi> I helped <hi>familiam</hi> the houſhold <hi>in</hi> in <hi>ſeponendis</hi> putting apart (or laying aſide or vp) <hi>lignis</hi> wood (or woods.) <hi>Herus</hi> my Lord (or maſter) <hi>Pater</hi> my father <hi>Hera</hi> my Lady (or miſtreſſe) <hi>Mater</hi> my Mother <hi>misèrat</hi> had ſent <hi>me</hi> mée <hi>quopiam</hi> to a certaine place. <hi>Attùli</hi> I brought <hi>vinum</hi> wine <hi>cerviſiam</hi> béere <hi>patri</hi> to my father, <hi>hero</hi> to my Lord <hi>praeceptor</hi> the Maſter. <hi>Cur</hi> wherefore <hi>ob</hi> for <hi>quam</hi> what <hi>cauſam</hi> cauſe <hi>tanto</hi> ſo great (or long) <hi>tempòre</hi> time <hi>non</hi> not <hi>veniſti</hi> cameſt thou in into <hi>Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam</hi> Schoole? <hi>Ludum</hi> the exerciſe place <hi>literarium</hi> of (or belonging to) learning? <hi>Cur</hi> wherefore <hi>non interfuiſti</hi> haſt thou not béene preſent <hi>hora</hi> in the houre <hi>prima</hi> firſt <hi>quarta</hi> fourth <hi>ſexta</hi> ſixth <hi>lectióni</hi> at Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, <hi>concióni</hi> at the Sermon? <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>impedívit</hi> hath hindred <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>quo minùs</hi> whereby the leſſe (that not) <hi>bodie</hi> to day <hi>interfuèris</hi> thou haſt not béene (or waſt not) preſent <hi>lectióni</hi> at the lecture (or leſſon, or reading?) <hi>diſcipùlus</hi> the ſcholler. <hi>Malè habui</hi> I was ill at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:980:6"/>
caſe. <hi>Aegrotávi</hi> I haue béene ſicke. <hi>Doluit mihi caput, venter</hi> my head, belly aked. <hi>Laborávi</hi> I haue béene ſicke of <hi>febri</hi> an agus (or feuer.) <hi>Non erant</hi> there were not <hi>mihi</hi> to mée <hi>tibialia</hi> ſtockens. <hi>Non erant mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi</hi> I had not <hi>calcei</hi> ſhooes. <hi>Lavìmus</hi> wée waſhed <hi>noſtrae</hi> at our <hi>domi</hi> houſe (or home.) <hi>Pacentes</hi> my parents <hi>noluérunt</hi> were vnwilling <hi>me</hi> that I <hi>frequentáre</hi> goe much to (or reſort to) <hi>Scholam</hi> Schoole <hi>propter</hi> by reaſon of <hi>intenſum</hi> the earneſt (or exceſſiue) <hi>frigus</hi> cold, <hi>vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi> the vehement <hi>aeſtum</hi> heat of the weather, <hi>pluviam</hi> raine, <hi>imbrem</hi> ſhowre. <hi>Mactavùnus</hi> we haue killed <hi>porcos</hi> hogges <hi>boves</hi> oxen <hi>oves</hi> ſhéepe. <hi>Nuptiae</hi> a marriage (or wedding) <hi>ſunt</hi> is <hi>celebrátae</hi> ſolemnized <hi>noſtri domae</hi> at our houſe <hi>quibus</hi> whereat <hi>parentes</hi> my parents <hi>volué<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt</hi> haue willed <hi>me</hi> that I <hi>intereſſe</hi> be preſent. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> O maſter <hi>rogo</hi> I pray <hi>te</hi> you <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>des</hi> you giue (or grant) <hi>mihi</hi> to mée <hi>veniam</hi> leaue (or pardon,) <hi>enim</hi> for <hi>poſthâc</hi> hereafter <hi>ero</hi> I will be <hi>dilìgens</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent <hi>et</hi> and <hi>aſſiduus</hi> continuall <hi>in</hi> in <hi>ſchola</hi> the ſchoole. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> the maſter. <hi>Eas</hi> thou maiſt goe <hi>viſum</hi> to ſée <hi>quid Petrus</hi> Peter <hi>agat</hi> doth (or may be a doing) <hi>quòd</hi> that <hi>nunc</hi> now <hi>non ſit</hi> he is not <hi>in</hi> in <hi>ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> the ſchoole. <hi>Diſcipùlus</hi> the ſchollar. <hi>Faciam</hi> I will doe it <hi>ô praeceptor</hi> O. maſter. <hi>Vado</hi> I goe. <hi>Salve</hi> God ſaue you <hi>Petre</hi> Peter. <hi>Et</hi> and <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>condiſcipùle</hi> ſchoolefellow <hi>ſalve</hi> haile. <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> the maſter <hi>juſſit</hi> hath commanded <hi>interrogáre</hi> to aske <hi>quid</hi> what <hi>agas</hi> you doe (or may be a doing) <hi>quòd</hi> that <hi>non</hi> not <hi>interſis</hi> you are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at <hi>lectionibus</hi> the readings (or lectures.) <hi>Petrus</hi> Peter, <hi>vides</hi> thou ſéeſt <hi>me</hi> that I <hi>eſſe</hi> am <hi>occupátum</hi> buſily occupied, <hi>malè habére</hi> am ill at eaſe, <hi>aegrotáre</hi> am ſicke. <hi>Ideò</hi> therefore <hi>oro</hi> I intreat <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>excúſes</hi> you excuſe <hi>me</hi> mée <hi>abſentem</hi> abſent. <hi>Vbi</hi> when <hi>caepèro</hi> I ſhall begin <hi>melius habére</hi> to be in better health, (or to finde my ſelfe better) <hi>ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim</hi> forthwith <hi>revertar</hi> I will returne <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>vos</hi> you <hi>in</hi> into <hi>ſcholam</hi> the ſchoole <hi>Diſcipùlus</hi> the ſcholler. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> O maſter <hi>curávi</hi> I haue taken care of <hi>quod</hi> what <hi>mandaſti</hi> you haue commanded (or giuen in charge.) <hi>Petrus</hi> Petes <hi>dicit</hi> ſaith <hi>ſe</hi> that hée <hi>occupátum eſſe</hi> is taken vp in buſines <hi>malè habére</hi> is ill at eaſe <hi>malè habuiſſe</hi> hath béene not well <hi>ſcripſiſſe</hi> hath written <hi>itèras</hi> letters. <hi>Decumbit</hi> haee lieth downe <hi>in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto</hi> in bed <hi>join</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (or already) <hi>tres</hi> thrée <hi>totos</hi> whole <hi>dies</hi> daies (hée hath now kept his bed thrée whole daies.) <hi>Parentes</hi> the Parents <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri</hi> of Peter <hi>dicunt</hi> doe ſay <hi>ipſum</hi> that he <hi>eſſe</hi> is <hi>profectum</hi> journied <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>règrè</hi> farre from home. <hi>Parentes</hi> the Parents <hi>Iohannis</hi> of Iohn <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt</hi> doe ſay <hi>nihil</hi> that nothing <hi>negotu</hi> of buſineſſe (no buſineſſe) <hi>faiſſe</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:980:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hath béene <hi>ei</hi> to him (or he hath had) <hi>ideò</hi> therefore <hi>rogant</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt <hi>te</hi> you <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>punias</hi> you puniſh <hi>caedas</hi> beate <hi>virgis</hi> with rods <hi>ipſum</hi> him <hi>cum</hi> when <hi>fuèrit reverſus</hi> he ſhall returne <hi>in ſcholam</hi> into the ſchoole. <hi>Formùlae</hi> little formes <hi>deferendi</hi> of accuſing (or making complaint on) <hi>diſcipùlum</hi> a ſcholler <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>praeceptórem</hi> the maſter. <hi>Chatiſsìme</hi> moſt deare <hi>praeceptor</hi> maiſter <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn <hi>exhìbet</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>mihi</hi> to mée <hi>negotium</hi> buſineſſe (putteth me to trouble.) <hi>Eſt</hi> he is <hi>moleſtus</hi> troubleſome <hi>mihi</hi> to me. <hi>Non ſinit</hi> he letteth not alone <hi>me</hi> me, <hi>Trudit</hi> he truſteth <hi>me</hi> mée. <hi>Premit</hi> he preſſeth (or ſquiſeth) <hi>me</hi> mée. <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn <hi>illúdit</hi> mocketh at <hi>mihi</hi> mée. <hi>Objécit</hi> hée hath laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>mihi</hi> me <hi>pedem</hi> his foot <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>cadèrem</hi> I night fall. <hi>Convellit</hi> he pulleth off <hi>capillos</hi> the haires <hi>mihi</hi> from me (be pulleth off my haires.) <hi>Non ſinit</hi> he ſuffereth not <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>tranſíre</hi> to paſſe away (or by.) <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbat</hi> he diſturbeth <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>ſcribentem</hi> writing <hi>ediſcentem</hi> learning by heart <hi>relegentem</hi> reading ouer (or againe) <hi>lectiónem</hi> the leſſon. <hi>Occùpat</hi> he keepeth by force (or withholdeth) <hi>meum</hi> my <hi>locum</hi> place. <hi>Extrúdit</hi> he thruu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth out <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>ex</hi> from <hi>meo</hi> my <hi>loco</hi> place. <hi>Percuſſit</hi> he hath ſmitten <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>baculo</hi> with a ſtaffe <hi>atramentario</hi> with an Inckhorne, <hi>pugno</hi> with the fiſt. <hi>Impégit</hi> he hath daſhed <hi>colàphum</hi> a buffet <hi>mihi</hi> on me, (he hath giuen me a blow on the cheeke.) <hi>conjé cit</hi> he hath hurled (or caſt forth) <hi>in</hi> on (or againſt) <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>librum</hi> a booke <hi>lapìdem</hi> a ſtone <hi>nivem</hi> ſnow. <hi>Petiit</hi> he hath ſtriken <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>lapìde</hi> with a ſtone. <hi>Vulnerávit</hi> he hath wounded <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>gladio</hi> with a ſword <hi>cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tello</hi> with a knife. <hi>Conſpuit</hi> he hath all to beſpit <hi>meum</hi> my <hi>pallium</hi> cloake <hi>veſtimentum</hi> rayment <hi>veſtem</hi> veſture (or garment.) <hi>Imprecá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus eſt</hi> he hath curſed <hi>mihi</hi> me. <hi>Maledixit</hi> he hath ſpoken ill <hi>mihi</hi> to me. <hi>Appellávit</hi> he hath termed (or called) <hi>me</hi> me <hi>ignominióſo</hi> by a nicke (or reproachfull) <hi>nomìne</hi> name. <hi>Comminátus eſt</hi> he hath threatened <hi>mihi</hi> me <hi>gravìter</hi> grieuouſly. <hi>Calumniátur</hi> he falſly and malitiouſly accuſeth <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>petulanter</hi> impudently. <hi>Diſcerpſit</hi> he hath tore in peeces <hi>aduſſit</hi> he hath burnt <hi>meum</hi> my <hi>librum</hi> booke. <hi>Commaculávit</hi> he hath all to beſtained <hi>meum</hi> my <hi>libellum</hi> little booke <hi>pileum</hi> cap <hi>pile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>òlum</hi> little cap. <hi>Debet</hi> he oweth <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>pecuniam</hi> money <hi>denari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> a pennie. <hi>Non vult</hi> he will not <hi>perſolvère</hi> pay truly (or all) <hi>red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dère</hi> reſtore <hi>ſolvère</hi> pay <hi>mihi</hi> to me. <hi>Conſùle</hi> the Conſull <hi>Senatóre</hi> the Senatour <hi>concionatóre</hi> the Preacher <hi>tranſeunte</hi> paſſing along (or by) <hi>non aperuit</hi> he vncouered not <hi>caput</hi> his head. <hi>Non praebuit</hi> he hath not wed (or yéelded) <hi>ſe</hi> himſelfe <hi>obedientem</hi> obedient <hi>parentibus</hi> to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:980:7"/>
his parents. <hi>Excuſatio</hi> the excuſe. <hi>Res</hi> the matter <hi>non</hi> not <hi>habet</hi> hath <hi>ſe</hi> it ſelfe <hi>ita</hi> ſo (the matter is not ſo) <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn <hi>mentítur</hi> lyeth. <hi>Petrus</hi> Peter <hi>odit</hi> hateth <hi>me</hi> me. <hi>Male</hi> euilly <hi>vult</hi> he willeth <hi>mihi</hi> to me (he beareth me ill will,) <hi>ideo</hi> therefore <hi>comminiſcitur</hi> he faigneth <hi>haec</hi> theſe things <hi>in</hi> againſt <hi>me</hi> mee. <hi>Non laeſi</hi> I haue not hurt <hi>cum</hi> him. <hi>Non attigi</hi> I haue not touched <hi>ipſum</hi> him <hi>digìto</hi> with my finger. <hi>Feci</hi> I haue done it <hi>non volens</hi> not willing. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ci</hi> I haue done it <hi>per</hi> through <hi>imprudentiam</hi> not thinking thereof (vnawares.) <hi>Non</hi> not <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>in</hi> againſt <hi>illum</hi> him <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>ille</hi> hee <hi>in</hi> againſt <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>delìquit</hi> hath done an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffence (or committed a fault of omiſſion.) <hi>Paenìtet</hi> it irketh <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>facti</hi> of the fact. <hi>Paenìtet</hi> it repenteth <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>íllorum</hi> of thoſe things <hi>quae</hi> which <hi>deliqui</hi> I haue committed <hi>in</hi> againſt <hi>Petrum</hi> Peter. <hi>Deinceps</hi> henceforth <hi>faciam</hi> I will doe <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>tale</hi> ſuch (no ſuch thing) <hi>non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit</hi> there hath not béene <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>otium</hi> leaſure <hi>ſcribendi</hi> to write <hi>diſcendi</hi> to learne <hi>haec</hi> theſe things. <hi>Propter</hi> by reaſon of <hi>oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupationes</hi> neceſſary buſineſſes <hi>non potui</hi> I haue not béene able (or I could not) <hi>adeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> be preſent. <hi>Promitto</hi> I promiſe, <hi>pollíceor</hi> I aſſure you of <hi>melióra</hi> better things. <hi>Vbi</hi> where <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>pater</hi> father, <hi>mater</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>praeceptor,</hi> maiſter, <hi>neſcio</hi> I am ignorant thereof, <hi>non ſcio</hi> I know not. <hi>Eſt</hi> hee is <hi>in</hi> in <hi>muſaeo</hi> the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dy, <hi>penu</hi> the buttry, <hi>vel</hi> or <hi>promptuario</hi> the victuals-ſtorehouſe, <hi>aeſtuario</hi> the hotehouſe, <hi>latrina</hi> the priuie houſe, <hi>ſtab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lo</hi> the ſtable, <hi>bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o</hi> the bath, <hi>horto</hi> the garden, <hi>cul ma</hi> the kitchin, <hi>cubicùlo</hi> the bed chamber, <hi>ſuperióri</hi> in the vpper <hi>parte</hi> part <hi>aedium</hi> of the houſe, <hi>hoc eſt</hi> that is, <hi>caenacùlo</hi> in the garret, <hi>tabulato</hi> in the loft, <hi>ſeu</hi> or <hi>contignatióne</hi> in the boorded floure (the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether raftering or plancking) <hi>aedium</hi> of the houſe. <hi>Cellario</hi> the cellar, <hi>templo</hi> the temple. <hi>Non eſt</hi> he is not <hi>domi</hi> at home. <hi>Egreſſus eſt</hi> he is gone forth <hi>extra</hi> without <hi>fores</hi> doore (or doores) <hi>vrbe</hi> out of the citie, <hi>ex</hi> out of <hi>aedibus</hi> the houſe. <hi>Formùlae</hi> the manners (or faſhions) <hi>agendi</hi> of ſpeaking (talking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> treating) <hi>cum</hi> with <hi>condiſcipùlis</hi> ſchoole-fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes. <hi>Accéde</hi> approach, <hi>veni</hi> come <hi>huc</hi> hither <hi>Petre</hi> O Peter. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſte</hi> ſtop, <hi>mane</hi> ſtay <hi>pauliſper</hi> a little while. <hi>Habeo</hi> I haue ſomewhat <hi>quod</hi> which <hi>dicam</hi> I ſhall tell <hi>tibi</hi> to thée. (I haue ſomewhat to ſay to thée.) <hi>Eſt</hi> there is ſomewhat <hi>quod</hi> which <hi>rogem</hi> I may aſke (or muſt aſke or requeſt) <hi>te</hi> thée. <hi>Eſt</hi> there is ſomething <hi>quod</hi> which <hi>petam</hi> I ſhall (or will) craue a of <hi>te</hi> thee. <hi>Rogo</hi> I requeſt <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>excúſes</hi> thou excuſeſt <hi>me</hi> me, (makeſt excuſe for me) <hi>abſentiae</hi> of abſence <hi>apud</hi> with (or before) <hi>praeceptórem</hi> the maiſter. <hi>Nam</hi> for <hi>ſum</hi> I am <hi>occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pátus</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:980:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
occupied <hi>certis</hi> in determined <hi>negotijs</hi> buſineſſes <hi>quo</hi> whereby <hi>fit</hi> it commeth to paſſe <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>nune</hi> now <hi>non poſſim</hi> I cannot <hi>eſſe</hi> be <hi>in ſchola</hi> in the ſchoole. <hi>Faciam</hi> I will doe it <hi>libenter</hi> gladly. <hi>Expediam</hi> I will diſpatch it <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>ea</hi> vpon this <hi>conditione</hi> condition <hi>vt</hi> that et al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>facias</hi> doeſt <hi>idem</hi> the ſame thing <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ortè</hi> peraduenture <hi>erit</hi> there ſhall be <hi>opus</hi> néede <hi>mihi</hi> to me. <hi>Interpretáre</hi> interpret <hi>haec</hi> theſe things (or words) <hi>mihi</hi> to me. <hi>Quantum</hi> how much <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>pronunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andum</hi> to be ſaid <hi>nobis</hi> of vs <hi>memorìter</hi> by heart <hi>prima</hi> in (or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the firſt) <hi>hora</hi> houre <hi>ſecunda</hi> at the ſecond (at one a clocke at two) <hi>haec</hi> theſe things <hi>ſunt</hi> are <hi>recitanda</hi> to be recited <hi>nobis</hi> of vs <hi>memorìter</hi> by heart (without looking in the booke, from the memorie onely.) <hi>Audí</hi> heare <hi>me</hi> me <hi>pronúnciantem</hi> ſaying ouer <hi>memoriter</hi> by heart <hi>quae</hi> what things <hi>debémus</hi> we ought <hi>ſcire</hi> to know, <hi>poſtea</hi> afterward <hi>audiam</hi> I will hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>viciſſim</hi> againe for my part. <hi>Abberras</hi> thou miſſeſt <hi>pronunciando</hi> in pronouncing (or ſaying ouer.) <hi>Legis</hi> thou readeſt <hi>malè</hi> badly. <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſay <hi>ſenſim</hi> leaſurely. <hi>Ne praecipìtes</hi> poſt not vp (or huddle not vp, or vtter not raſhly) <hi>verba</hi> thy words. <hi>In</hi> in <hi>loquendo</hi> ſpeaking <hi>eſt</hi> it is <hi>ſatiùs</hi> better <hi>peccáte</hi> to offend (or doe amiſſe) <hi>tarditáte</hi> with ſlowneſſe <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>celeritáte</hi> with haſtineſſe (or ſwiftneſſe.) <hi>Verba</hi> words <hi>debent</hi> ought <hi>naſci</hi> to be bred <hi>in pectòre</hi> in the breaſt <hi>non</hi> not <hi>in ore</hi> in the mouth. <hi>Sis</hi> be <hi>praeſenti</hi> of a bolde (or ſtrong) <hi>anìmo</hi> ſpirit (or conrage) <hi>metus</hi> feare <hi>officit</hi> hurteth <hi>memoriae</hi> the memorie. <hi>Claude</hi> ſhut <hi>librum</hi> the booke, <hi>libellum</hi> the little booke. <hi>Fidendum eſt</hi> one muſt truſt <hi>memoriae</hi> to his memory, <hi>non</hi> not <hi>libris</hi> to his bookes. <hi>Quiſque</hi> euery one <hi>ſcit</hi> knoweth <hi>tantùm</hi> ſo much <hi>quantùm</hi> as <hi>memoria</hi> the memory <hi>tenet</hi> holdeth (or kéepeth in it:) <hi>vnde</hi> from whence <hi>faciam</hi> ſhall I make <hi>initium</hi> beginning. <hi>Incipe</hi> begin <hi>vbi</hi> where <hi>deſijſti</hi> thou made<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t an end <hi>proxìmè</hi> laſt. <hi>Ne</hi> whether <hi>placet</hi> pleaſeth it (or thinke you it good) <hi>certare</hi> to contend (or try a maſterie) <hi>mecum</hi> with mee <hi>pingendis</hi> in writing (or drawing out the forme of) <hi>litèris</hi> letters. <hi>Quidem</hi> indéede <hi>placet</hi> I am well content <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>deeſt</hi> there is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>charta</hi> paper <hi>penna</hi> a penne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>atram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntum</hi> inke. <hi>Da</hi> giue <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>paulùlum</hi> a little <hi>de</hi> of <hi>tua</hi> thy <hi>charta</hi> paper <hi>atramento</hi> inke. <hi>Cuius</hi> whoſe <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>liber</hi> the booke. <hi>Eſt</hi> it is <hi>meus</hi> mine. <hi>Eſt</hi> it is <hi>Petri</hi> Peters. <hi>Redde</hi> reſtore <hi>tandem</hi> at the length (or at the laſt) <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>meum</hi> my <hi>librum</hi> booke, <hi>vſus es</hi> thou haſt vſed <hi>eo</hi> it <hi>ſatis</hi> enough. <hi>Desine</hi> ceaſe (or leaue off) <hi>fabulari</hi> to talke fooliſhly. <hi>Deſiſte</hi> ſurceaſe <hi>ridère</hi> to laugh. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> the maiſter <hi>aduènit</hi> commeth, <hi>adeſt</hi> is at hand.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:980:8"/>
               <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>libri</hi> booke <hi>habes</hi> haſt thou? <hi>Eſt</hi> it is <hi>Grammatica</hi> a Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar. <hi>Fac</hi> graunt <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>copiam</hi> leaue <hi>inſpiciendi</hi> to looke into <hi>tui</hi> thy <hi>libelli</hi> little booke <hi>parumper</hi> a little while. <hi>Tace</hi> hold thy peace, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>fac</hi> doe <hi>quae</hi> what things <hi>ſunt</hi> are <hi>mandáta</hi> enioyned (or giuen in charge) <hi>tibi</hi> to thée. <hi>Offendis</hi> thou offendeſt <hi>non</hi> not <hi>tam</hi> as much <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptóres</hi> maiſters <hi>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> as <hi>Deum</hi> God <hi>ipſum</hi> himſelfe <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>non obtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pèras</hi> thou obeyeſt not. <hi>Licèt</hi> although <hi>praeceptor</hi> the maiſter <hi>abſit</hi> be abſent <hi>tamen</hi> yet notwithſtanding <hi>Deus</hi> God <hi>adeſt</hi> is preſent <hi>qui</hi> which <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it</hi> knoweth <hi>et</hi> and <hi>intuétur</hi> beholdeth <hi>omnia</hi> all things. <hi>Noto</hi> I note (or accuſe) <hi>te</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>vernacùli</hi> of naturall (or mother) <hi>ſermónis</hi> ſpeach <hi>ſolaeciſmi</hi> of incongruity <hi>barbariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of barbariſme. <hi>Loquère</hi> ſpeake <hi>Latínè</hi> in Latine, <hi>Graecè</hi> in Gréeke. <hi>Vtère</hi> vſe <hi>ſermóne</hi> ſpéech, <hi>Latíno</hi> Latine, <hi>Graeco</hi> Greeke. <hi>An</hi> whether <hi>ignó<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as</hi> art thou ignorant <hi>Latí<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> that the Latine, <hi>Graecum</hi> that the Greeke <hi>ſermónem</hi> ſpeech <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parári</hi> is gotten <hi>loquendo</hi> by ſpeaking <hi>Latínè</hi> in Latine, <hi>Graece</hi> in Greeke? <hi>Fruſtra</hi> in vaine <hi>diſcìmus</hi> we learne <hi>multa</hi> many things, <hi>niſi</hi> except <hi>transferìmus</hi> we transferre <hi>eàdem</hi> the ſame things <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum</hi> vſe <hi>ſcribendo</hi> by writing <hi>et</hi> and <hi>loquendo</hi> by ſpeaking. <hi>Accende</hi> kindle <hi>mihi</hi> for mee <hi>hanc</hi> this <hi>candèlam</hi> candle. <hi>Adfer</hi> bring <hi>candelá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum</hi> a candleſtick, <hi>laternam</hi> a lanterne. <hi>Emunge</hi> ſnuffe, <hi>purga</hi> ſcoure (or make cleane) <hi>candélam</hi> the candle. <hi>Strue</hi> make (or frame) <hi>ignem</hi> a fire <hi>in</hi> in <hi>fornáce</hi> the fornace, <hi>foco</hi> the harth, <hi>camíno</hi> the chimney. <hi>Compóne</hi> put together, <hi>protrúde</hi> thruſt forward <hi>titiónes</hi> the fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands <hi>in</hi> in <hi>fornáce</hi> the fornace. <hi>Appóne</hi> put vnto <hi>plùs</hi> more <hi>aſſulá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> chips (or of the ſplinters) <hi>plus</hi> more <hi>lignórum</hi> wood (or woods.) <hi>Alius</hi> another <hi>dialogus</hi> dialogue. <hi>Quis</hi> who <hi>pulſat</hi> knocketh <hi>oſtium</hi> the doore? <hi>Ego</hi> I <hi>ſum</hi> am he. <hi>Quis</hi> who is <hi>ego</hi> the I? <hi>Ede</hi> vtter (or tell) <hi>tuum</hi> thy <hi>nomen</hi> name <hi>quod</hi> what <hi>nomen</hi> name <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>tibi</hi> to thee? <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes</hi> Iohn <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>nomen</hi> the name <hi>mihi</hi> to me. <hi>Intromitte</hi> let in <hi>me</hi> me. <hi>Apè<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i</hi> open <hi>januam</hi> the gate. <hi>Ianua</hi> the gate <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>aperta</hi> opened. <hi>Quiſpiam</hi> a certaine perſon <hi>quaeſívit</hi> hath ſought for <hi>te</hi> thee. <hi>Quidam</hi> one (or ſome perſon) <hi>ſtans</hi> ſtanding <hi>pro</hi> at (or before) <hi>foribus</hi> the doore (or doores) <hi>expè<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it</hi> deſireth (or craueth) <hi>conventum</hi> to ſpeake with <hi>te</hi> thee. <hi>Ne</hi> whether <hi>dicis</hi> ſayeſt thou <hi>iſtud</hi> this <hi>ſeriò</hi> in earneſt <hi>an</hi> or <hi>jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o</hi> in ieaſt? <hi>Dico</hi> I ſpeake <hi>extra</hi> without <hi>jocum</hi> ieaſt. <hi>Non jocor</hi> I ieaſt not <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>ago</hi> I doe (or tell) <hi>ſeria</hi> matters in earneſt. <hi>Ob</hi> for <hi>quam</hi> what <hi>cauſam</hi> cauſe, <hi>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> why <hi>fles</hi> doeſt thou weepe? <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>mali</hi> euill <hi>accìdit</hi> hath happened <hi>tibi</hi> to thee? <hi>Caeſus ſum</hi> I haue beene
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:980:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
beaten. <hi>Dedi poenas</hi> I haue beene puniſhed <hi>praeceptóri</hi> of (or by) the maiſter. <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>mali</hi> euill <hi>fecèras</hi> hadſt thou done? <hi>Nihil</hi> none (or nothing.) <hi>Haec</hi> this <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>commúnis</hi> the common <hi>reſponſio</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere <hi>omnium</hi> of all <hi>puerórum</hi> boyes, <hi>etiam</hi> yea <hi>cum</hi> when <hi>vapulárunt</hi> they haue beene beaten <hi>meritò</hi> deſeruedly. <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>controuerſiae</hi> controuerſie <hi>eſt</hi> is there <hi>inter</hi> among <hi>vos</hi> you? <hi>Referámus</hi> let vs make relation <hi>de</hi> concerning <hi>haec</hi> this <hi>controuerſia</hi> controuerſie (or vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>hypodidaſcàlum</hi> the vnder-teacher (or vther. <hi>Ne</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>affers</hi> bringeſt thou <hi>libellum</hi> the little booke <hi>quem</hi> which <hi>dedèr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> I had giuen <hi>commodáto</hi> for loanth (I had lended) <hi>tibi</hi> to thee. <hi>Vah</hi> O wonderfull <hi>iſtud</hi> that thing <hi>excidèrat</hi> had ſcaped <hi>mihi</hi> me (had ſlipped o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of my remembrance) <hi>omníno</hi> quite or altogether. <hi>Non incìdit</hi> it happened not <hi>mihi</hi> to me (it came not into my minde) <hi>cum</hi> when <hi>exí<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem</hi> I went out <hi>domo</hi> from home. <hi>Certò</hi> ſurely <hi>affèram</hi> I will bring it <hi>hodie</hi> to day <hi>cras</hi> to morrow. <hi>Cujus</hi> to whom <hi>eſt</hi> doth it appertaine <hi>nunc</hi> now <hi>miniſtráre</hi> to ſerue (or deliuer) <hi>nobis</hi> to vs <hi>candélam</hi> a candle <hi>quem</hi> whom <hi>oportet</hi> doth it behooue <hi>nunc</hi> now <hi>emère</hi> to buy <hi>ligna</hi> wood (or woods.) <hi>Cujus</hi> to whom <hi>eſt</hi> doth it belong <hi>verrère</hi> to ſweepe, <hi>purgáre</hi> to make cleane <hi>muſaeum</hi> the ſtudy. <hi>Eſt</hi> it is <hi>meum</hi> my d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty, <hi>tuum</hi> thy duty, <hi>Iohannis</hi> Iohns. <hi>Scopae</hi> a beeſome <hi>deſunt</hi> is wanting <hi>mihi</hi> to me. <hi>Egeo</hi> I want <hi>ſcopis</hi> a broome. <hi>Sterne</hi> ſpread (or make) <hi>lectum</hi> the bed <hi>lectùlum</hi> the little bed. <hi>Accende</hi> kindle <hi>lychnum</hi> a light. <hi>Repóne</hi> lay vp <hi>libros</hi> the bookes <hi>in</hi> into <hi>ſuum</hi> their <hi>locum</hi> place. <hi>Alius</hi> another. <hi>Quid</hi> why <hi>es</hi> art thou <hi>triſtior</hi> ſadder <hi>ſolìto</hi> than wont (or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed.) <hi>Ne</hi> whether <hi>res</hi> the matter <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>ſalva</hi> in good caſe (doth all goe well) <hi>perdìdi</hi> I haue loſt <hi>meum</hi> my <hi>libellum</hi> little booke. <hi>Cecìdi</hi> I haue fallen <hi>grauìter</hi> greeuouſly. <hi>Pettus</hi> Peter <hi>minátus eſt</hi> hath threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>verbèra</hi> blowes. <hi>Quid</hi> why <hi>es</hi> are you <hi>tam</hi> ſo <hi>laetus</hi> merry? (or glad) <hi>quia</hi> becauſe <hi>copia</hi> leaue <hi>facta eſt</hi> is graunted (or cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) <hi>nobis</hi> to (or for vs) <hi>abeundi</hi> to depart <hi>domum</hi> home. <hi>Venia</hi> leaue <hi>ludendi</hi> to play <hi>datà eſt</hi> is giuen <hi>nobis</hi> to vs. <hi>Ad</hi> at <hi>quotam</hi> what (or what number of) <hi>horam</hi> houre <hi>ſumus</hi> are we <hi>iuſſi</hi> commaunded <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>díre</hi> to returne <hi>in</hi> into <hi>ſcholam</hi> the ſchoole? <hi>ad</hi> at <hi>horam</hi> the houre <hi>ſextam</hi> ſixth, <hi>octávam</hi> eighth, <hi>decimam</hi> tenth, <hi>duodecìmam</hi> twelfth, <hi>ſecundam</hi> ſecond, <hi>quartam</hi> fourth, <hi>ſeptìmam</hi> ſeuenth, <hi>nonam</hi> ninth, <hi>vndecìmam</hi> eleuenth, <hi>primam</hi> firſt, <hi>tertiam</hi> third, <hi>quintam</hi> fifth: <hi>Quo</hi> whither <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis</hi> goeſt thou <hi>nunc</hi> now? <hi>eo</hi> I goe <hi>domum</hi> home. <hi>Abeo</hi> I goe (or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part) <hi>emptum</hi> to buy <hi>papírum</hi> paper, <hi>atramentum</hi> inke, <hi>pennas</hi> pennes,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:980:9"/>
               <hi>criticeum</hi> wheaten <hi>panem</hi> bread. <hi>Vbi</hi> where <hi>eſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> is <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn? <hi>exív ít</hi> he went out <hi>foras</hi> abroad <hi>ſchola</hi> from ſchoole <hi>ad</hi> for <hi>requíſita</hi> the needes <hi>natúrae</hi> of nature. <hi>Egreſſus eſt</hi> he went forth <hi>è</hi> out of <hi>literari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the learning <hi>ludo</hi> ſchoole <hi>cauſa</hi> for the cauſe <hi>reddendae</hi> of making <hi>vrínae</hi> vrine (or water.) <hi>Quanti</hi> for how much <hi>mercétus es</hi> haſt thou bought <hi>hunc</hi> this <hi>libellum</hi> little book. <hi>Emi</hi> I haue bought it <hi>tribus</hi> for three <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narijs</hi> penre, <hi>quatuor</hi> for foure <hi>aureis</hi> crownes (or nobles) <hi>quinque</hi> for fiue <hi>drach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is</hi> groates <hi>à</hi> of <hi>bibliop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la</hi> the bookeſeller. <hi>Emiſti</hi> thou haſt bought <hi>parvo</hi> for a ſmal <hi>precio</hi> price, <hi>nimio</hi> for too much (or ouermuch.) <hi>Nemo</hi> no body <hi>divendit</hi> ſelleth forth (or abroad) <hi>vendit</hi> ſelleth <hi>alio</hi> for another <hi>Precio</hi> price (at another rate.) <hi>Formùlae</hi> manners (or formes) <hi>commodandi</hi> of lending. <hi>Commòda</hi> lend <hi>pennam</hi> a penne <hi>acum</hi> a needle <hi>cum</hi> with <hi>filo</hi> a threed <hi>librum</hi> a booke. <hi>Non poſſum</hi> I cannot <hi>carére</hi> be without it (or lacke it) <hi>nunc</hi> now. <hi>Ipſe</hi> I my ſelfe <hi>nunc</hi> now <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or</hi> doe vſe <hi>eo</hi> it. <hi>Commodabo</hi> I will lend it <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>ea</hi> with this (or on this) <hi>lege</hi> condition <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>reſtituas</hi> thou reſtore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it <hi>mihi</hi> to mee <hi>ſalvum</hi> without hurt (or ſafe) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>matúrè</hi> timely (or quickly) <hi>ne</hi> leaſt that (or that not) <hi>ipſe</hi> I my ſelfe <hi>egeam</hi> neede it <hi>cum</hi> when <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit</hi> it ſhall be, <hi>vtendum</hi> to be vſed <hi>mihi</hi> of me (I muſt vſe it) or I ſhall be to vſe it) <hi>en</hi> behold <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abes</hi> thou haſt it <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>vide</hi> take heede (or ſée thou) <hi>ne</hi> that not <hi>commacùles</hi> thou ſtaine it <hi>aſpergas</hi> thou beſprinkle it <hi>labecùlis</hi> with little ſpots. <hi>Mens</hi> my <hi>praeceptor</hi> maiſter <hi>rogat</hi> reque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>mittas</hi> you ſend <hi>ſibi</hi> to him <hi>Graecum</hi> a Gréeks <hi>Teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> Taſtament <hi>vtendum</hi> to vſe (or to be vſed) <hi>in</hi> for <hi>breue</hi> a ſhort <hi>tempus</hi> time. <hi>Non poſſum</hi> I cannot <hi>commodáre</hi> lend it <hi>ei</hi> to him <hi>in praeſentia</hi> at this preſent (or for this preſent time.) <hi>Mutuári</hi> to borrow. <hi>Cogor</hi> I am conſtrained <hi>mutuári</hi> to borrow <hi>pecuniam</hi> money <hi>ad</hi> to <hi>emendas</hi> buy <hi>veſtes</hi> garments. <hi>Oro</hi> I pray <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>des</hi> thou giueſt (or granteſt) <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>mutuo</hi> for (or vnto) lone (thou lendeſt) <hi>denarium</hi> a peny <hi>candèlam</hi> a candle, <hi>chartam</hi> a leafe (or ſhéete) <hi>papíri</hi> of paper <hi>pete</hi> aſke thou <hi>ab</hi> of <hi>quodam</hi> ſome <hi>alio</hi> other <hi>enim</hi> for <hi>vix</hi> ſcarce <hi>ſuffìcit</hi> there is ſufficient <hi>mihi ipſi</hi> for my ſelfe. <hi>Alius</hi> another. <hi>Quota</hi> of what number <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>hora</hi> the houre (what is the clocke) <hi>prima</hi> the firſt, <hi>ſecunda</hi> the ſecond, <hi>tertia</hi> the third, <hi>quarta</hi> the fourth, <hi>quinta</hi> the fifth. <hi>Decìma</hi> the tenth <hi>hora</hi> houre <hi>immìnet</hi> is very néere (it is vpon the ſtroke of ten a clocke.) <hi>Septìma</hi> the ſeauenth <hi>octáva</hi> the eighth <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> houre <hi>effluxit</hi> is cleane gone <hi>praeterijt</hi> is paſt. <hi>Non numerávi</hi> I haue not tolde (or reckoned) <hi>horas</hi> the houres. <hi>Horologium</hi> the clock <hi>aberrat</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:980:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
goeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>iſſé. <hi>Aberras</hi> thou erreſt (or miſſeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>numerando</hi> in telling (or numbring.) <hi>Clepſammon</hi> the houreglaſſe, <hi>ſubſiſtit</hi> ſtandeth ſtill. <hi>Move</hi> wagge <hi>clepſammon</hi> the houre-glaſſe? <hi>Emenda</hi> amend (or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect) <hi>meam</hi> mine <hi>Epiſtòlam</hi> Epiſtle. <hi>Meum</hi> my <hi>ſcriptum</hi> writing. <hi>Meos</hi> my <hi>verſus</hi> verſes. <hi>Rogo</hi> I requeſt <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> thée <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>relègas</hi> thou reads ouer (or againe) <hi>meum</hi> my <hi>ſcriptum</hi> writing <hi>et</hi> and <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendèris</hi> thou ſhalt finde out (or eſpie) <hi>quid</hi> any <hi>erráti</hi> fault <hi>tollas</hi> thou take away (or put it out.) <hi>Formùlae</hi> formes <hi>rogandi</hi> of intreating <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptórem</hi> the maiſter. <hi>Nunc</hi> now <hi>aer</hi> the ayre <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>ſerénus</hi> cleare (without cloudes or raine) (now it is faire weather.) <hi>Coelum</hi> the heauen <hi>invitat</hi> inuiteth <hi>ad ludendum</hi> to play. <hi>Exeámus</hi> let vs goe forth <hi>luſum</hi> to play <hi>vel</hi> or <hi>ad ludendum</hi> to play. <hi>Nou licet</hi> it is not lawfull <hi>ludère</hi> to play <hi>abſque</hi> without <hi>venia</hi> leaue. <hi>Quiſpiam</hi> ſomebody <hi>eſt is <hi>mittendus</hi> to be ſent <hi>qui</hi> who <hi>impètrat</hi> may obtaine by requeſt <hi>nobis</hi> for vs <hi>veniam</hi> leaue <hi>ludendi</hi> to play. <hi>Paulus</hi> Paul <hi>éat</hi> may goe (or let Paul goe) <hi>nam eſt</hi> he is <hi>benè</hi> well <hi>linguax</hi> tongued (one well able to tell his tale) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>audax</hi> bold. <hi>Nemo</hi> no body <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>magis</hi> more <hi>ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> fit <hi>ad</hi> vnto (or for) <hi>hanc</hi> this <hi>legatiónem</hi> embaſſage (or meſſage) <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>Petrus</hi> Peter. <hi>Petre</hi> O Peter í goe thou <hi>orátum</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate <hi>nobis</hi> for vs <hi>veniam</hi> leaue <hi>ludendi</hi> to play. <hi>Eat</hi> let him goe <hi>qui</hi> which <hi>volet</hi> will (or ſhall be willing) <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>malo</hi> leifer <hi>carére</hi> be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out (or want) <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>rogáre</hi> aſke. <hi>Quaeſo</hi> I beſéech i goe thou <hi>initúrus</hi> to enter in (or get) <hi>magnam</hi> great <hi>gratiam</hi> fauour <hi>ab</hi> of <hi>omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> all <hi>nobis</hi> vs (to currie much friendſhip at our hands.) <hi>Quando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quìdem</hi> for as much as <hi>contendìtis</hi> you requeſt (or require) <hi>id</hi> this matter <hi>tantopère</hi> ſo earneſtly <hi>obſèquar</hi> I will obay <hi>veſtris</hi> your <hi>precì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> intreaties. <hi>Salve</hi> haile et alſo <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>Petre</hi> O Peter. <hi>Tui</hi> your <hi>diſcipùli</hi> ſchollers <hi>orant</hi> doe intreate of <hi>tuam</hi> your <hi>humanitátem</hi> courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie (or gentleneſſe) <hi>veniam</hi> leaue <hi>ludendi</hi> to play. <hi>Praeceptor</hi> the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. <hi>Ludant</hi> let them play <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>gregàtim</hi> in companies <hi>in loco</hi> in the place <hi>conſtitúto</hi> appointed <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>id</hi> it (thereunto) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>recipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant</hi> let them betake <hi>ſe</hi> themſelues <hi>domum</hi> home <hi>matúrè</hi> in ſeaſon. <hi>Sub</hi> about (or at) <hi>quintam</hi> the fift <hi>horam</hi> houre (fiue a clocke) <hi>redeant</hi> let them returne <hi>in</hi> into <hi>vrbem</hi> the Citie. <hi>Puer</hi> the boy. <hi>Simus</hi> let vs be <hi>hilàres</hi> frollique, <hi>impetrávi</hi> I haue by requeſt obtained <hi>veniam</hi> leaue <hi>quanquam</hi> although <hi>aegrè</hi> hardly (or with much adoe.) <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>intè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim</hi> in the meane time <hi>cavendum eſt</hi> we mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t beware <hi>ne</hi> leaſt that <hi>peccémus</hi> we do amiſſe <hi>quid</hi> any thing (leaſt ſomwhat we doe amiſſe) <hi>conſultabìmus</hi> we will conſult <hi>de</hi> of (or concerning) <hi>genère</hi> the kinde
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:980:10"/>
                  <hi>luſus</hi> of the play <hi>in campo</hi> in the plaine field. <hi>Formûlae</hi> formes <hi>collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendi</hi> of communing <hi>cum</hi> with <hi>condiſcipùlis</hi> ſchoole-fellowes. <hi>Vnde</hi> whence <hi>venis</hi> commeſt thou <hi>tam</hi> ſo <hi>mane</hi> early in the morning? <hi>ex</hi> out of <hi>noſtro</hi> our <hi>cubicùlo</hi> bed-chamber. <hi>Quando</hi> when <hi>ſurrexiſti</hi> aroſeſt thou? <hi>Paulò</hi> a little <hi>ante</hi> before <hi>ſextam</hi> the ſixth <hi>horam</hi> houre (ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a clocke.) <hi>Quis</hi> who <hi>excitá vit</hi> wakened (or ſtirred vp) <hi>te</hi> thée. <hi>Pater</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>Mater</hi> mother. <hi>Frater</hi> brother. <hi>Soror</hi> ſiſter. <hi>Adoraſti</hi> haſt thou prayed vnto (or worſhipped) <hi>Deum</hi> God? <hi>Egiſti</hi> haſt thou done (or giuen) <hi>gratias</hi> thankes <hi>Deo</hi> to God. <hi>Quum primùm</hi> as ſoone as <hi>pexui</hi> I kembed (or had kembed) <hi>crines</hi> my haire (or haires) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>laui</hi> waſhed <hi>manus</hi> hands, <hi>faciem</hi> face, <hi>ac</hi> and <hi>os</hi> mouth <hi>precátus ſum</hi> I prayed. <hi>Quomodo</hi> how <hi>precátus es</hi> prayeſt thou? <hi>genìbus</hi> my knées (or with my knees) <hi>flexis</hi> bowed (or bended, knéeling on my knées.) <hi>Et</hi> and <hi>manibus</hi> my hands <hi>coniunctis</hi> ioyned together (holding vp my hands together) <hi>recitávi</hi> I ſaid by heart (or recited) <hi>decalògum</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue (or ten commandements) <hi>Apoſtolìcum</hi> the Apoſtles <hi>ſymbò<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum</hi> creede, <hi>Dominicam</hi> the Lords <hi>oratiónem</hi> prayer <hi>et</hi> and <hi>addìdi</hi> I added <hi>notam</hi> a famous (or familiar) <hi>precatiónem</hi> prayer <hi>cum</hi> with <hi>actióne</hi> a doing (or giuing) <hi>gratiárum</hi> of thankes (a thankeſgiuing.) <hi>Qua</hi> in what <hi>lingua</hi> tongue (or language) <hi>ſoles</hi> art thou wont <hi>precári</hi> to pray <hi>aliàs</hi> ſometimes <hi>vernacùla</hi> in my motherne (or naturall) <hi>aliàs</hi> other-whiles <hi>Latina</hi> in the Latine <hi>nonnunquam</hi> ſometimes <hi>etiam</hi> alſo <hi>Graeca</hi> in the Greeke. <hi>Chare</hi> O well beloued <hi>puer</hi> boy <hi>facis</hi> thou doeſt <hi>piè</hi> godlily <hi>et</hi> and <hi>rectè</hi> rightly (or well.) <hi>Cura</hi> haue a care <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>nunquam</hi> neuer <hi>neglìgas</hi> tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neglecteſt <hi>hanc</hi> this <hi>partem</hi> part <hi>tui</hi> of thy <hi>officij</hi> duty. <hi>Dabo</hi> I will giue <hi>opèram</hi> endeauour <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dùlo</hi> diligently <hi>Deo</hi> God <hi>dante</hi> graunting <hi>memor</hi> mindfull <hi>dicti</hi> of the ſaying <hi>Chriſti</hi> of Chriſt <hi>ſine</hi> without <hi>me</hi> me <hi>poteſtis</hi> y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e can (or can be able) <hi>facère</hi> to doe <hi>nihil</hi> nothing. <hi>Item</hi> alſo (or likewiſe) <hi>oportet</hi> it behooueth <hi>oráre</hi> to pray <hi>ſemper</hi> alwayes <hi>et</hi> and <hi>non</hi> not <hi>defatigári</hi> to be weary. <hi>Quò</hi> whither <hi>vadis</hi> goeſt thou? <hi>Eo</hi> I goe <hi>domum</hi> home. <hi>Ne</hi> whether <hi>es</hi> art thou <hi>parátus</hi> ready <hi>ad</hi> for <hi>reddendam</hi> to render <hi>ratiónem</hi> an account <hi>tuórum</hi> of thy <hi>ſtudiórum</hi> ſtudies? <hi>Sum</hi> I am <hi>parátus</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (or prepared) <hi>vt</hi> as <hi>videor</hi> I ſeeme <hi>mihi</hi> to my ſelfe (as me think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.) <hi>Igìtur</hi> then (or therefore) <hi>redde</hi> render <hi>ratiónem</hi> an account <hi>et</hi> and <hi>ſis</hi> be thou <hi>praeſenti</hi> of a bolde (or good) <hi>anìmo</hi> ſpirit (or courage.) <hi>Hora</hi> at the houre <hi>ſexta</hi> ſixth, <hi>ſeptìma</hi> ſeauenth, <hi>octáva</hi> eighth, <hi>audìvì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> we heard <hi>Cicerónem</hi> Cicero, <hi>Terentium</hi> Terence, <hi>Iſocràtèm</hi> Iſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:980:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>Audivìmus</hi> wee haue hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>alìquid</hi> that ſomething <hi>explicári</hi> was expounded <hi>in Epiſtòlis</hi> in the Epiſtles. <hi>Nona</hi> in the ninth <hi>hora</hi> houre <hi>exercuì<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> we practiſed <hi>ſtylum</hi> our penne (we vſed writing.) <hi>Tenes</hi> doeſt thou keepe <hi>memoria</hi> in memory <hi>praelectiónem</hi> thy leſſon? <hi>Propemòdum</hi> in a manner. <hi>Ferè</hi> almoſt. <hi>Prope</hi> well-neere. <hi>Ne</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>vis</hi> wilt thou <hi>repetámus</hi> that we repeate <hi>vnà</hi> together? <hi>Maxìmè</hi> yea, (or very greatly) <hi>velim</hi> I would (or can be willing.) <hi>Incìpe</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>igitur</hi> then. <hi>Ordíre</hi> begin thou to ſay (or begin thou.) <hi>Faciam</hi> I will doe it <hi>libenter</hi> gladly, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>auſculta</hi> hearken <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>attentè</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiuely <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>corrìgas</hi> thou maiſt correct (or amend) <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> if <hi>peccavèro</hi> I ſhall erre) or miſſe in) <hi>quid</hi> any thing. <hi>Iam</hi> already <hi>ſemel</hi> once, <hi>bis</hi> twice, <hi>ter</hi> thrice, <hi>quater</hi> foure times, <hi>quinquies</hi> fiue times, <hi>ſexies</hi> ſixe times, <hi>ſepties</hi> ſeauen times, <hi>octies</hi> eight times, <hi>novies</hi> nine times, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> ten times, <hi>erraſti</hi> thou haſt miſſed. <hi>Me</hi> O me <hi>miſèrum</hi> wretched (wretched one that I am.) <hi>Putabam</hi> I did thinke <hi>me</hi> that I <hi>tenère</hi> did retaine or keepe in memory) <hi>praeclarè</hi> right well. <hi>Idem</hi> the ſame thing <hi>et</hi> alſo <hi>ſolet</hi> is wont <hi>accidère</hi> to chaunce <hi>mihi</hi> to me <hi>cum</hi> when as <hi>memoria</hi> my memory <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>non</hi> not <hi>ſatis</hi> enough <hi>confirmáta</hi> ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened. <hi>Felix</hi> happy is he <hi>qui</hi> which <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>praedìtus</hi> endued <hi>bona</hi> with a good <hi>memoria</hi> memory. <hi>Revéra</hi> in very deede <hi>eſt</hi> it is <hi>magnum</hi> a great <hi>beneficium</hi> benefit. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>tempus</hi> the time <hi>abit</hi> paſſeth away, <hi>ìgìtur</hi> therefore <hi>et</hi> alſo <hi>audi</hi> heare thou <hi>me</hi> me <hi>nunc</hi> now, <hi>audio</hi> I heare, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cìta</hi> recite. <hi>Diſcipùlus</hi> the ſcholler. <hi>Obſervande</hi> reuerend <hi>lu di-magiſter</hi> ſchoolemaiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r <hi>quaedam</hi> certaine (or ſome) <hi>neceſsìtas</hi> neceſſity <hi>cogit</hi> conſtraineth <hi>me</hi> me <hi>inviſère</hi> to goe to ſee (or viſite) <hi>patriam</hi> my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, <hi>parentes</hi> my parents <hi>cognátos</hi> my kinsfolke <hi>quod</hi> the which <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>liceat</hi> it may be lawfull (that the which may be lawfull) <hi>mihi</hi> for me <hi>per</hi> through <hi>te</hi> you (by your leaue) <hi>oro</hi> I intreate. <hi>Venerabìlis</hi> worſhipfull <hi>praeceptor</hi> maiſter <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>jam</hi> now <hi>alìquot</hi> certaine <hi>annis</hi> yeeres <hi>ſub</hi> vnder <hi>tua</hi> your <hi>ferùla</hi> paulmer <hi>navans</hi> employing <hi>opèram</hi> endeauour <hi>bonis</hi> to good <hi>litèris</hi> learning (or letters) <hi>inſtitútus ſum</hi> haue beene inſtructed <hi>à</hi> of (or by) <hi>te</hi> you <hi>diligenter</hi> diligently <hi>et</hi> and <hi>fidelìter</hi> faithfully: <hi>verò</hi> but (or and) <hi>nunc</hi> now <hi>viſum eſt</hi> it hath ſeemed good <hi>meis</hi> to my <hi>parentibus</hi> parents, <hi>amícis</hi> friends, <hi>tutorìbus</hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tours (or gardians) <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>confèram</hi> I betake <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>hinc</hi> hence <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>alì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam</hi> ſome <hi>academiam</hi> vniuerſity, <hi>vbi</hi> where <hi>poſſim</hi> I may be able <hi>capère</hi> to take <hi>ampliórem</hi> a more aboundant <hi>cultum</hi> ornament (or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture) <hi>ingenij</hi> of wit, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>poſtea</hi> afterward <hi>ſervíre</hi> to ſerue <hi>Deo in</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:980:11"/>
in <hi>aliqua</hi> ſome <hi>honeſta</hi> honeſt <hi>functióne</hi> function <hi>vtiliùs</hi> more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablely (or expediently) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>prodeſſe</hi> to profit <hi>alijs</hi> other <hi>hominibus</hi> men. <hi>Quare</hi> wherefore <hi>ago</hi> I giue <hi>tibi</hi> to you <hi>maxìmas</hi> moſt great <hi>gratias</hi> thanks <hi>pro</hi> for <hi>tuis</hi> your <hi>plurìmis</hi> very many <hi>beneficijs</hi> benefits <hi>in</hi> vnto (or towards) <hi>me</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>polliceor</hi> I promiſe <hi>me</hi> that I <hi>velle</hi> will <hi>non</hi> not <hi>ſolùm</hi> onely <hi>perpetuo</hi> continually <hi>meminiſſe</hi> remember <hi>illa</hi> them, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>etiam</hi> alſo <hi>apud</hi> among <hi>omnes</hi> all <hi>bonos</hi> good men <hi>praedicáre</hi> make good report of them <hi>grata</hi> with a thankfull <hi>mente</hi> minde <hi>et</hi> and <hi>lingua</hi> tongue. <hi>Ludimagiſter</hi> the ſchoolema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er. <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsìme</hi> man dearely beloued <hi>adoleſcens</hi> youth, <hi>ſignificatio</hi> the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation <hi>tuae</hi> of thy <hi>modeſtiae</hi> modeſty <hi>et</hi> and <hi>gratitudìnis</hi> gratefulneſſe <hi>quam</hi> which <hi>decláras</hi> thou declareſt <hi>hac</hi> by this <hi>tua</hi> thy <hi>oratióne</hi> ſpeach <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>grata</hi> acceptable <hi>mihi</hi> to me. <hi>Ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ò</hi> and <hi>vtìnam</hi> would <hi>hoc</hi> in this <hi>corrupto</hi> corrupt <hi>ſecùlo</hi> age, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>his</hi> in theſe <hi>perditis</hi> deſperately naught <hi>morìbus</hi> manners <hi>juventútis</hi> of youth, <hi>eſſent</hi> there were <hi>plures</hi> more <hi>tales</hi> ſuch <hi>qui</hi> which <hi>imitarentur</hi> would imitate <hi>tuam</hi> thy <hi>diligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam</hi> diligence <hi>in</hi> in <hi>diſcendis</hi> learning <hi>litèris</hi> letters (or literature) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>regendis</hi> in ruling (or ordering) <hi>moribus</hi> their manners. <hi>Verò</hi> and <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>non</hi> not <hi>ſolùm</hi> only <hi>libenter</hi> willingly <hi>do</hi> giue <hi>tibi</hi> to thée <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niam</hi> leaue <hi>abeundi</hi> to depart (or goe) <hi>in</hi> into <hi>patriam</hi> thy countrey, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>etiam</hi> alſo <hi>oro</hi> doe pray <hi>Deum</hi> God <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>deinceps</hi> afterward (or now hereafter) <hi>regat</hi> he rule <hi>et</hi> and <hi>gubernet</hi> he gouerne <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>ſicut</hi> as <hi>incepiſti</hi> thou haſt begun <hi>pulchrè</hi> goodly (or very well) <hi>ita</hi> ſo <hi>peràgas</hi> thou maiſt goe through with to an end, <hi>nec</hi> neither <hi>ſinas</hi> maiſt ſuffer <hi>te</hi> thy ſelfe <hi>corrumpi</hi> to be corrupted <hi>exemplis</hi> with the examples <hi>et</hi> and <hi>ſodalitio</hi> fellowſhip (or company) <hi>pravórum</hi> of naughty <hi>homì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> men <hi>quorum</hi> of whom <hi>vbique</hi> euery where <hi>eſt</hi> there is <hi>magna</hi> great <hi>copia</hi> ſtore, <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>paulò</hi> a little <hi>poſt</hi> after (not long after) <hi>poſſis.</hi> thou maid <hi>eſſe</hi> be <hi>emolumento</hi> a benefit (profitable) <hi>eccleſiae</hi> to church <hi>et</hi> and <hi>reipublicae</hi> common-wealth, <hi>honóri</hi> an honour <hi>patriae</hi> to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey <hi>et</hi> and <hi>amí<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is</hi> friends, <hi>verò</hi> and <hi>voluptáti</hi> a pleaſure <hi>et</hi> and <hi>ſolatio</hi> a ſolace <hi>parentibus</hi> to thy parents. <hi>Vade</hi> goe <hi>in pace</hi> in peace. <hi>Alíus</hi> another. <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>agis</hi> doeſt thou? <hi>Sedeó</hi> I fit. <hi>Ago</hi> I doe <hi>nihil</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. <hi>Video</hi> I ſee. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>quomòdo</hi> how <hi>tuae</hi> thy <hi>res</hi> matters <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent</hi> haue <hi>ſe</hi> themſelue, (how goe thine affaires.) <hi>Non</hi> not <hi>fatis</hi> enough <hi>felicìter</hi> happily. <hi>Habent</hi> they haue <hi>peſsìme</hi> very bad (they goe very ill.) <hi>Fort aſſis</hi> peraduenture <hi>interpello</hi> I diſturbe <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>occupátum</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied <hi>ſerijs</hi> in earneſt <hi>negotijs</hi> buſineſſes. <hi>Imò</hi> nay rather <hi>maxìmè</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:980:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
very greatly <hi>vacuum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ant (or at leiſure.) <hi>Enim</hi> for <hi>jam</hi> already <hi>tae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> a wearineſſe <hi>otii</hi> of leaſure <hi>cepèrat</hi> had taked <hi>me</hi> mee (had begun to take hold on mee) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>deſiderábam</hi> I did deſire <hi>congerrónem</hi> a merry companion. <hi>Fortaſsis</hi> peraduenture <hi>interturbo</hi> I interrupt <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedio</hi> I hinder <hi>tua</hi> thy <hi>negotia</hi> buſineſſes. <hi>Imò</hi> nay rather <hi>diſcùtis</hi> thou driueſt away <hi>taedium</hi> the weariſomeneſſe <hi>otii</hi> of idleneſſe. <hi>Da</hi> grant <hi>veniam</hi> pardon <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>interpellárim</hi> I haue interrupted <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rùm</hi> a little <hi>in tempòre</hi> in a ſeaſonable time. <hi>Imò</hi> nay rather <hi>advènis</hi> thou commeſt <hi>in</hi> in <hi>ìpſo</hi> the very <hi>tempòre</hi> ſeaſonable time (thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt euen at the very point and chiefe ſeaſon.) <hi>Tuus</hi> thy <hi>adventus</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>vehementer</hi> greatly <hi>gratus</hi> acceptable <hi>mihi</hi> to mée. <hi>Fortaſsis</hi> peraduenture <hi>alìquid</hi> ſome <hi>ſeriae</hi> ſerious <hi>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> matter <hi>agìtur</hi> is handled <hi>inter</hi> betwéene <hi>vos</hi> you, <hi>cui</hi> whereto <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>nolim</hi> am vnwilling (or would not) <hi>eſſe</hi> be <hi>impedimento</hi> an hinderance. <hi>Imò</hi> yea but <hi>locúti</hi> ſumus</hi> wée haue ſpoken <hi>de te</hi> concerning thée. <hi>Credo</hi> I beléeue it <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilè</hi> eaſily, <hi>nam</hi> for <hi>mirè</hi> wonderfully <hi>auris</hi> my eare <hi>tinniébat</hi> did tingle (or ring or burne) <hi>mihi</hi> to mée <hi>venienti</hi> comming <hi>huc</hi> hither. <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra</hi> whether? <hi>Siniſtra</hi> the left. <hi>Vnde</hi> from whence <hi>conjicio</hi> I coniecture <hi>nihil</hi> that nothing <hi>magnificè</hi> with much commendation <hi>fuiſſe dictum</hi> was ſaid <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e me</hi> concerning mée. <hi>Imò</hi> nay rather <hi>nihil non</hi> nothing not (euery thing) <hi>honorificum</hi> ſpoken to thy honour. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>quid</hi> what <hi>bonae</hi> good <hi>rei</hi> matter (or thing) <hi>eſt</hi> is it? <hi>Aiun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> they ſay <hi>te</hi> that thou <hi>factum eſſe</hi> art become <hi>venatórem</hi> an hunter. <hi>Imò</hi> yea. <hi>jam</hi> now <hi>intra</hi> within <hi>meos</hi> my <hi>caſſes</hi> nets (or hayes) <hi>eſt</hi> there is <hi>praeda</hi> the prey <hi>quam</hi> which <hi>venábar</hi> I hunted. <hi>Quaenam</hi> what is it? <hi>Lepìda</hi> a pretie <hi>puella</hi> damſell <hi>quam</hi> whom <hi>ſum</hi> I am <hi>ductúrus</hi> to marry (or take vnto wife) <hi>perendie</hi> the next day after to morro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ideò</hi> therefore <hi>oro</hi> I intreate <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>os</hi> you <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>tunc</hi> then <hi>cohoneſtétis</hi> you grace (or ſet forth) <hi>nuptias</hi> the Wedding <hi>veſtra</hi> by your <hi>praeſentia</hi> preſence. <hi>Quaenam</hi> who <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>Sponfa</hi> the Bride? <hi>Dorothea</hi> Dorothie <hi>filia</hi> the daughter <hi>noſtri</hi> of our <hi>concionatóris</hi> Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. <hi>De</hi> for (or concerning) <hi>hac</hi> her <hi>merìtò</hi> with good cauſe <hi>gratulá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur</hi> wée reioyce in the behalfe of <hi>tibi</hi> thée. <hi>Nam</hi> for <hi>non</hi> not <hi>ſolùm</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>eſt</hi> ſhee is <hi>pulchra</hi> faire (or beautifull) <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>etiam</hi> alſo <hi>benè</hi> well <hi>educáta</hi> brought vp <hi>et</hi> both <hi>ad</hi> to <hi>manendum</hi> abide <hi>domi</hi> at home <hi>ac</hi> and <hi>curanda</hi> to regard (or take care of) <hi>domeſtìca</hi> houſhold (or home) <hi>negotia</hi> buſineſſes, <hi>optìmè</hi> maruellouſly well <hi>inſtitúta</hi> trained vp (or inſtructed.) <hi>confabulatio</hi> a communing <hi>domeſtìca</hi> pertainingto houſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:980:12"/>
(or houſhold) matters. <hi>Heus</hi> ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>puer</hi> boy <hi>prodit</hi> commeth there forth <hi>nemo</hi> no body <hi>huc</hi> hither? <hi>Hic</hi> this man <hi>opinor</hi> I thinke <hi>effringet</hi> will breake open (or to péeces) <hi>fores</hi> the dore. <hi>Eſt</hi> it is <hi>veri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ìmìle</hi> very like <hi>eſſe</hi> that he is <hi>aliquem</hi> ſonte <hi>ſamiliárem</hi> familiar. <hi>O amice</hi> O friend <hi>mi</hi> my <hi>Petie</hi> Peter <hi>quid</hi> what <hi>adfers</hi> doeſt thou bring? <hi>Meipſum</hi> mine owne ſelfe. <hi>Tu</hi> thou <hi>certè</hi> truly <hi>attuliſti</hi> haſt brought <hi>huc</hi> hither <hi>rem</hi> a thing <hi>haud</hi> not <hi>magni</hi> of a great <hi>pretii</hi> price. <hi>Atqui</hi> yea but <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtìti</hi> I coſt <hi>meo patri</hi> my father <hi>magno</hi> a great price. <hi>Credo</hi> I beléeue <hi>eum</hi> that he <hi>feciſſe</hi> hath made (or beſtowed) <hi>majóres</hi> greater <hi>ſumptus</hi> coſts (or charges) <hi>in</hi> vpon <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>pro</hi> according to <hi>digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>táte</hi> thy worthines (or deſert.) <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>nc</hi> whether <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>Iohannes</hi> Iohn <hi>domi</hi> at home? <hi>Non ſcio</hi> I know not <hi>certò</hi> certainly (or aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly.) <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>abi</hi> goe <hi>viſum</hi> to ſée. <hi>Vel</hi> or <hi>abi</hi> goe <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>potiùs</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>interogátum</hi> to aske (or enquire) <hi>an</hi> whether <hi>ſit</hi> he be <hi>domi</hi> at home. <hi>An</hi> whether <hi>velit</hi> he will <hi>jam</hi> now at length (or ere it be long) <hi>eſſe</hi> bée <hi>domi</hi> at home? <hi>Heus</hi> hoe <hi>Petre</hi> Peter <hi>num</hi> whether, <hi>es</hi> art thou <hi>domi</hi> at home? <hi>Non ſum</hi> I am not. <hi>Impùdens</hi> thou ſhameleſſe one <hi>non ego audio</hi> doe not I heare <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>loquentem</hi> ſpeaking. <hi>Imò</hi> nay rather <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>impudentior</hi> art more ſhameleſſe. <hi>Enim</hi> for <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uper</hi> lately <hi>credìdi</hi> I beleeuedtuae thy <hi>ancillae</hi> maid <hi>te</hi> that thou <hi>non eſſe</hi> was not <hi>domi</hi> at home, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>non credis</hi> beleeueſt not <hi>mihi ipſi</hi> mée my ſelfe. <hi>Dicis</hi> thou ſayeſt <hi>aequum</hi> right (thou ſpeakeſt reaſon.) <hi>Nam</hi> for <hi>refers</hi> thou rendreſt <hi>par</hi> like <hi>pari</hi> for like <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>vidéris</hi> thou ſée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt <hi>mihi</hi> to mee <hi>agère</hi> to leade (or liue) <hi>vitam</hi> the life <hi>cochleae</hi> of a Snaile. <hi>Quid</hi> why <hi>ita</hi> ſo? <hi>Quia</hi> becauſe <hi>perpetuò</hi> alwaies <hi>ſedes</hi> thou ſitteſt <hi>domi</hi> at home <hi>nec</hi> and not <hi>prorèpis</hi> commeſt forth <hi>vſquam</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place. <hi>Eſt</hi> there is matter <hi>quod</hi> which <hi>agam</hi> I may doo <hi>domi</hi> at home, <hi>feris</hi> abroad <hi>eſt</hi> there is <hi>mihi</hi> to mee <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>negotii</hi> of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe (no buſineſſe.) <hi>Et</hi> and <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>eſſet</hi> there were <hi>quid</hi> any <hi>tamen</hi> yet notwithſtanding <hi>haec</hi> this <hi>aura</hi> winde (or ayrs) <hi>cohibuiſſet</hi> would had kept (or reſtrained) <hi>me</hi> mée à from <hi>publìco</hi> abroad <hi>alìquot</hi> certaine <hi>dies</hi> daies. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>nunc</hi> now <hi>coelum</hi> the firmament (or ayre) <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>ſerénum</hi> faire (or cleere) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>invítat</hi> inuiteth (or allureth) <hi>ad</hi> to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambulandum</hi> walke abroad. <hi>Si</hi> if <hi>lubet</hi> it liketh <hi>prodeambuláre</hi> to walke forth, <hi>non recúſo</hi> I refuſe not. <hi>Aſsìdes</hi> thou ſitteſt at <hi>libris</hi> thy bookes <hi>nimiùm</hi> ouermuch. <hi>Macèras</hi> thou weareſt out <hi>te</hi> thy ſelfe <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modìco</hi> with immoderate (or vnmeaſurable) <hi>ſtudio</hi> ſtudie. <hi>Malo</hi> I haue rather (or liefer) <hi>marceſcère</hi> to be conſumed (or become faint.)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:980:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſtudio with ſtudie <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>amóre</hi> with loue. <hi>Ecquid</hi> whether <hi>haec</hi> this <hi>deambulatio</hi> walking abroad <hi>fuit</hi> hath beene <hi>voluptáti</hi> vnto (or for) pleaſure? <hi>Quidem</hi> truly <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>delectátus ſum ea</hi> hane beene de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted therewith (or therein) <hi>vehementer</hi> very greatly. <hi>A liús</hi> another <hi>dialògus</hi> dialogue. <hi>Opto</hi> I wiſh <hi>tibi</hi> to thee <hi>multam</hi> much <hi>felicitátem</hi> happineſſe. <hi>Et</hi> and <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>opto</hi> wiſh <hi>conduplicátum</hi> double <hi>quicquid</hi> whatſouer <hi>optas</hi> thou wiſheſt <hi>mihi</hi> to mee. <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>agis</hi> doeſt thou? <hi>Confabùlor</hi> I commune. <hi>Quid</hi> what? <hi>Confábuláre</hi> doeſt thou commune <hi>ſolus</hi> alone? <hi>Certè</hi> truly <hi>confabùlor</hi> I talke <hi>cum</hi> with <hi>lepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſsìmo</hi> a moſt pleaſant <hi>congetróni</hi> merry companion. <hi>Quo</hi> with whom? <hi>Divo</hi> with ſaint <hi>Paulo</hi> Paul. <hi>Ciceróne</hi> with Cicero. <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem</hi> indeed <hi>facis</hi> thou doeſt <hi>iſtud</hi> that <hi>ſaepe</hi> oftentimes. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>variè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> varietie <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>grata</hi> pleaſant (or acceptable.) <hi>Tu</hi> thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>perpetuò</hi> continually <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>noctes</hi> nights <hi>et</hi> and <hi>dies</hi> daies <hi>incumbis</hi> applyeſt (or bendeſt earneſtly) <hi>litèris</hi> to learning. <hi>Nihil</hi> nothing <hi>ſuave</hi> is ſweet (or pleaſant) <hi>quod</hi> the which <hi>perpetuum</hi> is continuall without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. <hi>Facis</hi> thou doeſt <hi>tuo</hi> after thy <hi>more</hi> faſhion (or cuſtome.) <hi>Rides</hi> thou laugheſt at <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>vt</hi> as <hi>ſoles</hi> thou art wont. <hi>Ipſi</hi> the very <hi>libri</hi> bookes <hi>obducti</hi> couered ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>pulv ère</hi> with duſt <hi>teſtantur</hi> doe teſtifie (or witneſſe) <hi>meam</hi> my <hi>diligentiam</hi> diligence <hi>in</hi> in <hi>ſtudiis</hi> ſtudies <hi>de</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>mea</hi> my <hi>diligentia</hi> diligence <hi>in ſtudiis</hi> in ſtudies. <hi>Loquor</hi> I ſpeake <hi>ſeri ò</hi> earneſtly <hi>ex</hi> from <hi>anìmo</hi> my heart. <hi>Formùlae</hi> formes <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dandi</hi> of giuing in charge (or bidding) <hi>ac</hi> and <hi>pollicendi</hi> of promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. <hi>Quaeſo</hi> I beſeeth <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>haec</hi> this <hi>res</hi> thing <hi>ſit</hi> may be <hi>tibi</hi> to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>cordi</hi> vnto heart (that thou haſt a care of this thing.) <hi>Rogo</hi> I requeſt <hi>etiam</hi> yet <hi>atque</hi> and <hi>etiam</hi> yet further (earneſtly and diligently) <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>hoc</hi> this <hi>negotium</hi> buſineſſe <hi>ſit</hi> be <hi>tibi</hi> to thee <hi>curae</hi> a core. <hi>Si</hi> if <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> thou loueſt <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>efficias</hi> bring to paſſe (or to effect) <hi>hoc</hi> this thing <hi>fideliter</hi> faithfully <hi>et</hi> and <hi>diligenter</hi> diligently. <hi>Ego</hi> I <hi>reddam</hi> will make (or procure) <hi>hoc</hi> this thing <hi>effectum</hi> effected <hi>tibi</hi> for thee, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>quidem</hi> indeed <hi>propediem</hi> ſhortly (within theſe few daies.) <hi>Non poſſum</hi> I cannot <hi>praeſtàre</hi> vndertake for (or warrant) <hi>eventum</hi> the euent, <hi>polliceor</hi> I promiſe <hi>illud</hi> this, <hi>nec</hi> n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>fidem</hi> that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe <hi>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> nor <hi>ſtudium</hi> endea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our <hi>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utú<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>all be wanting <hi>mihi</hi> to (or in) mee. <hi>Polliceor</hi> I promiſe <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in ſpeach (or word.) <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>praeſtáb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> I will perform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the deed <hi>quicquid</hi> whatſoeuer <hi>eſt</hi> is the dutie <hi>ſincéri</hi> of a ſincere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> friend, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolentis</hi> bearing good will <hi>exanimo</hi> from the heart (or affection.)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:980:13"/>
               <hi>Cur</hi> why <hi>non viſis</hi> doeſt thou not viſit (or goe to ſee?) <hi>Propter</hi> by reaſon of <hi>quam</hi> what <hi>cauſam</hi> cauſe <hi>non invíſis</hi> doeſt thou not come to ſee <hi>nos</hi> vs <hi>tamdiu</hi> ſo long a while? <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>accìdit</hi> hath happened <hi>quòd</hi> that <hi>tam</hi> ſo <hi>longo</hi> long <hi>tempòre</hi> time <hi>non acceſsèris</hi> thou haſt not come <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>nos</hi> vs <hi>tam</hi> ſo <hi>longo</hi> long <hi>tempòre</hi> a time? <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>obſtìtit</hi> hath letted (or beene in the way) <hi>quo</hi> whereby <hi>minùs</hi> the leſſe (that not) <hi>jam</hi> now <hi>diu</hi> a great while (or long time) <hi>venèrís</hi> thou haſt come <hi>ad nos</hi> vnto vs? <hi>Non licuit</hi> it hath not beene lawfull; (or I might not, or could not.) <hi>Non licuit</hi> I was not free <hi>per</hi> by reaſon of <hi>occupatiónes</hi> neceſſary buſineſſes. <hi>Otium</hi> leiſure <hi>non fuit</hi> hath not beene <hi>mihi</hi> to mee (I haue had no leiſure.) <hi>Equìdem</hi> truly <hi>volui</hi> I haue beene willing <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>facultas</hi> ability (or leaue) <hi>non data eſt</hi> hath not beene giuen (or granted) <hi>mihi</hi> to mee. <hi>Negotia</hi> the buſineſſes <hi>quibus</hi> with which <hi>eram</hi> I was <hi>implicàtus</hi> incumbred <hi>non patiebantur</hi> ſuffered not <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>ſalutárem</hi> I might ſalute <hi>te</hi> thee (that I might doe my duty to you.) <hi>Accipio</hi> I accept <hi>tuam</hi> thy <hi>excuſatiónem</hi> excuſe, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>hac</hi> with this <hi>lege</hi> condition <hi>ne</hi> that not <hi>vtáris</hi> thou vſeſt it <hi>ſaepiùs</hi> oftner times. <hi>Tua</hi> thy <hi>excuſatio</hi> excuſe <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>juſtior</hi> juſter <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>vellem</hi> I would <hi>ſiquìdem</hi> in as much as <hi>morbus</hi> a diſeaſe <hi>fuit</hi> was (or hath beene) <hi>in cauſa</hi> for excuſe (hath beene the cauſe or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.) <hi>accipio</hi> I receiue (or take) <hi>tuam</hi> thy <hi>excuſatiónem</hi> excuſe <hi>hac lege</hi> vpon this condition <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>quod</hi> that which <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>neglectum</hi> neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected <hi>compenſes</hi> thou make amends for <hi>crebris</hi> with often <hi>alloquiis</hi> communications. <hi>Succeſſus</hi> the ſucceſſe (or euent.) <hi>Res</hi> the matter <hi>ſucceſſit</hi> hath proſpered (or had ſucceſſe) <hi>meliùs</hi> better <hi>opinióne</hi> than ſuppoſell (then you thinke.) <hi>Impetràvi</hi> I haue obtained by requeſt <hi>plus</hi> more <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>auſus fuiſſem</hi> I might had dared <hi>optáre</hi> to wiſh. <hi>Omnis</hi> all <hi>res</hi> the matter <hi>cecìdit</hi> hath chanced <hi>ex</hi> according to <hi>ſententia</hi> my minde (as I would wiſh or haue it.) <hi>Et</hi> both <hi>habeo</hi> I giue <hi>et</hi> and <hi>habitúrus ſum</hi> I will giue <hi>maxìmam</hi> very great gratiam thankes <hi>tibi</hi> to you <hi>quoad</hi> as long as <hi>vivam</hi> I liue. <hi>Poſſum</hi> I can vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſcarce <hi>agère</hi> giue <hi>gratias</hi> thankes <hi>pares</hi> meet (or equall) <hi>pro</hi> for <hi>iſto</hi> that <hi>tuo</hi> thy <hi>beneficio</hi> good turne, <hi>referre</hi> to requite <hi>nequá quam</hi> in no wiſe. <hi>quòd</hi> for that <hi>meum</hi> my <hi>negotium</hi> buſineſſe <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>tibi</hi> to thee <hi>cordi</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heart (a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.) Amo I loue <hi>te</hi> thee <hi>et</hi> and <hi>habeo</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>gratiam</hi> thankes, <hi>Ex</hi> out of (or among) <hi>omnìbus</hi> all <hi>beneficiis</hi> benefits <hi>quae</hi> which <hi>plurìma</hi> being very many <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>contuliſti</hi> haſt beſtowed in on <hi>me</hi> mee <hi>hoc</hi> this eſt is <hi>longè</hi> farre <hi>gratiſſimum</hi> the moſt acceptable.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:980:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Reſponſio</hi> the anſwer, <hi>Noſtra</hi> our <hi>neceſſitúdo</hi> nigh friendſhip <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>major</hi> greater <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>vel</hi> either <hi>tu</hi> thou <hi>mihi</hi> to mee <hi>vel</hi> or <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>tibi</hi> to thee <hi>debeam</hi> nought <hi>agère</hi> to giue <hi>gratias</hi> thankes <hi>pro</hi> for <hi>vllo</hi> any <hi>beneficio</hi> good turne. <hi>Qui</hi> hee which <hi>benè</hi> well <hi>merétur</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth <hi>de</hi> of <hi>amíco</hi> a friend <hi>non dat</hi> doth not giue <hi>beneficium</hi> a kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (or good turne) <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>foenèrat</hi> lendeth out to vſutie. <hi>Si</hi> if <hi>ex anìmo</hi> from the heart <hi>probas</hi> thou alloweſt (or approueſt) <hi>meum</hi> my <hi>officium</hi> duty (or ſeruice) <hi>in</hi> vnto (or towards) <hi>te</hi> thee, <hi>fac</hi> doo <hi>vtáre</hi> that thou maiſt vſe it (ſee that thou vſe it) <hi>ſaepids</hi> oftener. <hi>Alius</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. <hi>Prandébis</hi> will you dine <hi>coenábis</hi> will you ſuppe <hi>hodiè</hi> to day <hi>domi</hi> at home? <hi>Oportet me</hi> it behooueth me (I muſt) <hi>prandére</hi> dine <hi>caenáre</hi> ſuppe <hi>apud</hi> with <hi>ſocèrum</hi> my wiues father <hi>ſocrum</hi> my wiues mother <hi>genèrum</hi> my ſonne in law (hee that marrieth my daughter) <hi>affínem</hi> mine alliance (or couſin by marriage) <hi>conſùlem</hi> the Conſul. <hi>Igìtur</hi> therefore <hi>in</hi> for (or againſt) <hi>craſtìnum</hi> the morrow <hi>voco</hi> I call (or bid or inuite) <hi>te</hi> you <hi>ad</hi> vnto <hi>prandium</hi> dinner <hi>caenam</hi> ſupper. <hi>Oro</hi> I intreate <hi>te</hi> you <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>cras</hi> to morrow <hi>prandeas</hi> you dine <hi>caenes</hi> you ſuppe <hi>mecúm</hi> with mee. <hi>timeo</hi> I feare <hi>ne</hi> leaſt that <hi>non poſſim</hi> I cannot. <hi>Metuo</hi> I am afraid <hi>vt poſſim</hi> that I cannot. <hi>Veniam</hi> I will come <hi>ſiquìdem</hi> if ſo be that <hi>licèbit</hi> it ſhall be lawfull (I may.) <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>metuo</hi> I feare <hi>ne</hi> leaſt that <hi>non queam</hi> I cannot be able (or may not.) <hi>Quare</hi> wherefore <hi>cur</hi> why <hi>propter</hi> by reaſon of <hi>quam</hi> what <hi>cauſam</hi> cauſe? <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>obſtat</hi> letteth <hi>quo minùs</hi> that not <hi>poſſis</hi> you may <hi>veníre</hi> come? <hi>Tunc</hi> then <hi>quidem</hi> truly <hi>manendum eſt mihi</hi> I muſt tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>domi</hi> at home. <hi>Cras</hi> to morrow <hi>non licébit</hi> it will not be lawfull (or free) <hi>mihi</hi> for me <hi>exíre</hi> to goe forth. <hi>Ipſe</hi> I my ſelfe <hi>tunc</hi> at that time <hi>expecto</hi> expect <hi>alíquot</hi> certaine <hi>compranſóres</hi> diners with mee <hi>concoenatóres</hi> ſuppers with me <hi>non poſſum</hi> I cannot <hi>pollicéri</hi> promiſe certaínely. <hi>Nequeo</hi> I cannot <hi>promittère</hi> promiſe. <hi>Veniam</hi> I will come <hi>vbi</hi> when as <hi>videbìtur</hi> it ſhall ſeeme <hi>vtríque</hi> to both <hi>noſtrum</hi> of vs <hi>eſſe</hi> to be <hi>commodiſsìmum</hi> the moſt commodious (or conuenient) (or when it ſhall ſeeme to be moſt conuenient for both of vs.) <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>detineo</hi> doe detaine <hi>te</hi> thee <hi>fortaſſis</hi> peraduenture <hi>itúrum</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to goe <hi>aliò</hi> to another place. <hi>Imò</hi> yea rather <hi>ego</hi> I (doo detaine) <hi>te</hi> thee <hi>opíno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> I ſuppoſe. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>cras</hi> tomorrow <hi>confabulabìmur</hi> we will talke togither <hi>latiùs</hi> more amply. <hi>Craſtino</hi> on to morrowes <hi>die</hi> day <hi>nugabìmur</hi> wee will talke ſleightly of (or tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le about) <hi>plura</hi> more things. <hi>Intèrim</hi> in the meane while <hi>cura</hi> haue a care <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leas</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:980:14"/>
thou be in good health. <hi>Formùla</hi> a forme <hi>gratulandi</hi> of being glad in behalfe <hi>de</hi> of <hi>redìtu</hi> a returne. <hi>Matthaeus</hi> Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hew <hi>et</hi> and <hi>Lucas</hi> Luke. <hi>Gratùlor</hi> I reioyce in the behalfe of <hi>tibi</hi> thee <hi>reverſo</hi> returned <hi>in patriam</hi> into thy countrie <hi>de</hi> of <hi>redìtu</hi> thy returne <hi>in patriam</hi> into thy countrie. <hi>L. Et</hi> and <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>tibi</hi> for thee <hi>ſuperſtìti</hi> ſuruiuing (or aliue) <hi>Matthaee</hi> O Matthew. <hi>M. rediiſti</hi> thou haſt returned <hi>nobis</hi> to vs <hi>obeſior</hi> groſſer (or fatter) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>procerior</hi> taller <hi>ſolito</hi> than wont (than thou was wont.) <hi>Abiiſti</hi> thou departedſt (or wenteſt) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ine</hi> without <hi>barba</hi> beard <hi>imberbis</hi> beardleſſe: <hi>rediiſti</hi> thou haſt returned <hi>barbátus</hi> bearded. <hi>Habens</hi> hauing <hi>prolixam</hi> a long <hi>barbam</hi> bears. <hi>Praedìtus</hi> indued (or adorned) <hi>pulchra</hi> with a faire <hi>barba</hi> beard. <hi>L. At</hi> but <hi>quidem</hi> indeed <hi>mallem</hi> I ſhould leiſer <hi>redíre</hi> to returne <hi>pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior</hi> wiſer <hi>et</hi> and <hi>doctior</hi> learneder. <hi>M. Gratulámur</hi> wee reioyce in the behalfe of <hi>et</hi> both <hi>tibi</hi> thee <hi>et</hi> and <hi>nobis</hi> our ſelues, <hi>quòd</hi> becauſe <hi>ſis</hi> thou art <hi>reſtitútus</hi> reſtored <hi>nobis</hi> to vs <hi>vivus</hi> liuing <hi>et</hi> and <hi>valens</hi> in good health. <hi>L. Ego</hi> I <hi>viciſsim</hi> for my part likewiſe <hi>laetor</hi> am glad <hi>quòd</hi> becauſe <hi>incolùmis</hi> I ſafe and ſound <hi>offendèrim</hi> haue found <hi>vos</hi> yee <hi>incolùmes</hi> ſafe and ſound. <hi>Quòd</hi> for that <hi>reperèrim</hi> I haue found te thee <hi>ſalvum</hi> ſafe (or in good health) <hi>gaudeo</hi> I am glad <hi>vehementer</hi> exceeding greatly. <hi>M. Quid</hi> what <hi>vult</hi> meaneth <hi>ſibi</hi> to it ſelfe <hi>ille</hi> that <hi>pallor</hi> paleneſſe? (What meaneth that pale colour?) <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>maci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> the leanneſſe? <hi>Quid</hi> what <hi>rugae</hi> the wrinckles <hi>in fronte</hi> in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head? <hi>L. Qualis</hi> ſuch as (of what ſort) <hi>fortúna</hi> the fortune (euen as ones fortune is) <hi>talis</hi> ſuch <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>et</hi> alſo <hi>habìtus</hi> the habit <hi>corpòris</hi> of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. <hi>Nunquid</hi> whether any thing <hi>agìtur</hi> is done (or gone) <hi>malè</hi> badly <hi>tecum</hi> with thée? <hi>Nunquid</hi> whether <hi>alìquid</hi> any <hi>acerbi</hi> grieuous thing (or aduerſitie) <hi>accìdit</hi> hath chanced <hi>tibi</hi> tó thée? <hi>L. Etſi</hi> although <hi>ferè</hi> almoſt <hi>nullo</hi> in no <hi>tempòre</hi> time <hi>fortúna</hi> fortune <hi>favit</hi> hath fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>mihi</hi> mee, <hi>tamen</hi> yet notwithſtanding <hi>nunquam</hi> neuer <hi>adverſàta eſt</hi> it hath croſſed (or beene againſt) <hi>mihi</hi> mee <hi>magìs</hi> more <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>nunc</hi> now. <hi>M. Doleo</hi> I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (or am ſorrie for) <hi>tuam</hi> thy <hi>vicem</hi> caſe (or misfortune.) <hi>Tua</hi> thy <hi>calàmìtas</hi> calamity <hi>dolet</hi> grieueth (or is w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>full) <hi>mihi</hi> to mee. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>quid</hi> what <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>iſtud</hi> that <hi>mali</hi> euill? <hi>L. Feci</hi> I haue made <hi>naufragium</hi> ſhipwracke <hi>vniverſae</hi> of all (of euery whit of my) <hi>pecuniae</hi> money. <hi>M. Vbínam</hi> where <hi>chariſsìme</hi> moſt dearely beloued one? <hi>L. Navigatúrus</hi> ſayling (or about to ſaile) in in <hi>Baltìco</hi> the Balticke <hi>mari</hi> ſea <hi>ex</hi> out of <hi>Dania</hi> Denmarke in into <hi>Germaniam</hi> Germany. <hi>M. Igìtur</hi> then <hi>non eſt</hi> there is not <hi>dubium</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:980:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
doubt <hi>quin</hi> but <hi>oravèris</hi> thou prayedſt (or could haue prayed) <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter</hi> diligently. <hi>L. Nunquam</hi> neuer <hi>diligentiùs</hi> more diligently. <hi>M. Igìtur</hi> then <hi>fatéris</hi> thou confeſſeſt it <hi>eſſe</hi> to be <hi>verum</hi> true (that that is true) <hi>quod</hi> which <hi>dicìtur</hi> is ſaid; <hi>qui</hi> he that <hi>neſcit</hi> knoweth not <hi>orá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> to pray <hi>diſcat</hi> let him learne <hi>navigáre</hi> to ſaile. <hi>L. Fateor</hi> I confeſſe (it,) <hi>nam</hi> for <hi>expertus ſum</hi> I haue experienced (or proued it) <hi>ipſa</hi> in the very <hi>re</hi> deed. <hi>M. Habet</hi> it hath (or goeth) <hi>benè</hi> well, <hi>quòd</hi> that <hi>ipſe</hi> thou thy ſelfe <hi>enataſti</hi> haſt ſwimmed out (or eſcaped) <hi>nobis</hi> to vs <hi>vivus</hi> aliue. <hi>Eſt</hi> it is <hi>melius</hi> better <hi>facère</hi> to ſuffer <hi>Iactúram</hi> loſſe <hi>pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae</hi> of money <hi>quám</hi> than <hi>vitae</hi> of life. <hi>Igìtur</hi> therefore <hi>vides</hi> thou ſeeſt <hi>doctrínam</hi> that learning <hi>et</hi> and <hi>virtútem</hi> that vertue <hi>eſſe</hi> are <hi>tutiſsìmas</hi> moſt ſafe <hi>divitias</hi> riches <hi>quae</hi> which <hi>nec</hi> neither <hi>poſſunt</hi> can <hi>eripi</hi> bee taken away <hi>nec</hi> nor <hi>gravant</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t load (or burden) <hi>circumferentem</hi> the bearer (he that alwaies carrieth the ſame about him.) <hi>Tu</hi> thou <hi>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem</hi> indeed <hi>Philoſopháris</hi> philoſophiſeſt (ſtudieſt philoſophy or ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt Philoſopher like) <hi>pulchrè</hi> ioylily well, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>intèrim</hi> in the meane while <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>angor</hi> am vexed <hi>dolóre</hi> with the griefe. <hi>Salutáre</hi> to ſalute <hi>per alium</hi> another. <hi>Salúta</hi> ſalute thou <hi>meos</hi> my <hi>parentes</hi> parents (doe my commendations to my parents.) <hi>Sakíta</hi> ſalute <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſùlem</hi> the Conſul <hi>paſtórem</hi> the Paſtour <hi>ſocrum</hi> my wiues mother <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finem</hi> my couſin (by marriage) <hi>meo</hi> in my <hi>nomìne</hi> name <hi>vel</hi> or <hi>meis</hi> with my <hi>verbis</hi> words. <hi>Quò</hi> whither <hi>vadis</hi> goeſt thou <hi>Nicholaè</hi> O Nicholas? <hi>Rectà</hi> ſtraight forth <hi>in patrìam</hi> into the countrie. <hi>Reſiſte</hi> ſtop (or ſtay) <hi>pauliſper</hi> a little while, <hi>eſt</hi> there is buſineſſe <hi>quod</hi> the which <hi>mandem</hi> I may commit <hi>tibi</hi> to you. (There is ſomewhat which I ſhould giue in charge to you.) <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>ſarcìna</hi> a packe <hi>non convènit</hi> ſquareth (or ſuiteth not) <hi>pedìti</hi> to a footman (it is not fit for a footman to beare a truſſe or fardle.) <hi>Non impónam</hi> I will not put vpon <hi>tibi</hi> thée <hi>magnum</hi> a great <hi>onus</hi> burden. <hi>Autem</hi> but <hi>quid</hi> what <hi>rei</hi> thing <hi>eſt</hi> is it? <hi>Vt</hi> that <hi>amanter</hi> louingly <hi>ſalútes</hi> you ſalute <hi>meis verbis</hi> with my words <hi>omnes</hi> all <hi>praeceptóres</hi> the maſters (or tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>meos</hi> my <hi>familiáres</hi> familiars (or friends or acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) <hi>in</hi> in <hi>roſtochiána</hi> Roſtock <hi>Academia</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſitie. <hi>Si</hi> if <hi>impónis</hi> you impoſe (or la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e on mee) <hi>nihil aliud ſarcìnae</hi> no other packs <hi>praeter</hi> beſides <hi>ſalutatiónes</hi> ſalutations, <hi>facìlè</hi> eaſily <hi>perfèram</hi> I ſhall beare it through (to the waies end.) <hi>Autem</hi> and (or but) <hi>ego</hi> I, <hi>ne</hi> leaſt that <hi>facias</hi> thou maiſt (or ſhouldeſt doe) <hi>iſtud</hi> this thing gratis without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (for nothing) <hi>precor</hi> doe pray <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>Chriſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Chriſt ſit be <hi>tibi</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:980:15"/>
to thée <hi>comes</hi> a companion <hi>itinèris</hi> of the iourney. <hi>Quod</hi> that which <hi>precáris</hi> thou prayeſt for <hi>Deus</hi> God <hi>faxit</hi> grant. <hi>Enim</hi> for <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>habuèro</hi> I ſhall haue <hi>Chriſtum</hi> Chriſt <hi>comìtem</hi> a companion <hi>itinèris</hi> of the way (or iourney) <hi>ſcio</hi> I know <hi>me</hi> that I <hi>ſatìs</hi> enough <hi>eſſe</hi> am <hi>munítum</hi> fenced (or fortified) <hi>contra</hi> againſt <hi>omnia</hi> all <hi>pericùla</hi> dangers. <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mùlae</hi> formes <hi>interrogandi</hi> of asking <hi>de</hi> concerning <hi>valetudìne</hi> health. <hi>Georgius</hi> George. <hi>Lucas</hi> Luke, <hi>G. Ne</hi> whether <hi>vales</hi> are you in good health? <hi>L. Contempláre</hi> behold diligently <hi>vultum</hi> my countenance. <hi>G. Quin</hi> why, not <hi>magis</hi> rather <hi>jubes</hi> doeſt thou bid me (to looke dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently vpon) <hi>lotium</hi> thy water (or vrine?) <hi>An</hi> whether <hi>putas</hi> thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt thou, <hi>me</hi> that I (am) <hi>medicum</hi> a phiſitian? <hi>Non rogo</hi> I aske not <hi>an</hi> whether <hi>valeas</hi> thou be in good health, <hi>nam</hi> for <hi>ipſa</hi> thy very <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> face <hi>loquìtur</hi> ſpeaketh (or telleth) <hi>te</hi> that thou <hi>valére</hi> art in health <hi>bellè</hi> well (or goodly,) <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>quomòdo</hi> how <hi>placeas</hi> canſt thou pleaſe (or delight) <hi>tibi</hi> thy ſelfe? <hi>L. Corpus</hi> my body <hi>quidem</hi> indéed <hi>habet</hi> hath <hi>bellè</hi> well (is well) <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>eſt</hi> it is <hi>anìmo</hi> to my minde <hi>malè</hi> ill (my minde is not well) <hi>G. At</hi> but <hi>non valet</hi> he is not in good health, <hi>qui</hi> which <hi>labórat</hi> is ill at eaſe <hi>iſta</hi> in that <hi>parte</hi> part. <hi>L. Sic</hi> ſo <hi>meae</hi> my <hi>res</hi> matters <hi>habeut</hi> haue (goe or are,) <hi>corpus</hi> my body <hi>valet</hi> is well, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>cruména</hi> my purſe <hi>aegrótat</hi> is ſicke <hi>G. Mater</hi> thy mother <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debitur</hi> will cure <hi>iſti</hi> this <hi>morbo</hi> diſeaſe <hi>facilè</hi> eaſily. <hi>Vt</hi> how <hi>valuiſti</hi> haſt thou done (béene in health) <hi>hueuſque</hi> hitherto? <hi>L. Variè</hi> after a diuers manner, <hi>vti</hi> as <hi>res</hi> the things (or matters) <hi>mortalium</hi> of mortall men <hi>ſunt</hi> are. <hi>G. Fuiſtíne</hi> whether haſt thou béene <hi>ſemper</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies <hi>proſpèrâ</hi> of (or in) proſperous <hi>valetudìne</hi> health? <hi>Proſperrìma</hi> of moſt proſperous, <hi>gratia</hi> thankes <hi>Deo</hi> to God. <hi>Ego</hi> I <hi>beneficio</hi> through the fauour (or bountifulneſſe) <hi>Dei</hi> of God <hi>perpetuò</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually <hi>valui</hi> haue béene in health <hi>belliſsìmè</hi> moſt goodly (or pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.) <hi>hactèous</hi> hitherto <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i</hi> I haue béene <hi>bona</hi> in good <hi>valetudìne</hi> health. <hi>G. Deus</hi> God <hi>faxit</hi> grant <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>iſtud</hi> this (that) thing (or benefit) <hi>ſit</hi> be <hi>perpetuum</hi> continuall <hi>et</hi> and <hi>proprium</hi> thine owne. <hi>Audio</hi> I heare <hi>iſtud</hi> that thing <hi>laetus</hi> ioyfull, <hi>gratùlor</hi> I reioyce in the behalfe of <hi>tibi</hi> thée. <hi>Gratias</hi> thankes (be) <hi>Deo</hi> to God. <hi>Habeo</hi> I haue (or yéeld) <hi>gratiam</hi> thankes <hi>Deo</hi> to God, <hi>ago</hi> I giue <hi>Deo</hi> to God <hi>gratias</hi> thankes <hi>maxìmas</hi> very great <hi>quantas</hi> as (how great as) <hi>poſſum</hi> I can. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>fuit</hi> hath there béene <hi>tibi</hi> to thée <hi>intèrim</hi> in the meane while <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>moleſtiae</hi> of trouble (no diſquiet or tediouſneſſe?) <hi>L. Nihil</hi> nothing (or none) <hi>niſi</hi> except <hi>quòd</hi> that <hi>non licuit</hi> it was
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:980:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not lawfull (I might not) <hi>frui</hi> enioy <hi>ueſtra</hi> your <hi>conſuetudìne</hi> acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance (or company.) <hi>Malè valére</hi> to be ill (or infirme.) <hi>G. Ne</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>vales</hi> art thou in health <hi>rectè</hi> well (or rightly?) <hi>A. Quidem</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed <hi>vellem</hi> I would <hi>Non valeo</hi> I am not in health <hi>per omnia</hi> in all things (parts) <hi>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cumque</hi> howſoeuer <hi>valeo</hi> I am ſtrong. <hi>Non bene valeo</hi> I am not in good health <hi>corpòse</hi> in body <hi>admòdum</hi> very much <hi>vt</hi> as <hi>ſoleo</hi> I am wont. <hi>Valeo</hi> I am in health <hi>vt</hi> as <hi>viſum eſt</hi> it hath ſéemed good <hi>Deo</hi> to God. <hi>Valeo</hi> I am in ſtate <hi>ſecus</hi> otherwiſe <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>vellem</hi> I would. <hi>vt</hi> as <hi>ſolent</hi> they are wont, <hi>quibus</hi> to whom <hi>res</hi> matter, (buſineſſe or dealing) <hi>cum medìcis</hi> with phyſitians <hi>eſt</hi> is, <hi>G. Deus</hi> God <hi>avertat</hi> turne (it) away (forefend,) <hi>narras</hi> thou telleſt <hi>rem</hi> a matter <hi>peracerbam</hi> very ſowre (or vnpleaſant) <hi>mihi</hi> to mée. <hi>Oportet</hi> it behooueth (that) <hi>ſis</hi> thou be <hi>bono anìmo</hi> of a good courage. <hi>Oportet</hi> it behooueth (that) <hi>praeſtes</hi> thou declareſt <hi>te</hi> thy ſelfe <hi>virum</hi> a man. <hi>Eſto</hi> bee thou <hi>forti</hi> of a ſtrong <hi>infractóque</hi> and not diſcouraged <hi>anìmo</hi> minde (or ſpirit) <hi>contra</hi> againſt <hi>morbum</hi> the diſeaſe. <hi>Bonus anìmus</hi> a good courage <hi>multùm</hi> much <hi>juvat</hi> helpeth <hi>in mala re</hi> in a bad matter. <hi>Quo morbo</hi> with what diſeaſe <hi>tenèris</hi> art thou halden? <hi>Quis morbus</hi> what diſeaſe <hi>tenet</hi> holdeth <hi>te</hi> thée? <hi>Quid morbi</hi> what diſeaſe <hi>habes</hi> haſt thou? <hi>Quo morbo</hi> of what diſeaſe <hi>laboras</hi> art thou ſicke? <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Neſcio</hi> I know not, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>ideò</hi> therefore <hi>labóro</hi> I am ſicke <hi>pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſiùs</hi> the more dangerouſly. <hi>G. Dicis</hi> thou ſayeſt <hi>verum</hi> true. <hi>Dicis</hi> thou ſayeſt <hi>rectè</hi> rightly. <hi>Enim</hi> for <hi>primus gradus</hi> the firſt degrée <hi>ad ſanitátem</hi> vnto health <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>nouiſſe</hi> to know <hi>morbum</hi> the díſeaſe. <hi>Ne</hi> whether <hi>conſuluiſti</hi> haſt thou asked counſell of <hi>nullum medìcum</hi> no phyſitian? <hi>L. Equìdem</hi> truly <hi>multos</hi> many. <hi>G. Quid</hi> what <hi>reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> doe they anſwer? <hi>L. Alius</hi> one <hi>negat</hi> ſaith no, <hi>alius</hi> another <hi>cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet</hi> déemeth <hi>deliberandum</hi> that aduiſement muſt be taken. <hi>In ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in this <hi>omnes</hi> all <hi>conſentiunt</hi> doe agrée <hi>me</hi> that I <hi>eſſe</hi> am miſèrum miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. <hi>G. Quantum tempòris</hi> how much time <hi>eſt</hi> is it, <hi>quòd</hi> that <hi>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> malum</hi> this euill <hi>corripuit</hi> hath taken (or caught) to thée? <hi>Quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prídem</hi> how long <hi>habet</hi> holdeth <hi>te</hi> thée <hi>hic morbus</hi> this díſeaſe: <hi>L. Octo dies</hi> eight daies. <hi>Iam</hi> now <hi>eſt</hi> it is <hi>fermè</hi> almoſt <hi>intèger menſis</hi> a whole moneth. <hi>Malè habeo</hi> I haue béene ill <hi>tres</hi> thrée, <hi>quatuor</hi> foure, <hi>aut</hi> or <hi>quinque intègros menſes</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ue whole moneths. <hi>labóre</hi> I am (or haue béene) ſicke <hi>jam</hi> now <hi>decimum menſem</hi> the tenth moneth. <hi>Aegróto</hi> I am (or haue béene) ſicke <hi>jam</hi> already <hi>intègrum an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m a whole yéere. <hi>G. Genſeo</hi> I thinke good <hi>adniténdum</hi> that greatly it muſt be endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:980:16"/>
                  <hi>ne</hi> that not <hi>morbus</hi> the díſeaſe <hi>fiat</hi> become <hi>familiáris</hi> familíar. <hi>Num</hi> whether <hi>eſt</hi> is it <hi>hydrops</hi> a dropſie? <hi>I. Negant</hi> they ſay no. <hi>g. Num</hi> whether <hi>dyſenteria</hi> the bloudy flixe? <hi>I. Non arbitror</hi> I ſuppoſe not. <hi>g. Num</hi> whether <hi>febris</hi> a feauer? <hi>I. Credo eſſe</hi> I beleeue that it is. <hi>g. Qualiſnam</hi> of what ſort (or manner) <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>febris</hi> the feaner? <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance</hi> whether continuall, <hi>an</hi> or <hi>quotidiána</hi> quotídian (that happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth euery day) <hi>an</hi> or <hi>tertiána</hi> tertian (that happeneth euery third day) <hi>an</hi> or <hi>quartána</hi> quartaine (that happeneth on euery fourth day?) <hi>I. Opinor</hi> I ſuppoſe eſſe it to be <hi>novam ſpeciem</hi> a new kinde <hi>febris</hi> of feauer, <hi>vt</hi> as <hi>nunc</hi> now a dayes <hi>ſubinde</hi> euer now and then <hi>novi mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi</hi> new diſeaſes <hi>exoriuntur</hi> doe ariſe out (or ſpring forth) <hi>incognìti</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne <hi>antèhac</hi> heretofore. <hi>g. At</hi> but truly <hi>erat</hi> there was <hi>plus</hi> aboue (or more than) <hi>ſatis</hi> enough <hi>vetèrum</hi> of olde ones. <hi>l. Ita</hi> ſo <hi>viſum eſt</hi> it hath ſeemed good <hi>Deo</hi> to God <hi>punienti</hi> puniſhing <hi>nova peccáta</hi> new ſinnes <hi>novis morbis</hi> with new diſeaſes. <hi>g. Quoto die</hi> on what day <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit</hi> commeth againe <hi>dolor</hi> the paine? <hi>l. Quoto die</hi> on what day <hi>nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> ſayeſt thou? <hi>Imò</hi> yea <hi>quotidie</hi> daily, <hi>ſaepiùs</hi> oftner <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rípus</hi> (an arme of the ſea that ebbeth and floweth ſeauen times in a day.) <hi>g. O malum</hi> O euill <hi>abominandum</hi> to be abhorred! <hi>Vnde</hi> from whence <hi>contraxiſti</hi> haſt thou gotten <hi>morbum</hi> the diſeaſe? <hi>Vnde</hi> from whence <hi>ſuſpicáris</hi> doeſt thou ſuſpect (or ſuppoſe) <hi>hoc mali</hi> that this euill <hi>eſſe collectum</hi> hath beene taken (or gathered?) <hi>l. Ex inedia</hi> out of hunger (or lacke of meate and drinke.) <hi>g. At</hi> but <hi>non ſoles</hi> thou art not wont <hi>vſque adeò</hi> ſo much <hi>eſſe</hi> to be <hi>ſuperſtitióſus</hi> ſuperſtitious, <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>macèras te</hi> thou ſpendeſt (or conſumeſt thy ſelfe) <hi>jejunio</hi> with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting. <hi>l. Non erat</hi> it was <hi>not religio</hi> religion, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>inopia</hi> pouerty. <hi>Enim</hi> for <hi>cibus</hi> meat <hi>non dabátur</hi> was not gíuen. <hi>Arbìtror</hi> I iudge <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum</hi> that it was bred <hi>è frig òre</hi> out of colde: <hi>crudìtas</hi> the rawneſſe <hi>ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>màchi</hi> of the ſtomack <hi>contracta <hi>eſt</hi> was contracted <hi>è crudis malis</hi> from rawe apples. <hi>g. Vide</hi> ſee (or take heed) <hi>ne</hi> leaſt that <hi>concilláris</hi> thou haſt procured <hi>hoc mali</hi> thís euíll <hi>tibi</hi> to thy ſelfe <hi>ex</hi> out of <hi>immodìco</hi> vnmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable <hi>aut</hi> or <hi>intempeſtívo</hi> vnſeaſonable <hi>ſtudio</hi> ſtudy, <hi>aut</hi> either <hi>ex largióre potatióne</hi> out of more aboundant drinking (more than cuſtom was, or more than enough) <hi>aut</hi> or <hi>ex ebriétate</hi> out of drunkenneſſe. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>cur</hi> wherefore <hi>non accerſis</hi> goeſt not thou to call (or fetch) <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum</hi> the Phiſtian? <hi>l. Timeo</hi> I feare <hi>ne</hi> leaſt that <hi>augeat</hi> he may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe <hi>morbum</hi> the diſeaſe <hi>citìus</hi> ſooner <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>curet</hi> may cure (it.) <hi>Metuo</hi> I feare ac leaſt that <hi>det</hi> hee may giue <hi>venénum</hi> poyſon <hi>pro</hi> in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:980:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſtéede of <hi>remedio</hi> a remedy. <hi>g. Igìtur</hi> therefore <hi>eſt</hi> hee is <hi>diligendus</hi> to be beloued, <hi>cui</hi> whom <hi>fidas</hi> thou maiſt truſt <hi>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ò</hi> ſafely. <hi>l. Si</hi> if <hi>mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum eſt</hi> I muſt die, <hi>malo</hi> I haue rather <hi>mori</hi> to die <hi>ſemel</hi> once, <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>excarnificátus</hi> be rended in péeces (or tormented) <hi>tot pharmàcis</hi> with ſo many medicines. <hi>g. Igìtur</hi> then <hi>fac</hi> doe, <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>ipſe</hi> thou <hi>ſis</hi> maiſt be <hi>Medìcus</hi> a Phyſitiam <hi>tibí</hi> to thy ſelfe. <hi>Sì</hi> if <hi>diffídis</hi> thou di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſteſt <hi>homìni</hi> a man <hi>Medìco</hi> being a Phyſitian, <hi>precor</hi> I pray <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>Deus</hi> God <hi>ſit</hi> may be <hi>tibì</hi> to thée <hi>vice</hi> in ſteed <hi>Med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ci</hi> of a Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian. <hi>Sunt</hi> there are they <hi>qui</hi> which <hi>indúti</hi> clad <hi>veſte</hi> with a garment <hi>Monàchi</hi> of a Monke <hi>convaluérunt</hi> haue recouered health. <hi>l. Idem</hi> the ſame thing <hi>fortaſſe</hi> peraduenture <hi>eveniſſet</hi> would had happened, <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>fuiſſent</hi> they had béene <hi>recti</hi> couered <hi>pelle</hi> with the ſkinne <hi>Leónis</hi> of a Lyon. <hi>Verùm</hi> but <hi>iſta</hi> theſe things <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>condúcunt</hi> are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable <hi>diffidenti</hi> to one diſtruſting. <hi>g. Igìtur</hi> then <hi>fide</hi> truſt <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>reviviſcas</hi> thou maiſt come to thine olde ſtate agaíne (or recouer.) <hi>Alij</hi> ſome <hi>ſunt</hi> are <hi>leváti</hi> eaſed <hi>morbo</hi> of a diſeaſe, <hi>votis</hi> vowes (or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes) <hi>nuncupátis</hi> made ſolemnly (with formall words) <hi>alicui</hi> to ſome one <hi>divórum</hi> of the Saints. <hi>l. At</hi> but <hi>ego</hi> I <hi>non paciſcor</hi> doe not make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouenant <hi>cum diuis</hi> with the ſaints. <hi>g. Proinde</hi> therefore <hi>pete tu</hi> craus thou <hi>beneficium</hi> the benefit <hi>ſanitátis</hi> of health <hi>à Chriſto</hi> from Chriſt <hi>cui</hi> whom <hi>fi dis</hi> thou truſteſt. <hi>l. At ego</hi> but I <hi>neſcio</hi> know not <hi>an</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>ſit</hi> it be <hi>beneficium</hi> a benefit. <hi>g. An non eſt</hi> whether is it not <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficium</hi> a benefit <hi>liberári</hi> to be fréed <hi>morbo</hi> from a diſeaſe? <hi>Nonnun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam</hi> ſometimes <hi>eſt</hi> it is <hi>felicius</hi> more happy <hi>mori</hi> to die. <hi>Ego autem</hi> but I <hi>peto</hi> doe craue <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>à Chriſto</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>niſi</hi> except <hi>quod</hi> which <hi>ſit</hi> is (or may be) <hi>optìmum</hi> beſt. <hi>g. Tu quidem</hi> thou indéed <hi>philoſopháris</hi> doeſt philoſophize (or philoſophically treate) <hi>piè</hi> godlily. <hi>Enim</hi> for <hi>cùm</hi> when <hi>petìmus</hi> wee aſke (or craue) <hi>à Deo</hi> of God <hi>bona</hi> good things <hi>neceſſaria</hi> neceſſary <hi>ad hanc vitam</hi> for this life, <hi>ſemper</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies <hi>addendum eſt</hi> we muſt adde, <hi>Domìne</hi> O Lord <hi>ſi tu vis</hi> if thou wilt. <hi>Autem</hi> but <hi>ſpiritualia</hi> ſpirítuall <hi>et</hi> and <hi>aeterna</hi> eternall <hi>bona</hi> good things <hi>ſunt</hi> are <hi>petenda</hi> to be aſked <hi>à Deo</hi> of God <hi>ſine</hi> without <hi>vlla</hi> any <hi>conditióne</hi> condition. <hi>Sed but vale</hi> farewell <hi>mi Luca</hi> my Luke. <hi>l. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsìme Georgi</hi> O moſt deare George <hi>vale et tu</hi> farewell thou alſo <hi>in craſtìnùm</hi> till to morrow. <hi>Alius dialògus</hi> another dialogue. <hi>g. Fuitne</hi> whether hath béene <hi>hoc iter</hi> this iourney <hi>fauſtum</hi> lucky <hi>et commòdum</hi> and commodious <hi>tibi</hi> to thée? <hi>l. Sic ſatis</hi> ſo enough (indifferently) <hi>nìſi quod</hi> ſauing that <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>vſquam</hi> in any place <hi>eſt tutum</hi> is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:980:17"/>
ſafe <hi>à latronìbus</hi> from robbers. <hi>g. Advènis</hi> commeſt thou <hi>pedes</hi> a foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>an eques</hi> or a horſeman? <hi>I. Partim</hi> partly <hi>itinère</hi> by a going <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dèſtri</hi> ou foote, <hi>partim</hi> partly <hi>Vehicùlo</hi> by Waggon, <hi>partim</hi> partly <hi>equo</hi> on horſe, <hi>partim</hi> partly <hi>navigio</hi> by ſayling (or ſhipping.) <hi>g. Quo in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu</hi> in what ſtate <hi>ſunt</hi> are <hi>res Belgìcae</hi> matters of Belgica (or of the low Countries.) <hi>l. Sanè</hi> truly <hi>turbul ento</hi> in a turbulent (or full of troubles.) <hi>Sunt</hi> there are <hi>magnae minae</hi> great threats <hi>bellórum</hi> of warres. <hi>g. Sed</hi> but <hi>omittámus</hi> let vs omit <hi>haec</hi> theſe matters. <hi>Enim</hi> for <hi>nihil</hi> nothing is <hi>nobis</hi> to vs (we haue nothing to doe) <hi>cum marte</hi> with warre. <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mòdo</hi> how <hi>habent</hi> haue (or goe) <hi>tuae res</hi> thine owne matters? <hi>l. Bene</hi> well, <hi>pulchrè</hi> goodlily, <hi>optìmè</hi> very well. <hi>g. Nonne</hi> whether not <hi>agìtur</hi> is it done (or fallen forth) <hi>bene</hi> well <hi>tecum</hi> with thée? <hi>l. Optimè</hi> very well, <hi>feliciſsìmè</hi> moſt happily. <hi>g. Nonne</hi> whether not <hi>vtèris</hi> doeſt thou take profit of <hi>proſpèro ſtatu</hi> the proſperous eſtate <hi>fortúnae</hi> of fortune? <hi>l. Imo</hi> nay rather <hi>maxìmè adverſo</hi> the greatly vnfortunate. <hi>Res</hi> the matter <hi>non poteſt eſſe</hi> cannot be <hi>in pejóri ſtatu</hi> in a worſer ſtate. <hi>g. Non cepiſti</hi> haſt thou not taken, <hi>quod captábas</hi> that which thou didſt goe about to take? <hi>Non contìgit praeda</hi> hath not the prey happened, <hi>quam venabaris</hi> which thou didſt hunt? <hi>l. Venábor equìdem</hi> I did hunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, <hi>ſed iráta Diána</hi> but Diana being angry. <hi>g. Eſt</hi> is there <hi>nihil ſpei</hi> no hope <hi>reliquum</hi> remaining? <hi>l. Permultum ſpei</hi> very much hope, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>nihil rei</hi> no thing (or matter.) <hi>g. Conſul oſtendit nihil ſpei</hi> doth the Conſul ſhew no hope (put in no hope?) <hi>l. Tota plauſtra</hi> all the whole (or euery whit of) the Waines (or Chariets,) <hi>totas naves</hi> euery whit of the ſhips; <hi>ſed nihil</hi> but nothing <hi>praeterea</hi> beſides. <hi>g. Miſit ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil adhuc</hi> hath he ſent nothing as yet? <hi>l. Promíſit quidem largìter</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede he hath promiſed largely, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>miſit</hi> he hath ſent <hi>ne obòlum quidem</hi> not an halfe penny indéede. <hi>Promittit quidem</hi> hee promiſeth indéede <hi>multa</hi> many things <hi>verbis</hi> with words, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>praeſtat</hi> he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>re</hi> in the deede. <hi>g. Ergò</hi> therefore <hi>anìmus</hi> the minde <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>alendus</hi> to be fed <hi>ſpe</hi> with hope. <hi>l. Sed</hi> but <hi>venter</hi> the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>non ſaginátur</hi> is not fatted <hi>hac</hi> herewith. <hi>g. Autem</hi> but <hi>ideò</hi> for that cauſe <hi>eras</hi> thou was <hi>expeditior</hi> the morelight (or readier) <hi>ad iter</hi> for the iourney, <hi>quòd</hi> becauſe <hi>eſſet</hi> there was <hi>nihil onèris</hi> no burden <hi>in zona</hi> in purſe. <hi>l. Fateor</hi> I confeſſe, <hi>atque etiam</hi> and alſo <hi>tutior</hi> the ſafer. <hi>Enim</hi> for <hi>ſunt</hi> there are <hi>nulla arma</hi> no weapons <hi>certióra</hi> ſuerer <hi>adverſùs latrónes</hi> againſt robbers by the high way. <hi>Sed ego malim</hi> but I can be more williug of <hi>et</hi> both <hi>onus</hi> the burthen <hi>et</hi> and <hi>pericùlum</hi> the danger.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:980:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>g. Nihilne</hi> whether nothing <hi>ademptum eſt</hi> hath beene taken away <hi>tibi</hi> from thee <hi>in via</hi> in the way? <hi>l. Mihíne</hi> what from me? <hi>Quaeſo</hi> I pray <hi>quid cripias</hi> what cauſt thou take away <hi>nudo</hi> from a naked one? <hi>Erat</hi> there was <hi>alijs</hi> to others <hi>citìus</hi> ſooner (more likely) <hi>pericùlum</hi> danger <hi>à me</hi> by (or from) me. <hi>Licuit</hi> it was lawfull <hi>mihi</hi> for me <hi>vacuo viatóri</hi> an empty traueller (I an empty traueller might) <hi>per totum iter</hi> through the whole iourney (all the way along) <hi>canère</hi> to fing <hi>et</hi> and <hi>oſuríre</hi> to hunger. <hi>g. Quò autem</hi> but whither <hi>nunc abis</hi> departeſt thou now? <hi>l. Rectà</hi> ſtraite, way <hi>domum</hi> home <hi>ſolutatúrus</hi> to ſalute <hi>vxórem</hi> wife <hi>et</hi> and <hi>parentes</hi> parents <hi>non viſos</hi> not ſéene <hi>jam diu</hi> a great while. <hi>g. Precor</hi> I pray <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>illie</hi> there <hi>offendas</hi> you may finde <hi>omnia</hi> all things <hi>laeta</hi> pleaſant (or luckie.) <hi>l. Vtìnam</hi> would that <hi>Deus</hi> God <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit</hi> be willing <hi>ita</hi> ſo. <hi>Extìtit</hi> hath there béene (or happened) <hi>nihil novi</hi> no newes <hi>noſtrae domi</hi> at our houſe <hi>intèrim</hi> in the meane time? <hi>g. Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil</hi> none (or nothing) <hi>niſi</hi> unleſſe <hi>quòd</hi> that <hi>reperies</hi> thou ſhalt finde <hi>familiam</hi> the family <hi>auctam</hi> encreaſed, <hi>nam</hi> for <hi>tua gallína</hi> thy Hen <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pèrit</hi> hath laid <hi>tibi</hi> for thée <hi>pulchrum ovum</hi> a faire (or goodly) egge. <hi>l. Nuncias</hi> thou ſheweſt tydings <hi>benè</hi> well. <hi>Pro hoc nuncio</hi> for this newes <hi>do</hi> I giue <hi>tibi</hi> to thée <hi>munus</hi> a gift (or preſent) <hi>videlicet</hi> to wit, <hi>novum Teſtamentum</hi> the new Teſtament <hi>eleganter</hi> finely <hi>excúſtim</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed <hi>Lutetiae</hi> at Paris <hi>recèns</hi> lately. <hi>g. Itame Deus amet</hi> ſo God loue (helpe) me, <hi>pulchrum evangelium</hi> it is a faire Goſpell. <hi>Hoc munus</hi> this gift <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>longè gratiſsìmum</hi> farre moſt acceptable <hi>mihi</hi> to mee. <hi>Diſpiciam</hi> I will conſider in minde (or looke about diligently) <hi>vnde</hi> by what meanes <hi>poſſim</hi> I may be able <hi>penſare</hi> to recompence <hi>hoc do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> this gift. <hi>l. Puta</hi> thinke <hi>te</hi> that thee <hi>penſaſſe</hi> haſt recompenced <hi>abundè</hi> abundantly (or enough) <hi>ſi</hi> i. <hi>boni conſuluèris</hi> thou wilt take in good worth. <hi>Alius</hi> another. <hi>g. Ne</hi> whether <hi>adfers</hi> bringeſt thou <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>novárum rerum</hi> of new matters <hi>ex Patria</hi> from one Country? <hi>Portas</hi> beareſt (or bringeſt thou) <hi>nihil novi</hi> no newes <hi>à noſtris</hi> from ours? <hi>Quaenam nova</hi> what new things <hi>nuncias</hi> telleſt thou? <hi>l. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multá nova</hi> very many new matters <hi>at nihil veri</hi> but nothing true. <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fèro</hi> I bring <hi>tantum mendaciórum</hi> ſo great lies, <hi>quantum</hi> as <hi>vix</hi> ſcarce <hi>vna navis</hi> one ſhip <hi>vehat</hi> can carie. <hi>g. Igìtur</hi> then <hi>exonèra te</hi> vnburden thy ſelfe <hi>quamprímum</hi> as ſoone as can be poſſiblely, <hi>ne</hi> leaſt that <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbas</hi> thou fall vnder <hi>tanto onèri</hi> ſo great a burden. <hi>l. nihil habeo</hi> I haue nothing <hi>praeter ea</hi> beſides <hi>thoſe</hi> things. <hi>quae</hi> which <hi>jactantur</hi> are ſpoken of <hi>in Tonſtrínis</hi> in Barbers ſhops, <hi>in vehicùlis</hi> in wagens, <hi>et</hi> in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:980:18"/>
                     <hi>navibus</hi> and in ſhips. <hi>g. Quid</hi> what, <hi>no</hi> whether <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>noſtra patria</hi> out countrey <hi>immúnis</hi> free <hi>à peſtilèntia</hi> from the peſtilence? <hi>l. Non omní<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> not altogether, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>non eſt</hi> it is not <hi>perpetua</hi> continuall (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion:) <hi>aliquando</hi> ſometimes <hi>remittit</hi> it ſlacketh <hi>ſeſe</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>deinde</hi> afterwards <hi>recrudeſcit</hi> it waxeth grieuous againe. <hi>g. Nonne erat</hi> was there not <hi>ſatis malórum</hi> enough of euils, <hi>vbi</hi> when <hi>bellum</hi> warre <hi>graſſatur</hi> aſſaileth (or commeth on with violent rage?) <hi>l. Erat quidem</hi> there was indéede, <hi>niſi</hi> vnleſſe <hi>alìter</hi> otherwiſe <hi>viſum eſt</hi> it had ſeemed good <hi>Deo</hi> to God. <hi>g. Oportet</hi> there muſt needes <hi>eſſe be caritá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem</hi> a ſcarſity <hi>annónae</hi> of victuall <hi>iſtic</hi> there. <hi>l. Eſt</hi> there is <hi>inopia</hi> a ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity <hi>omnium rerum.</hi> of all things <hi>illic</hi> there <hi>praeterquam</hi> except <hi>ſcelera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tórum militum</hi> of miſchieuous ſouldiers. <hi>g. Vbi</hi> where <hi>milìtes</hi> ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers <hi>dominantur</hi> doe beareſway, <hi>ibi</hi> there <hi>parcunt</hi> they ſpare <hi>nec</hi> neither <hi>ſacris templis</hi> the ſacred temples <hi>nec</hi> nor <hi>ipſis Muſis</hi> the Muſes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. <hi>l. Rectè igitur</hi> rightly therefore <hi>et ſapienter</hi> and wiſely <hi>Xenò<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon inquit</hi> Xenophon ſaith: <hi>pax</hi> peace <hi>vidétur</hi> ſéemeth <hi>hominìbus</hi> to men <hi>eſſe</hi> to be <hi>magnum bonum</hi> a great good, <hi>bellum verò</hi> but warre <hi>magnum malum a</hi> great euill. <hi>Sed</hi> but <hi>non morábor te</hi> I will not cauſe thee to tarry <hi>diutiùs</hi> any longer. <hi>Aliàs</hi> at another time <hi>colloquémur</hi> we will conferre <hi>pluribus</hi> with more words, <hi>cum</hi> when <hi>erit</hi> it ſhall be <hi>commòdum</hi> commodious <hi>vtríque</hi> for both. <hi>Nunc nom quaedam ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotia</hi> certaine buſineſſes <hi>vocant me</hi> call me <hi>aliò</hi> to another place. <hi>Alius dialògus</hi> another dialogue. <hi>g. Audio</hi> I heare <hi>te</hi> that thou <hi>nuper</hi> lately <hi>reviſiſſe</hi> returnedt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to ſee <hi>Patriam</hi> thy Country <hi>l. Revíſi</hi> I went againe to ſee. <hi>Enim</hi> for <hi>non vidèram</hi> I had not ſeene <hi>meos parentes</hi> my pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents <hi>diu</hi> a good while. <hi>Non potèram</hi> Im as not able <hi>diutiùs ferre</hi> any longer to abide <hi>deſiderium</hi> the lacke (or abſence) <hi>Patriae</hi> of Countrey <hi>et amicórum</hi> and of friends. <hi>g. Feciſti piè</hi> thou haſt done godlily, <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mánus es</hi> thou art humane (or friendly) <hi>qui</hi> which <hi>cogitas</hi> thinkeſt on <hi>iſta</hi> theſe things. <hi>Omnes enim</hi> for all we <hi>ducimur</hi> are led <hi>quodam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirabili amore</hi> with a certaine wonderfull loue <hi>ejus regionis</hi> of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <hi>quae</hi> which <hi>aluit</hi> hath nouriſhed (or bred) <hi>et edìdit</hi> and hath brought forth <hi>nos</hi> vs. <hi>Sed dic quaeſo</hi> but tell I pray <hi>quonam in loco in</hi> what ſtate <hi>illic</hi> there <hi>offendiſti</hi> foundeſt thou <hi>omnia</hi> all things? <hi>l. Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa</hi> vniuerſall things <hi>nova</hi> new: omnia all things <hi>mutáta</hi> changed. <hi>Vidébar mihi</hi> I ſeemed to my ſelfe (me thought) <hi>venire</hi> to come <hi>in ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um mundum</hi> into another world. <hi>Vixdum abfuèram</hi> I had ſcarcely beene abſent <hi>decennium</hi> the ſpace of tenne yeares, <hi>mirábar</hi> I wondred
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:980:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
at <hi>omnia</hi> all things <hi>non ſecus</hi> no otherwiſe, <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>Epimenìdes princeps ſomniat órum</hi> Epimenides the chiefe of dreamers, <hi>vix</hi> ſcarce <hi>tandem</hi> when all came to all <hi>expergefactus</hi> wakened out of ſleepe. <hi>g. Quaenam eſt iſta fabùla</hi> what is that tale? <hi>l. Dicam quìdem</hi> I will tell it indeede, <hi>ſi vacat</hi> if there be leaſure <hi>audíre</hi> to heare. <hi>g. Nihil</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>fuèrit</hi> ſhall be <hi>jucundius</hi> more pleaſant (or acceptable.) <hi>l. Igìtur</hi> then <hi>jube</hi> commaund <hi>ſellam</hi> that a ſtoole <hi>cum pulvíno</hi> with a cuſhion <hi>poni</hi> be ſet <hi>mihi</hi> for me. <hi>g. Rectè admònes</hi> thou doeſt well put in mind, <hi>nam</hi> for <hi>ſedens</hi> ſitting <hi>mentiéris</hi> thou wilt lye <hi>commodiùs</hi> the more handſomly. <hi>l. Hiſtorìci</hi> the hiſtorians <hi>fabulantur</hi> doo fable <hi>de Epime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nìde</hi> concerning Epimenides <hi>quodam</hi> one (or a certaine man) <hi>Cretenſi</hi> of Crete, <hi>qui</hi> which <hi>gratiâ</hi> for the cauſe <hi>deambulandi</hi> of walking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad <hi>folus</hi> alone <hi>egreſſus vrbem</hi> paſſed forth of (or paſſed beyond) the Citie, <hi>cùm</hi> when as <hi>ſubìta vi</hi> through a ſuddaine violence <hi>pluviae</hi> of raine: <hi>compellente</hi> conſtraining <hi>ingreſſus</hi> hauing entred <hi>in quandam ſpeluncam</hi> into a certaine Caue <hi>obdormiſſet</hi> had fallen faſt a ſleepe, <hi>continuárit</hi> he continued <hi>ſomuum</hi> the ſleepe <hi>quadraginta ſeptem perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuos annos</hi> forty ſeauen whole yeares. <hi>g. Sed benè actum eſt</hi> but it was well brought to paſſe <hi>cum Epimenìde</hi> with Epimentdes <hi>qui</hi> which <hi>tandem</hi> at the laſt <hi>redijt</hi> returned <hi>ad ſe</hi> vnto himſelfe. <hi>Multi docti</hi> many learned men <hi>nunquam expergiſcuntur</hi> neuer awake à <hi>ſuis ſomnijs</hi> from their dreames. <hi>Sed facis</hi> but thou doeſt <hi>vt eſt dignum</hi> as is beſeeming <hi>Poéta</hi> a Peet. <hi>Perge igìtur</hi> goe forward then <hi>mentiri</hi> to lye. <hi>l. Epimenides igìtur</hi> Epimenides then <hi>ſolútus ſomno</hi> looſed from ſleepe (broad awaked) <hi>prodit</hi> commeth forth <hi>èſſpelurica</hi> out of the Caue, <hi>circumſpìcit</hi> looketh round about, <hi>videt omnia mutáta</hi> ſeeth all things changed, <hi>Sylvas</hi> Woods, <hi>ripas</hi> bankes, <hi>ſlumìna</hi> riuers, <hi>arbòres</hi> trees, <hi>agros</hi> fields, <hi>brevìter</hi> briefly, <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>non novum</hi> not new (euery thing new.) <hi>Accédit</hi> hee commeth <hi>ad Vrbem</hi> vnto the Citie, <hi>percontatur</hi> he aſketh queſtions, <hi>manet</hi> he abideth <hi>illic</hi> there <hi>aliquandiu</hi> a certaine while, <hi>neque</hi> neither <hi>novit</hi> knew <hi>quenquam</hi> any man, <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi> nor <hi>agnìtus eſt</hi> was knowne (or acknowledged) <hi>à quoquam</hi> by any one. <hi>Cultus</hi> the attire <hi>homìnum</hi> of men <hi>alius</hi> was of another ſort, <hi>nec</hi> neither <hi>vultus</hi> the countenance <hi>idem</hi> the ſame, <hi>ſermo</hi> the ſpeach <hi>mutátus</hi> changed, <hi>mores</hi> the manners <hi>diverſi</hi> diuers. <hi>Neque</hi> neither <hi>miror</hi> doe I wonder <hi>hoc</hi> that this thing <hi>eveniſſe</hi> happened <hi>Epimenide</hi> to Epimenides <hi>poſt tantórum annórum</hi> after ſo many yeares, <hi>cùm</hi> whereas <hi>idem</hi> the ſame thing <hi>propemòdum</hi> in a manner <hi>evenèrit</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:980:19"/>
                     <hi>Epimenìdi</hi> to Epimenides <hi>poſt tantum annorum</hi> after ſo many yeares. <hi>g. Quid</hi> what (what ſay you of) <hi>vterque parens</hi> both parents (both father and mother) <hi>vivuntne</hi> whether are they liuing? <hi>l. ambo</hi> both <hi>vivunt</hi> do liue, <hi>&amp;</hi> and <hi>valent</hi> do hold out (or are heart-whole, or are of abilitie,) <hi>vteunque</hi> howſoeuer <hi>confecti</hi> weakened (or féeble) <hi>ſenio</hi> through old age, <hi>morbo</hi> diſeaſe <hi>denìque</hi> and in concluſion <hi>calamitáte</hi> through the calamitie <hi>bellórum</hi> of warres. <hi>g. Haec eſt comoedia</hi> this is the comedy <hi>humánae vitae</hi> of mans life. <hi>Humánae res</hi> humane mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>ſunt</hi> are <hi>tales</hi> ſuch <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>nihil</hi> nothing <hi>duret</hi> doth endure (or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue) <hi>in eódem ſtatu</hi> in the ſame ſtate (the matters of mankinde are after ſuch a manner, as that nothing can continue in one ſtay.) <hi>De inſſituenda ratióne</hi> of diſpoſing the maner <hi>ſtudiórum</hi> of ſtudies <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctè</hi> rightly. <hi>Diſcipùlus</hi> the <hi>ſcholler &amp;</hi> and <hi>praeceptor</hi> the maiſter. <hi>d. Mi chariſſime praeceptor</hi> my moſt deare maiſter <hi>cupio</hi> I deſire <hi>audìre</hi> to heare <hi>ex te</hi> of thee <hi>breuìter</hi> briefly, <hi>quae ratio</hi> what manner (or way) <hi>ſtudórum</hi> of ſtudies <hi>ſit</hi> may be (or is) <hi>inſtituenda</hi> to be appointed <hi>rectè</hi> rightly, <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>modò</hi> ſo that <hi>ocium</hi> leaſure <hi>eſt</hi> be <hi>tibi</hi> to you, <hi>&amp; tempus</hi> and time <hi>commòdum</hi> conuenient <hi>his rebus</hi> for theſe matters. <hi>p. Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcens</hi> O youth, <hi>tu quidem</hi> thou indéed <hi>captaſti tempus</hi> haſt watched a time <hi>commòdum</hi> conuenient. <hi>Deinde</hi> moreouer <hi>illud tuum liberále &amp; honeſtum deſiderium</hi> that thy free and honeſt deſire <hi>libenter</hi> gladly <hi>anteferrem</hi> I ſhould ſet more by <hi>vel</hi> euen <hi>meis maxìmis occupationì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> than my greateſt employments. <hi>Quare</hi> wherefore <hi>praefatione</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing <hi>omiſſa</hi> being omitted, <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>&amp;</hi> both <hi>meliùs cognoſcam</hi> I may better know <hi>tuum ingenium</hi> thy nature (or wit,) <hi>&amp; magis probem ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi</hi> and may more proue to thée <hi>meam beneuolentiam</hi> my good will <hi>erga te</hi> towards thée, <hi>ſimplicìter</hi> plainly <hi>interròga</hi> aſke <hi>me</hi> mée <hi>de rebus</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning things <hi>ſingùlis</hi> euery one by it ſelfe (or in particular concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning euery thing one after another) <hi>quas</hi> which <hi>cupis</hi> thou deſireſt <hi>ſcire</hi> to know. <hi>d. Facis</hi> thou doeſt <hi>piè</hi> godlily <hi>&amp; honeſtè</hi> honeſtly, <hi>cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſime praeceptor.</hi> O moſt renowned maiſter, <hi>quòd</hi> becauſe <hi>non grauá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> you are not loath <hi>crudíre</hi> to inſtruct <hi>me</hi> mée <hi>beneuòlè</hi> fauerably <hi>de his tantis rebus</hi> concerning theſe ſo great matters. <hi>Itàque</hi> therefore <hi>primùm</hi> firſt <hi>cupio</hi> I deſire <hi>ſcire</hi> to know <hi>ex te</hi> of you <hi>quiſnam praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puus ſit finis</hi> what is the chiefe end <hi>noſtrórum ſtudiórum</hi> of our ſtudies, <hi>ad quem</hi> vnto the which, <hi>velut ad ſcopum</hi> as it were vnto a marke (or butte) <hi>omnes noſtri labóres</hi> all our labours <hi>diſcendi</hi> of learning <hi>debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant</hi> onght <hi>referri</hi> to be referred. <hi>p. Tu quidem</hi> thou indéed <hi>rectè ordí<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:980:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
doeſt tightly begin <hi>ab hac queſtióne</hi> from this queſtion. <hi>Intellecto enim ſcopo</hi> for the marke being vnderſtood <hi>et meta</hi> and the goale, <hi>ad quam tendìmus</hi> vnto which we make toward, <hi>poterìmus elìgère</hi> wée ſhall be able to chooſe <hi>facilitìs</hi> more eaſily <hi>etiam</hi> alſo <hi>media</hi> the meanes <hi>ducentia</hi> leading <hi>rectà</hi> ſtraite way <hi>ad iſtam metam</hi> vnto that goale (or butte.) <hi>Autem</hi> but <hi>ſunt</hi> there are <hi>duae propriae et praecipuae dotes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mìnis</hi> two proper and chiefe gifts of man, <hi>quibus</hi> by which <hi>antecellit</hi> he excelleth <hi>relìquo genèri</hi> the other kinde <hi>animantium</hi> of liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>ratio</hi> reaſon <hi>et</hi> and <hi>oratio</hi> ſpeach. <hi>His</hi> by theſe <hi>excultis</hi> garniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>ſtudiósè</hi> ſtudiouſly <hi>et</hi> and <hi>rectè</hi> rightly, <hi>homìnes</hi> men <hi>praeſtant</hi> doe excell <hi>non ſolùm</hi> not only <hi>caetèris animalìbus</hi> other liuing creatures, <hi>verùm</hi> but <hi>inter ſe</hi> among themſelues <hi>alii</hi> ſome <hi>praeſtant</hi> doe excell <hi>aliis hominìbus</hi> other men. <hi>Igìtur</hi> therefore <hi>ſtudia</hi> the ſtudies <hi>literárum</hi> of learning <hi>ſunt</hi> are <hi>dirigenda</hi> to be directed <hi>ad hoſce duos fines</hi> vnto theſe two ends <hi>proxìmos</hi> next <hi>et immediátos</hi> and immediate, <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lámus</hi> we may adorne <hi>ratiónem</hi> reaſon <hi>ſapientia</hi> by (or with) wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>ſeu</hi> or <hi>cognitióne</hi> by the knowledge <hi>Dei</hi> of God, <hi>natúrae</hi> of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>legum</hi> of lawes, <hi>et virtúte</hi> and by vertue: <hi>et</hi> and <hi>comparémus</hi> may get <hi>nobis</hi> to our ſelues <hi>facultátem</hi> the facultie <hi>oratiónis</hi> of ſpeach <hi>explicantis</hi> expreſſing (or declaring) <hi>bonas res</hi> good things (or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) <hi>purè ac perſpicuè</hi> purely and plainely. <hi>d. Extant ne</hi> whether are <hi>hi duo fines</hi> theſe two ends <hi>noſtrórum ſtudiórum</hi> of our ſtudies <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripti</hi> ſet downe (or deſcribed) <hi>apud authóres</hi> among others <hi>brevio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rìbus verbis</hi> in ſhorter words? <hi>p. Maxìmè</hi> yes truly. <hi>Perìcles enim</hi> for Pericles <hi>apud Thucydidem</hi> in Thucydides <hi>brevìter</hi> briefly <hi>et ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tundè</hi> and handſomely (or compactly) <hi>nomìnat</hi> expreſſeth; <hi>Scire</hi> to know <hi>quae</hi> what thiugs <hi>oportet</hi> it behooueth <hi>ſcire</hi> to know, <hi>et</hi> &amp; <hi>poſſe</hi> to be able <hi>elòqui</hi> to vtter aptly <hi>ca</hi> thoſe things: <hi>Luciánus autem</hi> but Lucian <hi>àppellat</hi> calleth (or nameth) them, <hi>cognitiónem</hi> the knowledge <hi>terum</hi> of things, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>facultátem</hi> the faculty <hi>explicandi</hi> of declaring (or expounding) <hi>eas</hi> them <hi>diſertè</hi> eloquently (or elegantly, <hi>id eſt</hi> that is, <hi>ſapientiam</hi> wiſedome <hi>et</hi> and <hi>eloquentiam</hi> eloquence. <hi>d. Quid autem</hi> but what <hi>vocas</hi> doe you call <hi>ſapientiam</hi> wiſedome? <hi>p. Sapientiam</hi> wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <hi>vt</hi> as <hi>ſacrae litèrae</hi> the ſacred Scriptures <hi>loquuntur</hi> doe ſpeake, <hi>nominámus</hi> we terme <hi>veram notitiam</hi> the true knowledge <hi>Dei</hi> of God, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>aliárum bonárum terum</hi> of other good things, <hi>coniunctam ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>cum vera pietáte</hi> with true deuotion <hi>erga Deum</hi> towards God; <hi>ſtultitiam verò</hi> but folly, <hi>ignoratiónem</hi> the not knowing, (or the lacke
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:980:20"/>
of knowledge) <hi>Dei</hi> of God, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>inobedientiam</hi> diſobedience <hi>erga Deum</hi> towards God. <hi>d. Quid autem eſt eloquentia</hi> but what is eloquence? <hi>p. Plato definit</hi> Plato doth define <hi>eloqùentiam</hi> eloquence <hi>graviſsìmè</hi> moſt ſubſtantially, <hi>poſſe</hi> to bée able (au abilitie) <hi>dicère</hi> to ſpeake <hi>grata</hi> things acceptable <hi>Deo</hi> to God. <hi>Nam</hi> for <hi>ad hunc vltìmum finem</hi> vnto this laſt and <hi>omnes homines</hi> all men <hi>debent referre</hi> ought to referre <hi>omnes ſuas actiónes</hi> all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>Deus condìtor</hi> God the Creatour <hi>agnoſcátur</hi> may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged <hi>et colátur</hi> and worſhipped <hi>à nobis</hi> of vs <hi>rectè</hi> rightly. 1 <hi>Cor. 10. Facìte omnia</hi> doe yée all things <hi>ad gloriam Dei</hi> to the glory of God. <hi>Quapropter</hi> wherefore <hi>et</hi> both <hi>in noſtris ſtudiis</hi> in our ſtudies, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>in actionibus</hi> in the actions <hi>totíus vitae</hi> of the whole life; <hi>ſempet</hi> alwaies <hi>haec vtiliſsima regula</hi> this moſt profitable rule <hi>debet eſſe</hi> ought to be <hi>in conſpectu</hi> in ſight. <hi>Fac</hi> make <hi>Deum</hi> God <hi>exordium</hi> the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>et finem</hi> and the end <hi>terum</hi> of things. <hi>Sit igìtur</hi> let there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be, <hi>finìs</hi> the end <hi>noſtrórum ſtudiorum</hi> of our ſtudies, <hi>ſapiens et e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquens piètas</hi> wiſe and eloquent godlineſſe, <hi>D. Dic quaeſo</hi> tell I pray, <hi>ex quibus doctrinis</hi> out of what doctrines <hi>illa ſapientia</hi> that wiſedome <hi>et eloquentia</hi> and eloquence <hi>potiſsimum</hi> moſt chiefly <hi>ſit</hi> is <hi>petenda</hi> to be fetcht. <hi>P. Sapientia</hi> with wiſdome <hi>ſeu rectò judicio</hi> or a right iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>de rebus</hi> concerning matters <hi>digniſsìmis</hi> moſt worthy <hi>cognitió<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> of knowledge, <hi>mentem homìnis</hi> the minde of man <hi>inſtrount</hi> there de inſtruct <hi>theologia</hi> diuinitie, <hi>et philoſophia</hi> and philoſophie, <hi>qua</hi> wherby (or wherein) <hi>complectìmur</hi> we comprehend, <hi>ſcientiam</hi> the knowledge <hi>legum</hi> of laws <hi>ſeu</hi> or <hi>praeceptótum</hi> of precepts <hi>de morìbus</hi> concerning manners, <hi>hiſtorias</hi> (and) hiſtories, <hi>quae exempla legum ſuppedìtant</hi> which finde (or miniſter ſufficiently) the examples of lawes, <hi>cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiónem naturalium terum</hi> (and) the knowledge of naturall things, <hi>et mathemàta</hi> and the learnings by demonſtration (or the mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call artes.) <hi>D. Ad intelligendam Oratiónem</hi> to vnderſtand the ſpeach <hi>aliórum</hi> of others, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>ad formandam noſtram rectè</hi> to frame ours rightly <hi>quid praecipuè requirìtur</hi> what chiefly is required? <hi>P. Artes dicendi</hi> the arts of ſpeaking, <hi>inprímis</hi> eſpecially <hi>grammatìcae</hi> the grammars <hi>linguae Latínae</hi> of the Latine tongue, <hi>et Graecae</hi> and of the Gréeke, <hi>et Ebraeae</hi> and of the Hebrow, <hi>docent</hi> doe teach <hi>intelligère rectè</hi> rightly to vnderſtand <hi>oratiónem</hi> the ſpeach <hi>in ſacris et prophánis ſcríptis</hi> in holy and prophane writings <hi>ſapientium et eloquentium au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thórum</hi>
                        <pb n="45" facs="tcp:980:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of wiſe and eloquent authors. <hi>Quarum linguárum monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis</hi> in the monuments of which languages <hi>cùm</hi> ſéeing that <hi>praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puae artes et hiſtoriae</hi> the chiefe acts and hiſtories <hi>contìneantur</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, <hi>cognitio</hi> the knowledge <hi>eárum</hi> of them <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>velut</hi> as it were <hi>janna</hi> a gate <hi>et elavis</hi> and a key <hi>qua</hi> whereby <hi>aditus</hi> an entrance <hi>aperí<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> is opened <hi>ad ſcientiam</hi> vnto the knowledge <hi>doctrinárum</hi> of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. <hi>Verò</hi> but <hi>ad formandam noſtram oratiónem rectè</hi> to frame our owne ſpeach rightly, <hi>praeter artes dicendi</hi> beſides the arts of ſpeaking, <hi>idonea natúra</hi> a fit nature, <hi>et lectio</hi> &amp; the reading <hi>atque imitatio</hi> &amp; alſo the imitating <hi>eloquentium ſcriptórum</hi> of eloquent writers, <hi>et aſſidua exercitatio</hi> and the continual exerciſe <hi>dicendi</hi> of ſpeaking <hi>acſcribendi</hi> &amp; of writing <hi>inprímis eſt neceſſaria</hi> is aboue other (principally) neceſſary. <hi>D. Cùm autem</hi> but wheras <hi>praecepta artium dicendi</hi> the precepts of the arts of ſpeaking <hi>non ſint finis</hi> are not the end <hi>noſtrórum ſtudiórum</hi> of our ſtudies, <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>inſtrumenta</hi> inſtruments <hi>tantummòdo</hi> only, <hi>quibus</hi> whereof <hi>in illis ſummis artìbus</hi> in thoſe greateſt arts, <hi>quae</hi> which <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent</hi> doe containe <hi>fontes</hi> the fountaines <hi>ſapientiae</hi> of wiſedame <hi>et elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentiae</hi> and of eloquence, <hi>et gubernant</hi> and doe gouerne <hi>actuentur</hi> and maintaine <hi>humanám vitam</hi> mans life, <hi>eſt nobis opus</hi> there is to vs néed (we haue néed) <hi>vt memìni</hi> as I remember <hi>te diſſerère</hi> that you did diſcourſe <hi>inter docendum</hi> at (or betweene) teaching, <hi>cupio ſcire ex te</hi> I deſire to know of you, <hi>quantum tempòris</hi> how much time <hi>ſit tribuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> is to be beſtowed <hi>iſtis artìbus</hi> on thoſe arts? <hi>P. Adoleſcens</hi> O lad, <hi>mones me</hi> thou putteſt me in minde <hi>rectè</hi> well. <hi>Non enim</hi> for not <hi>tota aetas</hi> the whole age <hi>debet aſsúmi</hi> ought to be taken vp in <hi>comparando inſtrumento</hi> in getting the inſtrument (or meanes) <hi>dialecticae</hi> of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke <hi>et Rhetorìcae</hi> and of Rhetoricke? <hi>Sed praeceptis cognìtis</hi> but the precepts being knowne <hi>neceſſariis</hi> neceſſary <hi>ad judicandum et dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum rectè</hi> to iudge and ſpeake rightly <hi>de rebus</hi> of matters <hi>(quae</hi> which <hi>poſſunt</hi> may <hi>facilè</hi> eaſily <hi>percìpi</hi> be perceiued <hi>et cognoſci</hi> and knowne <hi>intra vnum annum</hi> within one yéere, <hi>ſi fidélis monſtrátor</hi> if a faithfull ſhewer <hi>contingat</hi> chance <hi>ſtudióſo adoleſcenti</hi> to a ſtudious youth) <hi>ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim</hi> forthwith <hi>progrediendum eſt</hi> it is to be proceeded (one muit goe forward) <hi>ad ſummas</hi> vnto the chiefe points <hi>artium</hi> of the arts, <hi>quae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tìuent</hi> which do contain <hi>doctrínam</hi> the knowledge (or doctrine) <hi>terum</hi> of things (or matters,) <hi>et</hi> and <hi>exercitatio</hi> the exerciſe <hi>praeceptórum</hi> of the precepts <hi>adjungenda</hi> is to be adioyned. <hi>d. Ergo</hi> therefore <hi>vt</hi> as <hi>in caetèris artibus mechanicis</hi> in other mechanicall arts, <hi>ita</hi> ſo <hi>in ſtudiis</hi> in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:980:21"/>
the itudies <hi>doctrinarum</hi> of learnings, <hi>judicas</hi> thou iudgeſt <hi>eſſe</hi> it to be <hi>vſum ſolum</hi> vſe alone (or only) <hi>qui faciat</hi> which can make <hi>artifìces</hi> eunning workmen? <hi>P. Maximè</hi> yea truly, <hi>praeſertim</hi> eſpecially <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>natura idonea</hi> a fitte nature, <hi>ſi</hi> if <hi>magiſter</hi> a maſter <hi>boni judicii</hi> of a good iudgement, <hi>ſeu</hi> or <hi>gubernator</hi> a guider (or directer) <hi>exercitatiónis</hi> of the exerciſe <hi>vſu perítus</hi> by experience skilfull et <hi>fidélis</hi> and faithfull <hi>accédat</hi> be added to. <hi>D. Conſtitúto</hi> igitur <hi>fine ſtudiórum</hi> the end then of ſtudies being conſtituted, <hi>quem</hi> which <hi>dixiſti</hi> you ſaid <hi>eſſe</hi> to bée <hi>ſapientem et eloquentem pietatem</hi> wiſe and eloquent godlineſſe, <hi>quid porrò agendum eſt</hi> u hat further is to be done? <hi>P. primùm</hi> firſt of all ordine certo</hi> in a certaine (or true) order, <hi>quem fidus et vſu petitus praeceptor monſtrábit</hi> which a faithfull and by experience a skilfull teacher ſhall ſhew, <hi>attes</hi> the arts <hi>neceſſariae</hi> neceſſary <hi>vitae</hi> for life <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendae</hi> are to belearned, <hi>et velut</hi> and as it were <hi>per gradus</hi> by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grées <hi>ſcalárum</hi> of ladders <hi>tranſeundum eſt</hi> it is to be paſſed (procéeded) <hi>ab inferioribus</hi> from the lower <hi>ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uperiéres</hi> vnto the higher. <hi>D. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe</hi> peraduenturs <hi>eo conſilio</hi> for that intent <hi>fapiens antiquitas</hi> wiſe antiquity <hi>inſtituit</hi> appointed <hi>gradus</hi> degrées <hi>in ſcholis</hi> in ſchooles, <hi>et diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinxit</hi> and diſtincted (or diſtributed) <hi>artes ipſas</hi> the artes themſelues, <hi>vt</hi> that <hi>videlìcet</hi> to wit <hi>ſingùlos</hi> euery one ſeuerally <hi>velut in claſſes</hi> at it were into formes <hi>ſuo loco</hi> in its owne (or proper) place <hi>diſtribùtas</hi> diuided, <hi>ordìne et tempòre conveniente</hi> in a conuenient order and time <hi>juvenílis aetas</hi> young age <hi>facilius et rectiùs</hi> more eaſily and more right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>poſſit percipère</hi> may (or might) learne (or comprehend.) <hi>P. Rectè ſentis</hi> thou thinkeſt rightly (thou art of a right opinion) <hi>nam impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibile eſt</hi> for it is impoſſible, <hi>vt quis</hi> that any one <hi>faciat</hi> can doe <hi>multa</hi> many things <hi>ſimul</hi> together <hi>et eàdem</hi> and the ſame <hi>rectè</hi> well, <hi>vt</hi> as <hi>Xenòphon dixit</hi> Xenophon ſaid <hi>veriſsimè</hi> moſt truly. <hi>Et lex Platònis</hi> and the law of Plato <hi>eſt ſapientiſsima</hi> is moſt wiſe, <hi>quae</hi> which <hi>jubet</hi> diddeth <hi>vnumque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que civem</hi> euery Citizen <hi>diſcère</hi> et <hi>profitéri</hi> to learne &amp; profeſſe <hi>vnam artem</hi> one art <hi>tantummòdo</hi> only. <hi>Quare</hi> wherfore <hi>quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque artem</hi> what art ſoeuer <hi>adoleſcentes</hi> youths <hi>de conſilio praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tóris</hi> by the maſters counſell <hi>inſtituent diſcère</hi> ſhall begin to learne; <hi>Cognoſcant eam</hi> let them know it initio in the beginning <hi>ex vnico li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bello</hi> out of one alone little booke <hi>tantiùm</hi> only, <hi>qui</hi> which <hi>erudíta me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thòdo</hi> with a learned methode <hi>explicet</hi> may vnfold <hi>ſumniam artis</hi> the ſumme of the art <hi>diſtribútam</hi> diuided <hi>in certos locos</hi> into certaine (or ſet) places: <hi>Nec</hi> neither <hi>interea</hi> in the meane while <hi>ſumant in manus</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:980:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
let them take into hands <hi>alios libellos</hi> other little bookes <hi>ejuſdem argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti</hi> of the ſapre argument, <hi>priuſquam</hi> before that <hi>edidicèrist illum</hi> they haue learned it without booke. <hi>D. Quae</hi> what things <hi>aſſeruiſti</hi> you haue affirmed <hi>de ſummis artium</hi> concerning the ſummes of arts <hi>diſcendis</hi> to be learned <hi>tantùm</hi> only <hi>ex vnìco libello</hi> out of one alone lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle booke <hi>conſcripto</hi> written <hi>methòdìce</hi> methodically, (or, what things concerning learning the ſummes. &amp;c.) <hi>Omnia illa</hi> all thoſe things <hi>probantur mihi</hi> are approued of me, <hi>Nunc portô</hi> now further <hi>cupio au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>díre ex te</hi> I deſire to heare of you, <hi>quid ſit agendum mihi praecipuè</hi> what is to be done of mée chiefly <hi>in lectióne bonórum authórum</hi> in reading of good authors. <hi>P. In lectióne authórum</hi> in reading of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors <hi>(vt nihil dicam</hi> that I ſay nothing, <hi>de diligenti auſcultatióne</hi> of diligent hearkening <hi>et priváta repetitióne</hi> and priuate repeating, <hi>quae nullo modo eſt negligenda</hi> which by no meanes is to be neglected) <hi>vtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimum eſt</hi> it is moſt profitable, <hi>habére</hi> to haue <hi>commúnes locos</hi> the commune places <hi>diſtribútos</hi> diuided <hi>certo ordìne</hi> in a certaine order, <hi>ad quos</hi> vnto which <hi>omnia inſignia</hi> all notable (or remarkable) things <hi>et digna cognitióne</hi> and worthy of knowledge, <hi>quae occurrunt</hi> which occurre <hi>in lectióne authórum</hi> in reading of authors, <hi>annotentur</hi> may be noted (or regiſtred) <hi>et digerantur</hi> and may be digeſted <hi>velut in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas claſſes</hi> as it were into certaine rankes. <hi>D. Sed huic admonltióni</hi> but to this aduertiſement <hi>de colligèndis communìbus locis</hi> concerning gathering common places <hi>in certum librum</hi> into a certaine booke <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum platónis</hi> the ſaying of Plato <hi>in Phaedro</hi> in Pheadrus <hi>vidétur refragári</hi> ſeemeth to be againſt, <hi>quod monet</hi> which aduertiſeth, <hi>litèras et ſcripta</hi> that letters and writings <hi>adferre</hi> doe bring (or afford or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure) <hi>magis</hi> rather <hi>occaſiónem</hi> occaſion <hi>oblivióni et deſidiae</hi> to forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes and ſloathfulneſſe, <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>praeſidium</hi> helpe (or furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) <hi>memoriae</hi> to memory <hi>et</hi> and <hi>doctrínae</hi> to learning. <hi>Memìni e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam</hi> I alſo remember <hi>te vſurpáre</hi> that you vſe <hi>hanc ſententiam</hi> this ſentence <hi>crebris ſermònìbus</hi> in often ſpeaches: <hi>Vnuſquiſque exiſtìmet</hi> let euery one account <hi>ſe ſcire tantum</hi> that he know ſo much, <hi>non quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> not as <hi>adſervat ſcriptum</hi> he kéepeth written <hi>in libris</hi> in bookes; <hi>ſed</hi> but <hi>quantum</hi> as (or how much) <hi>tenet</hi> he holdeth <hi>memoria</hi> in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory <hi>fidelìter</hi> faithfully, <hi>et</hi> and <hi>habet promptum</hi> ready, <hi>vbi</hi> when as <hi>res</hi> matter <hi>ac vſus</hi> and vſe <hi>poſtùlat</hi> requireth. <hi>P. Vera quidem ſunt</hi> they are true things indéed, <hi>quae dicis</hi> which thou ſayéſt: <hi>ſed tamen</hi> but notwithſtanding <hi>habeo</hi> I haue <hi>quod reſpondeam</hi> what I can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:980:22"/>
                     <hi>Etſi</hi> although <hi>illa</hi> thoſe things <hi>quae</hi> which <hi>quis</hi> any one cupit deſireth <hi>meminiſſe</hi> to remember <hi>et ſcire</hi> and to know, <hi>debet inſcribère</hi> he ought to write in <hi>non chart is</hi> not papers, <hi>ſed anìmo</hi> but the minee; <hi>tamen</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>hi indìces</hi> theſe inderes (or ſummaries) <hi>et the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaúri</hi> and treaſures <hi>locorum</hi> of places, <hi>plùrimùm proſunt</hi> doe very much profit, <hi>ad recordationem</hi> vnto remembrance <hi>eórum</hi> of thoſe things, <hi>quae antea legìmus</hi> which wée haue read afore, <hi>aut didicìmus</hi> or haue learned, <hi>et velot inſtructum penu ſunt</hi> and are as it were a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed ſtore (or prouiſion) <hi>ex quo</hi> whereout <hi>ſtudióſi adoleſcentes</hi> ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious youths <hi>poſſunt depromère</hi> may fetch forth <hi>copiam</hi> plenty <hi>optimarum rerum</hi> of the beſt things, <hi>ſententiárum</hi> ſentences, <hi>ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinum</hi> ſimilitudes, <hi>hiſtoriárum</hi> hiſtories, <hi>et alia</hi> and other things <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus genèris</hi> of this kind <hi>cùm dicendum aut ſcribendum eſt</hi> when as it is to be ſpoken or written <hi>de alìqua re</hi> of any matter. <hi>D. Quid igìtur de memoria ſciendum eſt</hi> what then is to be knowne concerning memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>qùam Plutarchus nomìnat</hi> which Plutarch nameth <hi>promptuarium eruditiónis</hi> the ſtorehouſe of learning? <hi>P. Praecipuus cuſtos</hi> the chiefe kéeper <hi>et theſaúrus</hi> and treaſure <hi>eruditiónis</hi> of learning <hi>eſt</hi> is memoria memory, <hi>cui excolendae</hi> for adorning the which, <hi>et formandae</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into faſhion <hi>aſſiduo labóre ediſcendi</hi> by the daily labour of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by heart <hi>ſingùli ſtudióſi</hi> euery ſtudent <hi>debébunt</hi> ſhall be bound <hi>tribu ère certum tempus</hi> to bellow a certaine time <hi>ſingùlis diébus</hi> in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day. <hi>D. De arte autem memoriae</hi> but concerning the art of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, <hi>de qua</hi> wherof <hi>audio</hi> I heare <hi>Simonìde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chium</hi> that Simonides of Chios (or Caeos) <hi>et poſtea nonnullos alios</hi> and afterward ſome others <hi>tradidiſſe</hi> haue deliuered <hi>quaedam certa praecepta</hi> certaine ſure precepts, <hi>quid dicis</hi> what ſay you? <hi>P. Etſi</hi> although <hi>conſtat</hi> it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt <hi>memoriam iuvári diaetâ</hi> that the memory is holpen by diet, <hi>et bona valetudìne</hi> and good health <hi>et loco ſilenti</hi> and by a ſilent place, <hi>et matutíno tempòre</hi> and by the morning time, <hi>et certis notis</hi> and by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine notes (ſet markes:) <hi>tamen</hi> yet notwithſtanding <hi>ars memoriae</hi> the art of memory <hi>omnium optìma et certiſsìma eſt</hi> is the beſt and ſureſt of all, <hi>ediſcère</hi> to conne without booke <hi>multa</hi> many things <hi>aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duè</hi> daily (or continually,) <hi>et ſaepe repetère</hi> and often to repent <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dáta memoriae</hi> things committed to memory, <hi>ac ad vſum transferre</hi> and to turne vnto vſe. <hi>Si enim</hi> for if <hi>diſcentes</hi> learners <hi>neglìgènt</hi> will neglect (or haue little regard to) <hi>memoriam</hi> memory, <hi>et ſinent</hi> and will ſuffer (it) <hi>enervári</hi> to be weakened <hi>otio</hi> through idleneſſe <hi>deſidia</hi>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:980:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſlouthfulneſſe, <hi>torpóre</hi> drouſineſſe, <hi>aut deliciis</hi> delights, <hi>labor diſcendi</hi> the labour of learning <hi>erit</hi> will bée <hi>non mimìs inánis</hi> not leſſe vaine <hi>et ſupervacáneus</hi> and ſuperfluous, <hi>quàm ſi</hi> than if <hi>interea</hi> in the meane time <hi>ſcribèrent</hi> they did write <hi>in aqua</hi> in water, <hi>aut</hi> or <hi>mandárent</hi> did commit <hi>ſemìna</hi> ſéeds <hi>arénae</hi> to ſand (did ſow in the ſand.) <hi>quare</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>ſtatuas</hi> thinke thou for a ſuretie <hi>vnam</hi> that one <hi>ex praecipuis et maximè neceſſariis partìbus ſtudiórum</hi> of the chiefe and moſt neceſſary parts of ſtudies <hi>eſſe</hi> is, <hi>frequentem et aſſiduam exercitatiónem memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae</hi> the frequent and continuall exerciſe of thè memory, <hi>et labórem e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcendi multa</hi> and the labour of learning by heart many things. <hi>Poſt cultúram memoriae</hi> after the due ordering of the memory, <hi>quam</hi> which <hi>dixi</hi> I ſaid <hi>potiſsìmum</hi> moſt ſpecially <hi>eſſe</hi> is <hi>cuſtódem</hi> the kéeper (or <hi>eſſe potiſsìmum cuſtódem</hi> is the principall kéeper) <hi>cognitiónis</hi> of the knowledge <hi>rerum</hi> of things, <hi>ſeu</hi> or <hi>ſapientiae</hi> of wiſedome, <hi>praecipuum</hi> the chiefe <hi>et maxìmè neceſſarium inſtrumentum</hi> and moſt neceſſary meane (or helpe) <hi>verae et ſolidae eruditiónis</hi> of true and ſound lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nig, <hi>eſt</hi> is <hi>dilìgens et aſſidua exercitatio ſtyli</hi> the diligent and daily ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of ſtyle (or writing) <hi>directa</hi> framed <hi>ad imitatiónem ac formam eórum</hi> according to the imitation and forme of them, <hi>qui locúti ſunt</hi> which haue ſpoken <hi>prudenter</hi> wiſely, <hi>et perſpicuè</hi> and plainely, <hi>et ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganter</hi> and elegantly. <hi>Vt igitur Apelles</hi> as therefore Apelles, <hi>quoties</hi> as often as <hi>feciſſet</hi> he had made (or done, or might had done) <hi>nullum opus ſuae artis</hi> no worke of his art, <hi>velut</hi> as it were <hi>deplórans</hi> bewai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>jactúram</hi> the loſſe <hi>diéi</hi> of a day: <hi>ſolébat dicère</hi> he was wont to ſay: <hi>nullam bodielineam duxi</hi> I haue drawne no line to day: <hi>ita</hi> ſo <hi>ſtudióſi adoleſcentes ſinant</hi> let (or may) ſtudious youths ſuffer <hi>nullam diem elábi</hi> no day to paſſe (or ſlip away.) in <hi>que</hi> wherein <hi>non connectant</hi> they doe not compoſe <hi>vel epiſtòlam</hi> either an Epiſtle, <hi>vel partem ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis</hi> or part of an oration, <hi>vel verſus alìquot</hi> or ſome verſes. <hi>Ad hanc exercitatiónem ſtyli</hi> vnto this exerciſe of ſtyle (or penning,) <hi>si</hi> if <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſèrint</hi> there ſhall be added <hi>vtiliſsìma inſtrumenta</hi> the moſt profitable meanes <hi>parandae et confirmandae doctrínae</hi> of getting and confirming (or making ſure) learning, <hi>videlìcet</hi> to wit <hi>repetitiónes</hi> repetitions, <hi>et examìna</hi> diligent examinations (parſings,) <hi>item</hi> alſo <hi>diſputatiónes</hi> diſputations, <hi>et declamatiónes ſcholaſtìcae</hi> and ſcholaſticall declamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>non dubium eſt</hi> there is no doubt, <hi>quin</hi> but <hi>Deo fortunante noſtros labóres</hi> God proſpering our labours, <hi>facultas</hi> the ability <hi>judicandi</hi> of iudging (or vnderſtanding) <hi>et dicendi</hi> and of ſpeaking, <hi>ac ſcribendi</hi>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:980:23"/>
and of writing <hi>rectè</hi> rightly, <hi>quam initio hujus noſtri ſermónis</hi> which in begìnning of this our ſpeach <hi>dixìmus eſſe finem noſtrórum ſtudió<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> we ſaid was (or is) the end of our ſtudies, <hi>ſit ſecutúra</hi> will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. <hi>ex omnìbus autem</hi> but out of all the things, <hi>quae dicta ſunt</hi> which are ſaid (or haue béene ſpoken) <hi>facile vides</hi> thou eaſily ſéeſt, <hi>quòd dilìgens ſcholaſticus non ſit</hi> that he is not a diligent ſcholler, <hi>qui vagá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> which wandreth <hi>in ſtudiis</hi> in ſtudies <hi>ſine certa ratióne et ordìne</hi> without certaine reaſon and order, <hi>qui audit omnes lectiònes in ſchola quotidie ſine judicio</hi> which heareth all leſſons (or lectures) in ſchoole daily without iudgement, <hi>omnia dictáta excìpit</hi> beareth away all dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates (declarations tobe written, or inditures) <hi>et coacervat</hi> heapeth vp togither <hi>prolixas rapſodias</hi> long (or large) rapſodies (or compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of verſes,) <hi>vel quotidie perlègit</hi> or daily readeth through <hi>mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num numèrum paginárum</hi> a great number of pages, <hi>et graſſátur</hi> and procéedeth (or goeth on rouing) <hi>per multos ac varìos authóres</hi> through many and ſundry authors. <hi>Sed qui primùm</hi> but hée which firſt of all <hi>prudenter proſpìcit</hi> prudently foreſéeth (or looketh vnto) <hi>finem et me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam</hi> the end and the goale, <hi>ad quam ſtudia ſint dirigenda</hi> whereunto ſtudies are to be directed: <hi>deinde</hi> after that <hi>rectè elìgit media</hi> rightly chooſeth the meanes, <hi>neceſſaria ad aſſequendum illum finem</hi> neceſſarie to attaine that end; <hi>poſtea</hi> afterward <hi>in parandis ac tenendis illis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis</hi> in getting and kéeping (or preſeruing) thoſe meanes <hi>praeſtat in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiònem anìmi</hi> performeth (or maketh) a ſtraining of the minde, <hi>curam</hi> care, <hi>vigilantiam</hi> watchfulneſſe, <hi>aſsiduitatem</hi> continuall dui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, <hi>et labórem</hi> and labour. <hi>Sed de his quidem</hi> but about theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters indéed <hi>hactènus</hi> this farre (or ſo much.) <hi>Ego</hi> I <hi>quae</hi> what things <hi>de ratióne diſcendi</hi> concerning the way of learning, <hi>et ſtudiis rectè in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituendis</hi> and rightly framing ſtudies, <hi>partim</hi> partly <hi>memìni</hi> haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred <hi>eſſe</hi> to be <hi>tradìta</hi> deliuered <hi>à doctiſsìmis viris</hi> by moſt learned men, <hi>partim</hi> partly <hi>babui</hi> haue had <hi>cognìta</hi> knowne <hi>propria experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> by mine owne experience, <hi>et aſſiduo vſu</hi> and by the continuall vſe <hi>diſcendi</hi> of learning (or obſeruing) <hi>impertívi</hi> I haue imparted <hi>ea</hi> thoſe things <hi>tibi</hi> to thee <hi>libenter</hi> gladly <hi>et fidelìter</hi> and faithfully, <hi>quae vt ſint tibi magno vſui</hi> the which that they may be (or that the which may be) to thée great profit (or fruìt) <hi>precor deum toto pectóre</hi> I pray God with my whole heart. <hi>d. Quae tu</hi> what things you, <hi>prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiſsìme praeceptor</hi> moſt excellent maſter, <hi>de fine noſtrórum ſtudió<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> of the end of our ſtudies, <hi>de certo ordìne diſcendi</hi> of the certaine
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:980:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
order of learning, <hi>de dìſcendis ſummis artium</hi> concerning learning the ſummes of arts <hi>ex vno alìquo libello methodìcè ſcripto</hi> out of ſome one little booke written methodically; <hi>de colligendis locis communibus</hi> concerning gathering common places: <hi>de excolenda memoria</hi> of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing (or poliſhiug) the memory: <hi>de exercitatióne ſtyli</hi> of exerciſing of the ſtyle (or manner of penning:) <hi>de repetitionìbus et examinìbus</hi> of repetitions and parſings (or examinations:) <hi>Item</hi> like wiſe <hi>de di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputationìbus et declamationìbus ſcholaſtìcis</hi> of ſcholaſticall diſputings &amp; delaimings <hi>diſſeruiſti prudenter et gravìter</hi> you haue declared (or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed) wiſely and weightily, <hi>audívi haec cum tanta voluptáte</hi> I haue heard theſe things with ſo great pleaſure, <hi>vt ſperem</hi> that I hope <hi>illa fore vtiliſsìma</hi> that they ſhall be moſt profitable <hi>non ſohìn, mihi</hi> not only to mée, <hi>ſed et plurìbus aliis</hi> but to others more, <hi>cum quibus decrévi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municáre ipſa</hi> with whom I haue decréed to communicate them. <hi>Cùm autem ſciam</hi> but whereas I know, <hi>parem honórem et pretium</hi> equina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent (or méet) honour and reward <hi>non poſſe referri</hi> rendred (or giuen) <hi>à nobis</hi> by vs, <hi>praeceptoribus</hi> to maſters, <hi>qui impertiunt nobis</hi> which impart vnto vs <hi>veram ſapientiam</hi> true wiſdome, <hi>oro toto pectòre</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech with whole heart <hi>deum fontem omnis boni et ſalutáris doctrínae</hi> God the fountaine of all good and of wholeſome (or ſauing) doctrine, <hi>vt rependat tibi gratiam cumulátè</hi> that he recompence (or grant) fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to you aboundantly <hi>pro tuis ampliſsìmis beneficiis</hi> for your very great benefits <hi>in me</hi> vnto mée, <hi>et labóres noſtros gubemet et adjùvet</hi> and gouerne (or direct) and further our labours, <hi>et nos omnes doceat et regat</hi> and teach and rule vs all, <hi>vt diſcámus et doceámus</hi> that wee may learne and teach <hi>grata Chriſto</hi> acceptable things to Chriſt, <hi>et ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutaria eccleſiae ipſius ac nobis</hi> and ſauing for his Church and our ſelues. Amen. Finis colloquiórum</hi> an end of the dialogues (or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences.) <hi>In oratiónem clariſsìmi viri. d. Iohannis Poſſelii,</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the moſt famous man, maſter Iohn Poſſelius <hi>epigramma</hi> an Epigramme (or ſuperſcription.) <hi>Maxìma pars</hi> the greateſt part <hi>homìnum</hi> of men <hi>non cernit</hi> perceiueth not <hi>quomòdo vivat</hi> how it may liue; <hi>homo</hi> a man <hi>primùm</hi> firſt <hi>diſcit</hi> learneth <hi>vivère</hi> to liue, <hi>cùm vixit</hi> when he hath liued. <hi>Maxima pars juvènum</hi> the greateſt part of young men <hi>non cernit</hi> ſéeth not <hi>quomòdo diſcat</hi> how it may learne: <hi>diſcit diſcère</hi> he learneth to learne, <hi>vbi negat</hi> when as he denieth <hi>ſe didiciſſe</hi> that he hath learned. <hi>Sit lex divína</hi> let Gods law be <hi>nobis</hi> to vs <hi>regù<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> the rule <hi>piae vitae</hi> of a godly life; <hi>ſit ordo bonus</hi> let good order bee
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:980:24"/>
                  <hi>regùla</hi> the rule <hi>diſcendi ritè</hi> of learning well (or euen as it ſhould be.) <hi>Quem</hi> which <hi>haec oratio</hi> this oration <hi>pingens</hi> deſcribing <hi>perſpicuis ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> with euident tokens (or demonſtrations) <hi>eſt digna auro</hi> is worthy gold, <hi>digna Cedro</hi> worthy of Cedar (or immortalitie) <hi>probanda ſcholis</hi> to be approoued of ſchooles. <hi>Iohannes Frederus D.</hi> Iohn Freder doctor. <hi>De ratióne</hi> concerning the way (or feate) <hi>diſcendae ac docendae linguae latínae ac graecae</hi> of learning and teaching the latine and gréeke tongue, <hi>oratio Iohannis Poſſellij</hi> an oration of Iohn Poſſellius. <hi>Cum</hi> when as <hi>multa ſunt inventa atque inſtitúta</hi> many things haue been found out and inſtituted <hi>ſapienter</hi> wiſely <hi>à majoribus noſtris</hi> by our anceſtours, <hi>tum</hi> then <hi>nihil praeclarius</hi> nothing more excellent (was inuented and ordained) <hi>quàm</hi> than <hi>quòd</hi> than <hi>in hiſce publìcis congreſſìbus!</hi> in theſe publicke aſſemblies, <hi>voluérunt</hi> they would <hi>non ſolùm</hi> not onely <hi>idone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is hominìbus</hi> by méete men <hi>honeſta teſtimonia</hi> that honeſt teſtimonies <hi>vitae ac eruditiónis</hi> of life and learning <hi>tribui</hi> be giuen (or ſhewed,) <hi>ſed etiam</hi> but alſo <hi>oratiónes</hi> that orations <hi>habèri</hi> vs had (or made) <hi>de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis rebus</hi> concerning good things, <hi>quibus audítis</hi> which being heard, <hi>juv ènes</hi> yong men <hi>partim rectè erudirentur</hi> partly might be truly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed <hi>de ſuſcipienda &amp; ingredienda ratióne ſtudiórum</hi> of vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and entring into the way of ſtudies; <hi>partim excitarentur</hi> partly might be ſtirred vp <hi>ad amórem literárum &amp; virtútis</hi> vnto the loue of learning and virtue, <hi>partim exacuerentur</hi> partly might be whetted on (or encouraged forward) <hi>currentes ſponte</hi> running on (or procéeding) willingly. <hi>Non enim</hi> for (or truly) not <hi>ad oſtentatiónem eloquentìae aut doctrínae</hi> for oſtentation of eloquence or learning <hi>recitamus</hi> wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite (or openly reade or publiſh) <hi>noſtras oratiónes</hi> our orations: <hi>Sed vt imperátor bonus et induſtrins</hi> but as a good and induſtrious commander (or generall) <hi>inſtructa acie</hi> ín an army ſet in aray (ready to fight,) <hi>dat</hi> giueth <hi>tyroníbus</hi> to young ſouldiers <hi>quaedam certa prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta pugnandi</hi> certaine ſure precepts of fighting, <hi>dedúcit</hi> he diſwadeth <hi>á timóre</hi> from feare <hi>perterritos</hi> the ſore afraid ones, <hi>et hottátur</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth <hi>parátos ac fortes milìtes</hi> the ready furniſhed and valiant ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers <hi>ad pugnandum ſtrenuè</hi> to fight ſtoutly: <hi>ita nos ſolémus</hi> ſo we are wont <hi>in hiſce conuentìbus</hi> in theſe aſſemblies <hi>et imperitióres docére</hi> both to teach the vnſkilful ones <hi>et languentes excitáre</hi> and to encourage the languiſhing (or ſlouthfull) ones, <hi>&amp; inflammáre ad verum decus</hi> and to incenſe vnto true honour <hi>parátos</hi> the ready ones <hi>ac ingreſſos pleno gradu</hi> and hauing (or ſuch as haue) made entrance with a great pace
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:980:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
(or full ſtride.) <hi>Hi fines cùm nobis in dicendo propoſiti ſint</hi> whereas theſe ends are propoſed of vs in ſpeaking, <hi>non dubium eſt</hi> there is no doubt, <hi>quin omnes ſapientes viri</hi> but all wiſe men, <hi>cùm multos alios ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tères et honeſtos mores</hi> both many other ancient and honeſt cuſtomes <hi>cum</hi> and alſo <hi>hos ſcholaſticos gradus</hi> theſe ſchoole degrées <hi>et ſpectacùla promotiónum</hi> and ſpectacles of promotions, <hi>in quibus de ejuſmòdi bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis rebus diſſerìmus</hi> wherein we diſcourſe of good matters of this ſort, <hi>magnifaciant</hi> do make high account of, <hi>colant</hi> do honour, <hi>et putent eſſe</hi> and account to be <hi>ornanda</hi> things to be adorned <hi>et conſervanda</hi> and to be maintained. <hi>Cum autem</hi> but whereas <hi>hoc tempòre</hi> at this time <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio officij</hi> the conſideration of dutie <hi>impónat mihi neceſſitátem</hi> impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth on me a neceſſitie <hi>dicendi</hi> of ſpeaking, <hi>et encomia homìnum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantium</hi> and the praiſes of excellent men, <hi>ac rerum omnium conſenſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne laudatárum</hi> and of things praiſed by the conſent of all men, <hi>item</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>parainéſeis</hi> admonitions <hi>et vtìles adhortatiónes</hi> and profitable exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations <hi>ab alijs</hi> by others, <hi>qui eloquentia valent</hi> which are mightie in eloquence (or are of great eloquence) <hi>ſaepe hic recitátae ſunt</hi> are here of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes recited, <hi>breuìter indicáre decréui</hi> I haue decréed briefly to ſhew, <hi>qua ratióne</hi> by what way <hi>lingua latina et graeca</hi> the latine and gréeke tongue <hi>commòdè diſcenda et docenda ſit</hi> is to be learned and taught conueniently (or profitably.) <hi>Hoc argumentum etſí oratórem plenum atque perfectum requírit,</hi> although this argument requireth a compleate and perfect oratour: <hi>tamen cùm non tam verba et actio di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centis, quám res, quae dicuntur, ſpectandae ſint,</hi> yet notwithſtanding whereas not ſo much the words and action of the ſpeaker, as the things, which are ſaid, are to be conſidered, <hi>dicam de hac materia illa</hi> I will ſay of this matter (or argument) thoſe things, <hi>quae partìm ipſe longo vſu,</hi> which partly I myſelfe by long vſe (or practiſe) <hi>partima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liórum prudentium hominum judicio ac teſtimoniò edoctus</hi> partly taught by the iudgement and teſtimony of other prudent men, <hi>judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cábo vera eſſe</hi> ſhall iudge to be true, <hi>et cum ce ipſa congruère</hi> and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée with the matter it ſelfe. <hi>Ac á vobis, clariſſimi viriet ſtudióſi iuvè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, amanter peto,</hi> and of you O moſt famous men, and ſtudious youths (or yong men) I craue louingly (or as a friend) <hi>vt me benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè attentéque audiátis</hi> that you heare me gently (or fauourably) and attentiuely, <hi>quod veſtra ſponte facìtis</hi> which ye doe of your owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. <hi>Perficiam enim, deo juvante,</hi> for I will performe, God helping, <hi>vt fateamini me dixiſſe non omnino ineptè aut perpèram</hi> that ye may
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:980:25"/>
confeſſe that I haue ſpoken not altogether from the purpoſe or amiſſe, <hi>de re tam vtilì et neceſſaria</hi> of a matter ſo profitable and neceſſarie. <hi>Primùm autem vidétur mihi</hi> but firſt of all, it ſéemeth to me (that it is to be ſpoken) <hi>de tempóre</hi> concerning the time, <hi>quo puèri in ſcholas lat tínas ducendi,</hi> wherein youths are to brought into latine ſchooles, <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui labóres ipſis imponendi ſint</hi> and what labours (taſkes) are to bée impoſed on them. <hi>Deinde de exercitijs ſcribendi</hi> after that of the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of writing, <hi>et ratióne emendandi ſcripta,</hi> and the way (or reaſon) to amend writings. <hi>Poſtea</hi> afterward <hi>quando graeca debeant propóni</hi> when gréeke matters ought to be propounded, <hi>et quo ordìne &amp; modo illa tradi</hi> and in what order and manner (theſe ought) to be deliuered. <hi>Poſtrémò de exercitijs grae cis eſſe dicendum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt of all that is to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken concerning gréeke exerciſes. <hi>Puèri litèris adhibendi ſunt</hi> boies are to be ſet to learning <hi>anno aetatis ſex to vel ſeptìmo</hi> in the ſixth or ſeuenth yeare of age, <hi>ſi omníno fièri poteſt</hi> if at all it can be done, <hi>tunc enim in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genia</hi> for then wits <hi>non planè ſtupida &amp; tarda</hi> not vtterly (or quite &amp; cleane) dull and ſlow (or hard) <hi>ad percipiend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m doctrínam idonea ſunt</hi> are fit to receiue (or conceiue) learning. <hi>Et ſimùlac latína legère nouérunt</hi> and as ſoone as they know to reade latine (or latine wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,) <hi>proponendae ſunt illis octo partes oratiónis</hi> there are to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to them the eight parts of ſpéech <hi>ex puerili alìquo líbello compendióſè ſcripto</hi> out of ſome puerile (or belonging or fit for youth) little booke compendiouſly written, <hi>&amp; aſſuefiant ad ediſcenda paradig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>màta declinatiónum &amp; conjugatiónum</hi> and let them be accuſtomed to learne by heart the patternes of the declenſions and coniugations, <hi>&amp; vocabùla rerum ex compendio Hadriáni Iunij</hi> and the names (or terms) of thinge out of the abridgement (or ſhort forme) of Hadrian Iunius <hi>aur ſimili libello</hi> or from the like little booke, <hi>cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s germanìca verſio cum puerórum idiomàte congruat</hi> whoſe dutch tranſlation may agrée with the proper forme of ſpéech of the children. <hi>Quorſum enim at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>net</hi> for to what purpoſe pertaineth it (tendeth it) <hi>puèros reddère verba non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellecta pſittàci more</hi> that children do render words not vnderſtood in Parrat wiſe (or after the manner of a Parrat,) <hi>&amp; eos inutìli labóre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neráre</hi> and to burthen them with an vnprofitable labour? <hi>his addátur Cato</hi> to theſe may be added Cato, <hi>&amp; ſimilia dicta ſententióſa</hi> and the like ſententious ſayings, <hi>ex prouerbijs Salomonis &amp; Syracìde</hi> out of the prouerbs of Solomon and out of the ſonne of Syrach, <hi>propriè &amp; latíne reddìtis</hi> rendred (or tranſlated) properly and after the forme and faſhion of latine <hi>hi enim duos authóres</hi> for theſe two authers, <hi>longè ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pèrant
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:980:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
omnes gnomològo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſcriptóres</hi> farre ſurpaſſe all ſentence-vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring writers <hi>&amp; rerum bonitáte &amp; figurárum venuſtáte</hi> both in the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the things (or matters) and in the pleaſant grace of figures, <hi>quae puèris propriè &amp; perſpicuè explicentur,</hi> which may be expounded to the children properly and plainely, <hi>&amp; in cuius repetitióne ſingùlae voces examinentur,</hi> and in the repeating whereof all words particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may be examined, <hi>vt puèri diſcant</hi> that children may learne, <hi>&amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes oratiónis probè nouiſſe</hi> both well to know the parts of ſpéech, <hi>&amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acte nomina &amp; verba inflectère</hi> and exactly to decline nounes and verbs <hi>In his cùm annum vnum aut altèrum exercitàti ſunt</hi> when as they are (or haue béene) exerciſed in theſe things one yeare or two, <hi>proponen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>is grammatìca latína</hi> the latine grammar is to be propounded (or expounded) to them, <hi>breuìter &amp; neruóſè ſummam artis contìnens</hi> briefly and pithily containing the ſumme (or chiefe) of the art, <hi>quae aſſiduè tractanda, inculcanda, &amp; illuſtranda eſt</hi> which continually is to be handled, beaten into minde, and to be illuſtrated, <hi>exemplis ex pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bátis authoribus deſumptis</hi> by examples taken out of approued au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. <hi>Neque ìn his preceptis nimis diu magiſter ímmorabitur</hi> neither in theſe precepts a maiſter ſhall abide ouer long, <hi>vt quidem aliquando fit</hi> as alſo truly ſometimes it is done, <hi>&amp; ego memìni</hi> and I remember <hi>in quadam ſchola</hi> in a certaine ſchoole, <hi>grammat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cam ad finem perduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam eſſe</hi> that the grammar was brought to an end (or finiſhed, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued,) <hi>integro quinquennio</hi> in a whole fiue yeares ſpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e (or that the grammar was in teaching fiue whole yeares) <hi>cùm induſtrius praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor poſſit abſolvère cam facìlè ſex menſium ſpacio</hi> whereas an induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous teacher can eaſily diſpatch it in the ſpace of ſixe moneths. <hi>Neque propter alìquos hebètes &amp; ſtupìdos</hi> neither by reaſon of ſome ſlow and dull ones, <hi>alij bonae indòlis puèri negligendi ſunt</hi> other boyes of good towardneſſe or aptneſſe) are to be neglected. <hi>Saepe enim magiſtri vna &amp; eádem opèra</hi> for oftentimes maſters by one and the ſame labour, <hi>volentes inſeruíre multis, ijſque diuerſi progreſſus diſcipùlis</hi> willing to ſerue many ſchollers, and thoſe of a diuers progreſſe, <hi>remorantur &amp; impediunt alios bonos ingenio praedìtos</hi> do ſtay and hinder others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with a good wit. <hi>His igitur qui jam ſuperiorem claſſem aſcendé<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt</hi> to theſe therefore which already haue come vpon (or are paſt) the former fourme, <hi>epiſtòlae Cicerónìs, &amp; ſimilia ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ripta pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponenda ſunt</hi> the epiſtles of Cicero &amp; the like writings are to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. <hi>Vt autem puèri non nimis di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in diſcendis praeceptis grammatices
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:980:26"/>
detine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>di ſunt,</hi> but as youths are not to be detained ouer long in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the precepts of grammar: <hi>Sic damnanda &amp; explodenda eſt illó<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſententia</hi> ſo the opinion of them is to be condemned and to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, <hi>qui dicunt liberalia ingenia lab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re ediſcendi praecepta non one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randa</hi> that free wits (or courages) are not to be burthened with the labour of learning by the heart rules (or precepts,) <hi>ſed linguam la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinam lecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum auth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rum tantum diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndam eſſe</hi> but that the latine tongue is onely to be learned by the reading of good authours. <hi>Etſi enim praecepta &amp; regúlae grammaticae ad re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tè loquendum &amp; ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendum non ſuffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>unt</hi> for although precepts and grammar rules doe not ſuffice vnto ſpeaking and writing well: <hi>tamen propter maximas &amp; neceſſarias cauſas, diligenter &amp; accuratè diſci debent</hi> yet for very great and neceſſary cauſes they ought to be learned diligently and exactly. <hi>Et quia his puèris</hi> and becauſe vnto theſe boyes, <hi>quos ſecundae claſſis auditores nomìnò</hi> whom I terme ſchollers of the ſecond fourme, <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thóres proponuntur</hi> authors are declared (or read) <hi>non tam cauſa ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enciae ſeu rerum</hi> not ſo much for the ſake of wiſedome or matters, <hi>quam oratiónis formandae</hi> as of forming (or bringing into faſhion) the ſpeech <hi>praeceptor op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ram dabit</hi> the maſter ſhall giue endeauour, <hi>vt ſingulari diligentia monſtret puèris</hi> that with ſingular diligence he doe ſhew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the boyes <hi>vim &amp; ſignificationem ac pondèra verborum</hi> the force and ſignification, &amp; weightineſſe of words, <hi>item ſimilium ſeu ſynonymorum differentias</hi> likewiſe the differences of the like words or ſynonymaes (words of one ſignification) <hi>phraſes</hi> the faſhions of ſpeaking, <hi>compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiónem</hi> the compoſing together, <hi>&amp; ſimilem effi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gendae oratiónis ratió<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> and the like reaſon of e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>preſſing (or repreſenting) a ſpéech. <hi>Quod quò rectiùs &amp; commodiùs fièri poſſit</hi> to the end that the which may be done more rightly and more aptly, <hi>oſtendat in ſcriptis Cicerónis</hi> he may ſhew in the writings of Cicero, <hi>quae locutiónes à materna lingua diſcé<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant</hi> what ſpeakings do differ from the mother tongue, <hi>quomòdo hanc vel illam ſententia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> germanìcè explicarémus</hi> how we ſhould expreſſe this or that ſentence in duteh, <hi>item in quibus vernacùlam linguam imité<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur</hi> likewiſe wherein we may imitate the naturall language, <hi>in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus verò non</hi> and wherein not: <hi>vt hac ratióne puèri diſcant</hi> that by this meanes boyes may learne <hi>latinitátem à germaniſmis ſepará<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh latine from dutch manners of ſpeaking, <hi>&amp; purè &amp; eleganter latí<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè loqui ac ſcribère</hi> and to ſpeake and to write in latine both purely and elegantly, <hi>ac Cicerónis ſcripta inprímis amáre</hi> and eſpecially to loue
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:980:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the writing of Cicero, <hi>memòres dicti Quintiliáni</hi> being mindfull of the ſaying of Quintilian: <hi>ille ſciat ſe multùm profeciſſe,</hi> let him know that he hath much profited, <hi>cui Cicèro valdè placébit</hi> whom Cicero ſhal greatly like. <hi>Ante omnia autem cauendum eſt</hi> but before all things it is to be bewared, <hi>ne ſine diſcrimine ſcriptóres praelegantur</hi> that not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difference writers be read (before ſchollers) <hi>&amp; puèri turbentur va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria &amp; multiplìci authórum auditióne</hi> and boyes be troubled with ſundry and manifold hearing of authours, <hi>conſtat enim plaeroſque authóres</hi> for it is manifeſt that authours for the moſt part <hi>inter ſe diſſimill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mos eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe</hi> are among themſelues verie vnlike, <hi>non ſolùm tota oratiónis genère</hi> none onely in the whole kinde of ſpéech; <hi>ſed etiam vocìbus &amp; modis loquendi</hi> but alſo in words and manners of ſpeaking. <hi>Quòd multi bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni viri hoc noſtro tempòre</hi> as for that many good men in this our time, <hi>qui magnum labórem &amp; ſtudium in ſcientia aliqua praeclára &amp; vtili po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuérunt</hi> which haue beſtowed great labour and ſtudy in ſome famous and profitable ſcience, <hi>priuentur tamen illa vera gloria</hi> are notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding depriued of that true glory, <hi>quòd non literáta oratióne</hi> becauſe not in a learned ſtile (or ſpéech) <hi>ea quae tenent</hi> thoſe things which they hold <hi>poſſint vel proferre, vel litèris mandáre</hi> they can either expreſſe, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to letters (or writing,) <hi>nulla alia cauſa eſt</hi> there is none other cauſe <hi>quàm infaelicìtas primae aetatis</hi> than the miſfortune of the firſt age, <hi>quae aptis lection<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus &amp; neceſſarijs exercitijs</hi> which by fit leſſons (or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings) and neceſſary exerciſes, <hi>ad linguam latínam non eſt informáta</hi> was not informed (or faſhioned or inſtructed) vnto the latine tongue. <hi>Audio</hi> I heare ſay <hi>doctiſsimum virum lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>annem Capni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nem interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gátum</hi> that the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> learned man Iohn Capnion being demanded, <hi>cur hoc tempòre homìnes non tam docti eſſent</hi> why in this time men were not ſo learned, <hi>quàm temporibus Cicer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nis &amp; Quintili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni</hi> as in the times of Cice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o and Quintilian, <hi>reſpondiſſe</hi> anſwered, <hi>illos tunc ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buiſſe paucos libros</hi> that they then had few bookes, <hi>coſque bonos</hi> and the ſame good, <hi>quos diligenter &amp; aſſiduè legendo ſibi familiariſsimè con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feciſſent</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ich by reading diligently and continually they had made moſt familiarly knowne to themſelues; <hi>Nunc autem homìnes obrùere ſe variet te &amp; copia librórum</hi> but now that men ouerwhelme (or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themſelues found with the variety and multitude of bookes. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> verè cogitáre volùmus</hi> if we will conſider truly, <hi>non omnino errauit Capnion</hi> Capnion erred not altogether. <hi>Nuſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enim eſt, qui vbíque eſt</hi> for he is no where, which is euery where. <hi>Et qui, quò deſtináuit, pervenire vult,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:980:27"/>
and he which will reach through (or come home) whither he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, <hi>vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſequátur via<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> let him follow one way, <hi>non per multas vagé<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> let him not wander through many: <hi>iſtud non ire ſed erráre eſt</hi> that is not to go but towander, <hi>vt verè &amp; ſapienter-Senèca dixit</hi> as Senecaſaid truly &amp; wiſely. <hi>Quare explóſa è ludis puerórü praecipuè authórü multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine</hi> wherefore the multitude of authors chiefly being reiected forth of the ſchooles of children, <hi>vnum genus ſermónis idque optimum propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nátur,</hi> let one kinde of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>éech and that the beſt be propoſed, <hi>in quo tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſper deti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ur</hi> wherin ſo long let them be detained, <hi>dum poſsi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia purè &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ferre</hi> vntill they can vtter all things purely and in latine wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, <hi>et au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>ris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ac <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiam loquendo &amp; ſcribendo vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque expri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ère</hi> and after a ſort expreſſe the force and elegancy of the authour in ſpeaking and writing: <hi>&amp; dum ad alios vetères &amp; recen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiores ſcriptóres tutò admittentur</hi> and vntill they ſhall be ſafely admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto other ancient and later writers, <hi>quos non minori cam vtilitá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te quàm iudicio, pervolutabunt</hi> whom they ſhall turne often ouer (or reade ouer diligently, not with leſſe profit than iudgement. <hi>De exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citio latínè loquendi hic non dicam</hi> I will not ſpeake here conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning the exerciſe of ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ing of latine. <hi>Sciunt enim viri docti &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> for learned and wiſe men do know, <hi>id omníno neceſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ium eſſe</hi> that that is altogether neceſſary, <hi>&amp; ſine magno diſcentium incommodo neglìgi aut omitti non poſſe</hi> and cannot be neglected or omitted without the great hurt of the learners <hi>Qualia autem exercitia puèris proponenda ſint,</hi> but what manner exerciſes may be to be propounded to youths, <hi>paucis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicábo</hi> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ill ſhew in ſew words, <hi>ſi priús dixèro</hi> if I ſhall afore tell, <hi>quibus virtutibus ludimagiſtri &amp; paedag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gi praediti eſſe debeant</hi> with what vertues ſchoolemaſters and teachers of children ought to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued. <hi>Primùm neceſſe eſt eos, qui alios vtilìter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rudire volent, latínè do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctos eſſe</hi> firſt it is neceſſary that they be learned in latine, which will inſtruct others profitably: <hi>&amp; vias ac ratiónes docendi expeditiſsimas te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nére</hi> and to know the readieſt wayes and reaſons (or feats) of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: <hi>&amp; humanitáte ac <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> acultáte delectandi &amp; excitandi puèros valére</hi> and be of power (or of much e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imation) by reaſon of humanitie and the faculty of delighting and of ſtirring vp youths. <hi>Quomòdo enim poteſt alios docére</hi> for how can he teach others, <hi>qui ipſe purè &amp; emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dátè loqui nec poteſt,</hi> who himſelfe can neither ſpeake purely and without fault <hi>nec idipſum loquendo et pronunciando praeſtáre</hi> nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that very thing in ſpeaking and vttering <hi>quod à ſuis diſcipùlis
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:980:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
requirit</hi> which he requireth of his ſchollers? <hi>Deinde</hi> furthermore, <hi>cùm maxìmam vim habeat ad foelícem in ſtudiis progreſſum via &amp; ratio docentis</hi> whereas the way and manner of the teacher hath the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt force vnto an happy progreſſe in ſtudies, <hi>prudens magiſter omnia dextrè &amp; explicátè propónet</hi> a prudent maſter ſhall propound all things properly (or f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atly) and plainly, <hi>&amp; diſcipùlos in illis, quae pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posìta ſunt, vtilìter exercébit</hi> and ſhall profitably exerciſe the ſchollers in thoſe things, which are propounded; <hi>id autem, quomòdo fièri de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat, ſuo loco clàriùs oſtendémus</hi> but that, how it ought to be done, we will ſhew more manifeſtly in its place. <hi>Quantúm verò humanitas praeceptóris &amp; alacritátis &amp; amóris erga bonas litèras adfert</hi> but how much both cheerefulneſſe and loue vnto good learning the court<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of the maſter bringeth, <hi>tantùm ſaevitia &amp; crudelìtas tenèros &amp; imbecil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ìmos frangit, &amp; à ſtudiis deterret</hi> ſo much the fierceneſſe and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie doth daunt tender and weake mindes (or courages,) and doth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>right from ſtudies. <hi>Quare meminèrint praeceptóres</hi> wherefore ſhall (or let) maſters remember, <hi>Se erga diſcipùlos, vt erga filios, affectos eſſe oportère</hi> that they ought to be affected towards ſchollers, as to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſonnes, <hi>nec vel nimia auſteritáte</hi> nor either by ouermuch ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, <hi>vel plagis</hi> or by ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ripes, <hi>vel diris execrationìbus</hi> or by terrible cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, <hi>ignic ùlum à natúra datum, extinguère</hi> to quenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſparke gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by nature, <hi>ſed potiùs comitáte paterna excitáre &amp; inflammáre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bére</hi> but rather ought to ſtirre vp and to inflame (it) with a fatherly gentleneſſe. <hi>Neque ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ò haec ita accipienda ſunt</hi> neither truely theſe things are ſo to be taken, <hi>quaſi puèri ignávi &amp; contumáces debita poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na coercendi non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt</hi> as if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oathfull and ſullen (or ſtubborne) boies are not to be conſtrained (or kept in) by due puniſhment, <hi>aut vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis in ſcholis omníno non ſit vtendum</hi> or that one muſt not vſe rods at all in ſchooles, <hi>vt quidem nonnulli exiſtìmant</hi> as indeed ſome doe thinke. <hi>Nam vt pius et</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(philóſtorgos) pater edúcat ſuos libèros</hi> for as a godly and a louingly affectioned father bringeth vp his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>non ſolùm per</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (noutheſian) <hi>ſeu doctrínam</hi> not only by admonition or doctrine, <hi>ſed etiam per</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(paideían) hoc eſt, per aſſuefactiónem, quotidiána exercitia, exempla, et tempeſtivas caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiónes</hi> but alſo by diſcipline, that is, by inuring, daily exerciſes, examples, and ſeaſonable corrections <hi>nam haec quatuor appellatión<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diſciplínae continentur</hi> for theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oure are contained in the name (or naming) of diſcipline <hi>et memor dicti Salomonis</hi> and minde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:980:28"/>
ſaying of <hi>Solomon: Pater qui parcit virgae odit ſuum filium</hi> the father which ſpareth the rod, hateth his ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne: <hi>puèros petulantes ferùla cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> beateth the wanton (or malapert) boyes with the paulmer, <hi>eam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que collocat in conſpectu liberórum</hi> and ſetteth it in ſight of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, <hi>vt ſemper incurrens in ocùlos</hi> that alwaies comming vnto the eyes (or into their ſight,) <hi>eos in diſciplina retineat</hi> may retaine them in diſcipline, <hi>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> laſciviam coerceat</hi> and may reſtraine wantonneſſe. <hi>Ita praeceptóri</hi> ſo a maſter, <hi>qui parentum vicarius eſt</hi> which is one in ſtead of the parents, <hi>et eorum partes ſuſtìnet</hi> and executoth their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>vtendum eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>em mediis inſtitutióne diſcipulórum</hi> muſt vſe the ſame meanes in inſtruction of ſchollers; <hi>quare nec virgae nec aliae op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portúnae animadverſiónes</hi> wherefore neither rods, nor other conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent puniſhments, <hi>ex ſcholis tolli aut debe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aut poſſunt</hi> either ought or may be taken out forth of ſchooles. <hi>Eſt enim metus poenárum velut</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(Ergodió<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes)</hi> for the feare of puniſhments is as it were an haſtener forward of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orke, <hi>et cuſtos officii ac diligentiae diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulórum</hi> and a preſeruer of the duty and diligence of the ſchollers, <hi>ſine quo</hi> without which, <hi>maxìmè in hac delíra mundi ſenecta</hi> eſpecially in this doting old age of the world, <hi>cùm mores juventútis ad nimiam ignaviam et contumaciam incubuérunt</hi> when as the manners of youth haue béene inclined vnto ouermuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oathfulneſſe and ſtubbornneſſe, <hi>Florens illa aetas in officio retinéri non poteſt</hi> that flouriſhing age can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bée retained (or held in) in duty. <hi>Sed in omnibus modus eſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vandus</hi> but in all things meaſure is to be kept, <hi>et ira removenda</hi> and anger to be put a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ay, <hi>cum qua nihil rectè fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri, nihil conſiderátè po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt</hi> with which nothing can bée done rightly, nothing conſiderately. <hi>Sed jam ad id, vnde digreſſus ſum, revertar</hi> but now I will returne to that whence I digreſſed. <hi>Primum ſcribendi exercitationis genus eſt</hi> the firſt kinde of the exerciſe of writing is, <hi>puèro illa, germanìcè red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita proponère</hi> to propound to a boy thoſe things rendred in Dutch, <hi>quae in Ciceróne obſervanda eſſe audivit</hi> which he hath heard are to bée obſerued in Cicero, <hi>temporìbus, perſónis, locis, rebus etiam nonnihil commu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>átis</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imes, perſons, places, yea and the things ſomewhat altered, <hi>quae ad imitationem Cicerónis in Latinum ſermónem convertat</hi> which (the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oreſaid obſeruable matters) he may turne into Latine ſpeach after the imitation of Cicero. <hi>Ratio autem emendandi ſcripta omnium optìma <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſimpliciſsìma eſt</hi> but of all the beſt and moſt ſince<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e way of amending writings is (or the beſt and plaineſt way of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:980:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the writings of all is,) <hi>non praeceptóris arbitrio</hi> not according to the pleaſure of the maſter, <hi>ſed ipſius Cicerónis judicio</hi> but after the iudgement of Cicero himſelfe, <hi>puèri compoſitiónem emendáre</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the boyes compoſition (of words,) <hi>illiuſque epiſtòlam vel lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, ei proponère</hi> &amp; to propound to him his Epiſtle or place, <hi>ex quo ſcribendi argumentum deſumptum eſt</hi> from whence the argument of writing is taken, <hi>velut exemplar et ſpecùlum</hi> as it were a patterne and looking-glaſſe, <hi>in quo videat</hi> wherein he may ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>quid ſuo labóri deſit</hi> what is wanting to (or for) his labour. <hi>Nihil autem pernitiòſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſtudiis linguae Latínae accidère poteſt</hi> but nothing can happen more pernicious to the ſtudies of the Latine tongue, <hi>quàm quòd puèri, neglecta omni imitatióne</hi> than that boyes all imitation neglected, <hi>à ſuis magiſtris magis quàm à Ciceróne ipſo,</hi> of their maſters rather than of Cicero himſelfe, <hi>et ſimilibus authoribus bonis</hi> and other like<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, <hi>latinittá<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m diſcère coguntur</hi> are enforced to learne Latine. <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céditeò</hi> there appertaineth to this matter (or moreouer then this) <hi>quòd illa ſaepe praeceptóres puèris vertenda praeſcribunt</hi> that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times maſters preſcribe thoſe things to be tranſlated by the boyes (or preſcribe to the boyes thoſe things to be tranſlated,) <hi>quorum vel appellatiónes vel loquendi modos nunquam antea audívérunt</hi> wherof ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the names or manners of ſpeaking they neuer heard afore. <hi>Imò quae ipſi praedagógi, quomòdo rectè et propriè reddenda ſunt, ignórant</hi> yea which the ſchoolemaſters themſelues know not how they are to be rendred rightly and properly. <hi>Quare ante omnia cavébit praeceptor</hi> wherefore before all things the maſter ſhall beware, <hi>ne puèrum vel ſcribère vel loqui permittat</hi> that he ſuffer not the boy either to write or to ſpeake, <hi>niſi iſtis modis et rationibus quas non à ſe, ſed ab optìmis au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorìbus didicèrit</hi> vnleſſe in thoſe manners and formes, which he hath learned not from him, but from the beſt authors. <hi>Quòd ſi tale argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum propoſitum eſt</hi> that if ſuch an argument (or matter to bee written of) be propound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, <hi>cujus exemplum intègrum in authóre non extat</hi> whereof a whole example is not extant in an author, <hi>vt nec ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per extáre poteſt</hi> as neither alwaies it can be extant, <hi>emendátor illud ipſum argumentum quod diſcipùl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tractárunt, propriis verbis et phrasì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus praeclárè retextum et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>laborátum illis propónat</hi> the correctour may propound that very argument which the ſchollers haue handled, very well changed cleane otherwiſe and elaborated (or eractly done with ſtudy,) in proper words and phraſes, <hi>in quo ſicut et in Ciceró<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:980:29"/>
cernant</hi> in which as euen in Cicero they may ſée, <hi>quld ſuo ſcripto deſit</hi> what is wanting to their owne writing, <hi>&amp; quantum ab illa for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma diſcrèpet</hi> and how much it differeth from that forme. <hi>Deinde vbi aliquandiu in hoc exercitio verſáti ſunt</hi> afterward when as ſome while they haue béene conuerſant in this exerciſe, <hi>&amp; in eo aliquid profecé<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt</hi> and haue profited ſome what therein, <hi>ad majora deducendi ſunt</hi> they are to be led along vnto greater matters, <hi>&amp; curandum</hi> and it is to be cared, <hi>vt Cicerónis ſcripta facilióra</hi> that the eaſier writings of Cicero, <hi>&amp; praecipuè epiſtòlas ad verbum à praeceptóre germanìco ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mónere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> chiefly the Epiſtles by the maſter rendred accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word (word for word) in the Dutch ſpeach, <hi>non inſpecto exemplári</hi> the patterne (or coppie) not looked into, <hi>ſuo marte latínè vertant</hi> by their owne proper wit (or endeauour) doe turne into La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, <hi>quae ad eundem, quem dixi, modum emendandae ſunt</hi> which are to be amended after the ſame manner which I ſaid. <hi>Quod ſi aſsiduè fit</hi> the which if it be continually done, <hi>non dubium eſt</hi> there is no doubt, <hi>quin facìlè puèri ad purè &amp; eleganter ſcribendum aſſueſíant</hi> but eaſily the boyes may be inured to write purely and elegantly. <hi>Vt enim foras, cùm in ſole ambulámus</hi> for as when we walka broad in the Sun, <hi>etiamſi ob aliam cauſam ambulémus</hi> although we walke for another cauſe, <hi>tamen colorámur</hi> notwithſtanding wee are ſteyned (or colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red:) <hi>ſic fièrinón poteſt</hi> ſo it cannot come to paſſe, <hi>quin cùm hoc modo puer exercétur</hi> but when as a boy is erecciſed in this manner, <hi>ejus o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio aſſiduo illo vſu &amp; conſuetudìne colorétur</hi> his ſpeach by that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall vſe and cuſtome may bee died (or haue a timture) <hi>&amp; puritá<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ac ſuavitátem quandam Ciceroneánam redoleat</hi> and may ſauour of a certaine Ciceronian puritie and ſweetneſſe (or pleaſantneſſe.) <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium exercitii genus eſt</hi> the third kinde of exerciſe is, <hi>oratiónem latí<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, aliis verbis Latínis, &amp; Ciceróni vſitátis, exprimère</hi> to expreſſe a Latine ſpeach in other Latine words, and alſo much vſed of Cicero. <hi>Verum id exercitium non ad hos puèros, ſed ad perfectióres, &amp; cos ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis, qui charactérem oratiónis effingère, quam qui Latínè tantum loqui &amp; ſcribère diſcunt, propriè pertinet</hi> but that exerciſe properly pertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not to theſe boyes, but vnto perfecter, and thoſe rather which learne to reſemble a ſtile of ſpeach, (or to deuiſe a like forme of words,) than which learne only to ſpeake and write in Latine. <hi>Vt autem haec ſcribendi exercitia diligenter &amp; fideliter colenda ſunt</hi> but as theſe exerciſes of writing are to bee practiſed diligently
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:980:29"/>
&amp; faithfully: <hi>Sie et latinè lo quendi exercitátio, de qua paulò ante dixi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quàquam, neglìgi debetſo</hi> alſo the exerciſe of ſpeaking in latine, wherof I ſpake a little before, in no wiſe ought to be neglected. <hi>Quod quò rectiùs fièri poſſit</hi> the which that it may be done the righter (or to the end that the which may be done more rightly.) <hi>Cuſtodes ſeu corycéi conſtituendi ſunt</hi> watchers or ſpies are to be ſet, <hi>qui et juniores teuto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nìcè loquentes, et grandióres vel Germaniſmis vel ſoloeciſmis, vel denì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que barbariſmis vtentes, annòtent</hi> which may note (or put in writing) both the younger ſpeaking Leutonicely (or in low Dutch,) and the elder vſing either Germaniſmes (or proprieties of the high Dutch) or incongruities; or finally Barbariſmes, <hi>et ad magiſtrum defèrant, à quo iuſta poena afficiantur</hi> and may appeach (or report them) vnto ths maſter, by whom they may be afflicted with iuſt puniſhment (or bée duly puniſhed.) <hi>Vtrumque enim exercitium</hi> for both exerciſes, <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiné ſcribendi et loquendi</hi> of writing and ſpeaking in Latine, <hi>in Latí<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſcholis vigére debet</hi> ought to flouriſh (or bee in force) in Latine ſchooles, <hi>nec altèrum ab altèro ſeparári poteſt</hi> neither can the one bée ſeuered from the other. <hi>Nam vt prudentis et induſtrii informatóris eſt</hi> for as it is the part of a wiſe and induſtrious inſtructer, <hi>indicáre et proponère puero</hi> to ſhew and to propound to a boy, <hi>illa quae ſingulári ſtudio, obſervanda, exercenda, et imitanda ſunt</hi> thoſe things which with ſingular ſtudy are to be obſcrued, exerciſed, and imitated: <hi>Sic is eàdem non ſolùm ſcriptione, ſed etiam locutióne, imitabìtur</hi> ſo hee ſhall imitate the ſame, not only in writing, but alſo in ſpeaking. <hi>Dixi de ratióne ſervanda in inſtituendis puèris in lingua latína</hi> I haue ſpokeu of the forme to be kept in inſtructing youths in the Latine tongue, <hi>vſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad annum aetátis vndecimum aut duodecìmum</hi> euen vntill the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth or twelfth yeare of age: <hi>Reſtat nunc, vt brevìter diſsèram de ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tióne tradendae et diſcendae linguae Graecae</hi> it remaineth now that I briefly diſcourſe of the manner of teaching and learning the Gréeke tongue. <hi>Quòd pauci noſtrùm conſequuntur alìquam mediòcrem cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiónem Graecae linguae</hi> that few of ours doe attaine any meane (or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different) knowledge of the Gréeke tongue, <hi>vel quòd ſtudíum ejus vidétur nobis perdiſficile</hi> or that the ſtudy thereof ſeemeth to vs very hard, <hi>nulla alia cauſa eſt</hi> there is none other cauſe, <hi>quàm quòd aut ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius ſuſcipimus hoc ſtudium</hi> than that either ſomewhat late wée vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake this ſtudie; <hi>aut ſi ſuſcipimus</hi> or if wee doe vndertake, frigìdè in eo verſámur</hi> wée are coldly (remiſſely) conuerſant in it, <hi>nec eo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:980:30"/>
et modo, quo decet, in eo progredimur</hi> neither in that order, and manner, wherein it becommeth, doe wée procéed therein. <hi>Vt autem in omnibus aliis rebus rectè, tempeſtìvè, et foelicìter perficiendis</hi> but as in all other things to bee performed rightly, ſeaſonably, and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly: <hi>Sic et in diſcendis graecis litèris</hi> ſo alſo in learning the Gréeke tongue, <hi>ordo conveniens omninò neceſſarius eſt</hi> a conuenient order is altogether neceſſarie. <hi>Quare vbi ab anno aetátis ſexto vel ſeptimo</hi> wherefore when as from the firth or ſeuenth yeere of age <hi>vſque ad annum vndecimum</hi> euen vntill the eleuenth yeere, <hi>in latina, lingua, ea, qua dixi, ratióne puèri exercitáti ſunt</hi> boyes are exerciſed in the Latins tongue, in that manner wherein I ſaid, <hi>(his enim ſex annis, niſi planè tardi et indociles ſunt, linguam Románam vtcunqne diſcère poſſunt</hi> for in theſe ſixe yéeres, vnleſſe they bée vtterly ſlow and vnteachable, they may learne the Latine tongue after a ſort (or ſo ſo.) <hi>Graeca vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabula ex evangeliis, vt vocant, dominicalibus, ipſis proponantur,</hi> the Gréeke wdrds out of the Goſpels, as they call Domimcall ones, (or Sundaies ones) let be propounded to them, <hi>quorum quotidie aliquot ediſcant recìtent,</hi> whereof ſome daily let them learne by heart, let them recite, <hi>et octávo quoque die illa, quae praeterìta hebdomàde didi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cérunt, ab initio repètant,</hi> and on euery eighth day let them répeate thoſe things from the beginning, which they haue learned in the wéekepaſt. <hi>Vt enim liberalia ingenia facillimè res bonas arripiunt et addiſcunt</hi> for as franke witts moſt eaſily take quickly and learne good things: <hi>Sic eadem ipſis facilè excidunt</hi> ſo the ſame things eaſily doe ſlip from them, <hi>ſi non diligenti et aſsidua repetitióne inculcentur</hi> if they bée not poured in (or beaten into memory) by diligent and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all repetition. <hi>His paradigmàta declinationum et conjugatiónum grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cárum addantur,</hi> to theſe things let be added the patternes of the Gréeke declenſions and coniugations, <hi>in quibus certis diébus exercen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ſunt</hi> in which they are to be exerciſed certaine daies. <hi>In hoc ſtudio cùm annum conſumpſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>runt</hi> when as they haue ſpent a yeere in this ſtudie, <hi>evangelia graeca, non inſpecta verſione latína interpretári jube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buntur</hi> they ſhall bee bid to interpret the Gréeke Goſpels, the Latins tranſlation not looked in. <hi>Et quia hujus claſsis auditoribus nunc gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matìca graeca intègrè proponìtur,</hi> and becauſe to the ſchollers of this forme now the Gréeke grammer is propounded entirely, <hi>non ſolùm in nomìnum ac verbórum inflexionìbus, ſed etiam in temporìbus verbó<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum actívae, paſsívae, et mediae vocis formandis, ac regulis graecae Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxeos
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:980:30"/>
praecipuis et maximè neceſſariis cum vno et altèro exemplo edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendis opèram ponent</hi> they ſhall beſtow viligence not only in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinings of nounes and verbes, but alſo in forming the tences of verbs of the actiue, paſſiue, and <hi>medium</hi> (or middle or meane) voice, and in cunning by heart the chiefe and moſt neceſſary rules of the Gréeke Syntaris with one or another example. <hi>Diligenter autem et accurátè, vt dixi, hiſce puèris Grammatìca graeca ediſcenda eſt</hi> but dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and accurately, as I ſaid, the Gréeke grammer is to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without booke by theſe boyes, <hi>quam qui tenet</hi> the which hée that kéepeth in remembrance, <hi>ſciat ſe deuoraſſe maxìmam partem moleſtiae</hi> let know that hee hath ſuſteined and paſſed ouer the greateſt part of the totle, <hi>quae ſuſcip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enda et perferenda eſt in diſcenda hac lingua</hi> which is to be vndertaken and ſuſteined in learning this tongue. <hi>Propóni autem quatuordècim, quindècim vel ſedècim annórum adoleſcentùlis debent Socràtis oratio ad Demonìcum et Nicoclem, et illa, quae Nicocles inſCribìtur</hi> but to lads of fouretéene, fiftéene or ſixtéene yéeres, there ought to be propounded the oration of Socrates vnto Demonicus and Nicocles, and that, which is intitled Nicocles; <hi>Plutarchi paeda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogia</hi> Plutarchs pedagogie (or treatiſe of training vp young chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,) <hi>facilióres et lepidióres dialògi Luciáni</hi> the eaſier and pleaſanter dialogurs of Lucian, <hi>et fabùlae Aeſópi</hi> and Ieſops fables: <hi>Ex quibus praeter verbórum copiam</hi> out of which beſides the ſtore of words, <hi>phraſes et variárum rerum appellatiónes</hi> the phraſes and names of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers things, <hi>magnam ſapientiae partem de gubernandis conſiliis,</hi> a great part of the wiſedome concerning gouerning intents (or aduices,) <hi>actionibus et moribus</hi> actions and manners, <hi>ſine vllo taedio tenèra a tas diſcère poteſt</hi> tender age may learne without any wearineſſe of minde. <hi>Et quia variètas delectat, ac voluptátem parit</hi> and becauſe va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie delighteth and cauſeth pleaſure, <hi>graeca poemàta, cujuſmòdi ſunt, aurea carmìna Pythagòrae, Phocylìdes et poſtea Heſiòdus, ac quidam li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bri Homéri, lectióni oratórum admiſcendi erunt</hi> Gréeke poemes, of which ſort are, the golden vorſes of Pythagoras, Phocylides, and afterward Hefiod, and certaine bookes of Homer, ſhall bee to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddled to the reading of Drators. <hi>His auditoribus, ſingulis ſcp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timánis breve argumentum Latínum proponendum eſt</hi> to theſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, in euery wéeke a ſhort Latine argument (or ſumme of a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter written) is to bée propounded, <hi>quod ad imitatiónem Iſocràtis, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthènis, et ſimilium authórum, in graecum ſermónem convertant</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:980:31"/>
which after the imitation of Iſocrates, Demoſthenes, and of like authors, they may turne into the Gréeke ſpeach. <hi>Nam vt in linguà Latína optìmos quoſque authóres et legìmus et imitámur</hi> for as in the Latine tongue wée both read and imitate all the beſt authors: <hi>Sic et in graeca idem facère, et noſtram oratiónem ad graecórum authorum ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monem effingère debémus</hi> ſo alſo wée ought to doe the ſame in the Gréeke tongue, and to frame our ſtile according to the ſpeach of the Gréek authors. <hi>Nec imitandi ſunt, qui ex dictionario, vel Synonymis graecis, epiſtólas graecas, aut verſus conſarcináre ſolent</hi> neither are they to be imitated, which are wont to patch vp gréeke Epiſtles, or verſes out of a Dictionary, or greeke Synonymaes. <hi>Debet etiam hitce, de quibus dixi, diſcipùlis, liber aliquis epiſtolarum Ciceronis, qui facilior et elegantior videbitur, prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni, quem ordine graecè vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t, et praecep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tóri certis horis exhibeant,</hi> there ought alſo to be propounded to theſe ſchollers, of whom I haue ſaid, ſome booke of the epiſtles of Cicero, which ſhall ſeeme the eaſier and the eleganter, which in order they may turne into Greeke, and may ſhew to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> at certaine houres. <hi>Hoc enim ſi fecèrint, eádem opèrà purit tem latíni ſermonis et graecam linguam addiſcent</hi> for this if they will doe, with the ſame la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour they ſhall learne the puritie of the Latine ſpeach, and the Greek tongue. <hi>Emendandi autem haec ſcripta, via expeditiſsima eſt;</hi> but the readieſt way to amend theſe writings is, <hi>Primùm vitia, ſi quae ſunt, comìter indicáre, et vel ipſum authórem, ex quo argumentum ſcribendi depromptum eſt, vel praeceptóris elaborátain verſiónem quam cum ſua confèrant, ipſis ob oculos proponère,</hi> firſt of all gently to ſhew the faults, if there be any, and to ſet to them before the eyes, either the author himſelfe, from whom the argument of writing is taken out, or the maſters tranſlation exactly done, which they may compare with their owne. <hi>Ad hoc vtile exercitium, et illud accedère debet, vt certis quibuſdam horis nihil aliud ipſis loqui liceat, niſi graecè.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto this profitable exerciſe, alſo this ought to be added, that it be lawfull for them in certaine appointed houres to ſpeake no other thing (no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe) than in Greeke. <hi>Vt enim in lingua Latína, ſic et in graeca illa, quae puer audívit, non ſolùm ſcribendo, ſed etiam loquendo ad vſum transferre docet</hi> for as in the Latine tongne, ſo alſo in the Greeke, thoſe things, which the boy hath heard, hee teach to transferre (or turne) to vſe, not only by writing, but alſo by ſpeaking. <hi>Neque eſt quod quiſquam vereátur, ne puèri difficultáte quadam aut obſcuritáte,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:980:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
à ſtudio hujus linguae deterreantur</hi> neither is there (cauſe) that any one feare, leaſt boyes by ſome difficultie or obſcurity, bee deterred from the ſtudie of this tongue. <hi>Nam vt ipſi natúrâ peregrinárum lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guárum amantes ſunt, eaſque facìlè ad diſcunt,</hi> for as they by nature are louers of forraigne languages, and doe learne them eaſily: <hi>Sic nulla alia lingua jucundiòr eſt, nec ſuavióre ſono amìbus illabitur, quàm grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> ſo no other tongue is more pleaſant, neither with a ſweeter ſound entreth into the eares, than the Greeke. <hi>Quare vt requies ſuave con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimentum laboris eſt vt graecum dictum,</hi> wherefore as reſt is the ſweet ſauce of labour, as the Greeke ſaying, <hi>he anó pauſis</hi> reſt <hi>eſtin</hi> is <hi>ártu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> the ſauce <hi>tòn ponôn</hi> of laboure <hi>monet</hi> aduertiſeth: <hi>Ita graecárum literárum ſtudium reliquis diſcendi laborìbus non modò taedium nullum adfert, ſed eos etiam jucundi res reddit, et quadam oblectatióne ac vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptáte tanquam ſale perſpergit</hi> ſo the ſtudie of the Greeke tongue not only bringeth no yekiomiteſſe to the remaining labours of learning, but maketh them alſo more pleaſant, and ſpringleth them all ouer with certaine delight and pleaſure as with ſalt. <hi>Quod autem de grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae linguae ſtudio ejuſque exercitis hacrènus dixi,</hi> but what hitherto I haue ſpoken concerning the ſtudie of the Greeke tongue, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes thereof, <hi>non ita intelligendum eſt</hi> it is not ſo to bee vnderſtood, <hi>quaſi interealatinae lectiónes prorſus omittendae aut de ponendae vel eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am muſica, Arithmetìca et initia dialectìces et rhetorìces, his grandiorìbus non vnâ tradendae ſint</hi> as if in the meane while latine readings hee (or were) altogither to be omitted or laid aſide, or alſo muſicke a ithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, and the beginnings of Logicke and Rhetoricke not to bee togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taught to thoſe elder (or of more yeeres.) <hi>Debet enim ſimul ac latinae linguae fundamentum jactum eſt, vtriuſque linguae, latinae et grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae, ſtudium ſimul in ſcholis ſlorére et dominári</hi> for as ſoone as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Latine tongue is laid, the ſtudie of both tongues, the Latine and the Greeke, ought to flouriſh and to haue the ſouaraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie togither in the ſchooles. <hi>Maximè cùm haec linguarum inter ſe colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio tantas habeat opportunitátes, vt vtramque hoc modo et citiùs et faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liùs ſimul, quàm altèram ſeparátim puèri diſcère poſſint</hi> eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that this comparing of languages betweene themſelues hath ſo great commodities, that by this meanes boyes may learne both ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and eaſier both togither, than one apart. <hi>Vt enim latina lingua ſine graeca non intelligìtur, ſic ne graeca ſine latina explicári et tradi poteſt</hi> for as the Latine tongue without the Greeke is not vnderſtood, ſo not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:980:32"/>
the Greeke without the Latine can bee expounded and taught (or deliuered.) <hi>Caetèrae etiam artes, quarum modò mentio facta eſt, cùm recreatiónis, tum vtilitátis et neceſſitátis cauſà, ſimul caetèris Latínè et graecè diſcendi laborìbus admiſcendae ſunt</hi> the other arts alſo, whereof now mention was made, both for the ſake of recreation, and alſo of profit and neceſſitie, are to bee intermeddled togither to the other la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of learning Greeke and Latine. <hi>Debent autem illi, qui aetáte et eruditióne provectióres ſunt, illuſtres authórum locos, inſignes narratió<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes et hiſtorias, ex graeca lingua in Latinam, et ex latina in graecam ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tère</hi> but they which are riper (or forwarder) in age and learning, ought to turne out of the Greeke tongue into the Latine, and out of the Latine into the Greeke, the renouned places of authors, the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table diſcourſes and the hiſtories. <hi>Sed meminèrint ſtudióſi, in conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendis è graeca lingua in Latinam, et contra, ſcriptis, non ſemper verbum ex verbo exprimendum eſſe, ſed dandam eſſe opèram, vt ſi quid abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reat à conſuetudìne et more ejus ſermónis, in quem alìquid convertétur, id omittátur on nino.</hi> But ſtudents ſhall remember (or let ſtudents remember) in tranſlating writings out of the Greek tongue into the Latine, and contrariwiſe, that not alwaies word is to bee tranſlated out of word (or that they muſt alwaies tranſlate word for word) but endeauour is to bee giuen, that if any thing diſagreeth from the cuſtome and manner of that ſpeach, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into ſomething ſhall bee tranſlated, it be omitted altogither. <hi>Quod à ſe obſeruátu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in conuertendis orationibus adverſarijs Aeſchinis et Demoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hènis Cicèro affirmat,</hi> which thing Cicero affirmeth to be obſerued by him ſelfe in turning the aduerſarie orations of Aeſchines &amp; Demoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes. <hi>Sic enim in libro de optìmo genère oratórum ſcribit</hi> for ſo he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the booke of the beſt kinde of oratours: <hi>quorum ego oratiónes, vt ſpero, ita expreſsèro, virtutibus vtens illórum omnibus, id eſt, ſententijs, et eárum figúris, et rerum ordìne verba perſèquens eatènus, vt ea non ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreant à more noſtro.</hi> Whoſe orations I, as I hope, ſhall ſo expreſſe (or tranſlate) vſing all the properties (or vertues) of them, that is, the ſentences, and the figures of them, and the order of the matters, throughly following the words ſo farre, as they bee not diſagréeing from our cuſtome. <hi>Eſt igitur Cicerónis de verbis conuertendis ſententia, ea perſequenda eſſe duntaxat, quae à more illórum ìn quorum linguam vſú inque conuertentur, non abhorrebunt.</hi> It is therefore the opinion of Cicero concerning tranſlating words, that thoſe things are onely to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:980:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
befollowed, which diſagrée not from the manner (or cuſtome) of them, in whoſe language and vſe they ſhall be tranſlated. <hi>Vt autem ſtudió<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi graecárum literárum optìmum exemplar habeant, quod in conuertén<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis conjungendíſque graecis cum latinis imitentur.</hi> But that the ſtudents of the gréek language may haue a very good pattern, which they may imitate in tranflating and conioyning (or comparing) gréeke with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, <hi>cùm alios ex apología, phaedóne phaedro, libris de legibus, et de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publìca Platónis locos, a Ciceróne latínè reddìtos, tum librum Ciceró<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis de vniuerſitáte, cum ea parte Timéi Platónis, cui reſpondet, diligenter et attentè inter ſe conjungent, confèrent, et cùm primùm alìquid ſcire graecè caepèrint, ad imitandum ſedùlò ſibi propónent,</hi> both ſome places out of the apologie, the phaedon, the phaedrus, the bookes of the lawes and of the commonwealth of Plato, rendred in latine by Cicero, alſo the booke of Cicero concerning vniuerſity, with that part of Timaeus of Plato, whereto it anſwereth, diligently and attentiuely they ſhall ſet together betweene themſelues, ſhall compare (or conferre) and as ſoone as they ſhall begin to know any thing in gréeke, they ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixe before them to be imitated of themſelues diligently; <hi>quod ſi fecè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, non modò elègans dicendi genus, quod apud Cicerónem perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum eſt, diſcent, ſibíque comparabant: fed etiam graeca faciliùs intellì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, et diſcit ùs explicábunt,</hi> which if they will do, they ſhall learne, and get to themſelues, not onely the elegant kind of ſpeaking, which is continuall in <hi>Cicero;</hi> but alſo more eaſily they ſhall vnderſtand, and more expreſſely (or elegantly) ſhall expound the gréeke (writings.) <hi>Sed fortè objiciet alìquis, &amp; eſſe &amp; fuiſſe nonnullos, qui ſerò admòdum, cum quidem aetáte prouecti eſſent primùm litèras diſcère caepèrint, &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men illos in vtráque lingua praecláros progreſſus feciſſe,</hi> but peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſome one will obiect, that there are and haue béene certaine, which very late, when as truly they were run farre in age (or yeares) at the firſt began to learne good letters (or language) and yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that they made excellent progreſſes in both tongues. <hi>Fateor eſſe ingenia quaedam eximia atque illuſtria, quae celerìter quod docétur, arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piant, &amp; brevi tempòre mulcùm proficiant,</hi> I confes that there are ſome ſingular &amp; cléere (or renowned) wits, which quickly learne that which is taught, and profit much in a ſhort time. <hi>Sed hoc adjungo, vt horum exempla confirmant dicta tò eróti panta peraſima amóri omnia per via ſunt: item, dia carterías kai phíloponías ouden tôn ontôn agàthôn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>náloton péphùke tolerantiâ &amp; induſtriâ nihil in rerum natúra bonórum
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:980:33"/>
eſt, quin acquirátur: item labor omnia vincit impròbus, ſic nemo illis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplis ad excuſandam ignaviam ſuam, &amp; negligendam diſcendi occaſió<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, abúti debet. Non enim cuíuis contingit adíri co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inthum.</hi> But this I adde, as ſayings do confirme the examples of theſe, all things are paſſeable (or open, or haue a way through) to (or for) loue. And alſo there is nothing of the good things in the nature of things, but it may be atchieued by enduring (or ſufferance) and induſtry. <hi>(Ouden</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>tòn ontòn agàthôn</hi> of the exi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent (or being) good things <hi>pephùke</hi> hath beene brought forth <hi>analòton</hi> vnattaineable <hi>dia carterías</hi> through through patience (or enduring) <hi>kai philoponías</hi> and induſtry.) And likewiſe importunate (or great, labour ouercommeth all things. So no body ought to abuſe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe examples to excuſe his ſlothfulneſſe, and to neglect the opportunity of learning: for it happeneth not to euery one to go vnto Corinthu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ac quemadmòdum heroica facta ſunt ſupra regùlam, et mediocres homìnes intra metas regùlae m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>érè debent: ita ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, temèrè talia praeſtantium hominum, quibus per fortúnam vel alias cauſas, citiùs litèras attingere non licuit, exempla imitári, et occaſió<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i quae datu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in pueritia diſcendi litèras et linguas, negligère, maxì<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mè cum ars ſit longa, vita autem breuis, vt veriſsimè Hippocrates initio ſuorum aphoriſmorum inquit.</hi> And euen as her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icall (or noble mens) déeds are aboue rule, and mean men ought to abide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thin the bounds of rule. So no man ought raſhly to imitate ſuch examples of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leni men, to whom through fortune or other cauſes, it was not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to attaine learninig ſooner, and to neglect the occaſion, if any be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in childhood to learne letters and languages; eſpecially ſeeing that art is long, and life ſhort, as moſt truly ſayth Hippocrates in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his aphoriſmes. <hi>Quid? quòd natúra ipſa ſic homìnis vitam diſpertiùit, vt prima aetas linguae, media eloquentiae, poſtréma vſui et commúni vtilitáti tribuerétur: quam ſi tanquam ducem ſapientiſsìmum ſequémur, puer ab incunabùlis, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſque ad annum decìmum quartum aut decìmum ſextum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>linguis et politioribus litèris informandus erit.</hi> What? (or why, or do you aske me why?) becauſe nature it ſelfe hath ſo diuided the life of man, that the firſt age ſhould be applyed to lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, the middl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to eloquence, the laſt to vſe and common profit: whom if we will follow as the moſt wiſe guide, a boy from the cradle (from infancy) euen vntill the fourteenth or ſixteenth yeare, ſhall be to be inſtructed in languages and in the more exquiſite learning. <hi>Ita potèrit poſtea et ſtudia ſuſcipere et tractáre quae ipſi emolumentum et
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:980:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
honorem, eccleſiae verò et reipublìcae vtilitátem immenſam pariant.</hi> So ſhall hee bee able afterward to vndertake and handle thoſe ſtudies, which may bring commodity and honour to himſelfe, and exceeding great profit to Church and common wealth. <hi>Sed dolendum eſt, hunc ordinem à natúra praeſcriptum, et omnium ſanórum homínum judicio approbátum, multis modis turbári,</hi> but it is to be ſorrowed, that this order preſcribed by nature, and approued by the iudgement of all ſound men, is confounded in many manners. <hi>Nam vel prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptores ſiue ignorantià, ſiue ignauia, ſaepe iuſtum inſtituendi ordinem non ſeruant, vel adoleſcentes ſine pennis, vt in prouerbio eſt, voláre volunt, et neglectis linguis ac humaniorìbus diſciplínis, ad ſuperióres artes, theologiam, iuris prudentiam, vel artem medicam ſe confèrunt: vel praepoſtèro ordìne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedentes, in linguárum ſtudijs, ſine ſuo et aliórum homínum fructu con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeneſcunt.</hi> For either maſters, whether through ignorance, or through ſlouthfulneſſe, oftentimes kéepe not the iuſt order of teaching, or youths will fly without wings, as it is in the prouerbe, and langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and the liberaller learnings being neglected, they betake them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſuperiour arts, diuinity, knowledge of the law, or the phiſicall art: or going in a prepoſterous order, do waxe old (or ſpend all the time) in the ſtudy of tongues, without their owne and the fruit of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men. <hi>Quod ne fiat, magiſtri períti et ad docendum idonei, liberalibus ſtipendijs conducendi, &amp; ſcholis praeficiendi ſunt; ex quibus, qui puro ornatóque ſermóne, ſuperiora ſtudia illuſtráre, exornáre, &amp; propágare poſſint, emittantur: quod, vt ego quidem arbìtror, rectè et commòdè fièri potèrit, ſi implorato Dei auxilio, ſine quo irrìta eſt omnis humána induſtria, ordó, qui vtcunque à me hac breui oratióne delineátus eſt, in docendo et diſcendo ſeruabitur.</hi> Leaſt the which be done (or that the which be not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne) ſkilfull maiſters and fit to teach are to be hired with liberall ſtipends, and to be ſet ouer the ſchooles; out of which they may be ſent forth, which are able to illuſtrate, adorne and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the ſuperiour ſtudies, with a pure and an elegant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ile (or ſpéech) which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I truly doe thinke, will be done rightly and profitably, if Gods help being beſéeched, without which al mans induſtry is of none effect, the order ſhall be kept in teaching and learning, which is pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed (or deſcribed) by me in this ſhort oration after a ſort. <hi>Haec ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bui quae de lingua latína et graeca diſcenda et docenda, hoc tempòre dicè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, quae e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſi non omnìbus placébunt, vt nec placére debent, vel poſſunt, (quis enim omnibus ſatisfacère poteſt?) tamen viris doctis, et vſu perítis
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:980:34"/>
ac judicio certo rem ponderantìbus omníno probátum iri co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fído Dixi.</hi> Theſe things I haue had, which I would ſay at this time, concerning learning and teaching the latine and gréeke tongue, which things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they will not pleaſe all, as neither ought they to pleaſe, or can (for who can ſatisfie all men?) yet notwithſtanding I am ſure that they will be approued altogether of men learned and by experience ſkilfull, and pondering the matter with the firme (or ſound) iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I haue ſaid.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>The vſe of this Booke.</head>
            <p>YOV are to haue the booke called <hi>Poſſelij Colloquia,</hi> and to conferre this booke therewith. And in this booke you ſhall ſee euery <hi>Latine</hi> word therof engliſhed, and alſo the <hi>Latine</hi> words thereof ſo taken (or placed) one after another, as they are to be conſtrued or engliſhed. And you may at the firſt by helpe of this conſtruing booke learne to engliſh ſo many <hi>Latine</hi> words, as doe in <hi>Poſſelius</hi> reach to a full point. And then looking only on <hi>Poſſelius</hi> to endeauour to conſtrue them according as this booke hath them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued, and ſo to learne to conſtrue all <hi>Poſselius.</hi> In the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part whereof there are more <hi>Latine</hi> words than one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued togither; becauſe ſome of the words there, are in the forepart of the booke with their engliſh next after them; which you remembring, you will be able to diſcerne which
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:980:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
words of the Engliſh are the Engliſh of ſuch words, as you haue not read afore: and ſo notwithſtanding you will know how to apply each <hi>Engliſh</hi> word unto each <hi>Latine</hi> word, and be able to engliſh euery <hi>Latine</hi> word thereof ſeuerally. And hereby alſo you will bee exerciſed how for to vndetſtand Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, whoſe tranſlation is not word for word, as it is in the <hi>Latine.</hi> Vnto the true pronouncing of the words of <hi>Poſſelius,</hi> you are to remember that ſuch ſyllables, as haue the note o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, are to be vttered ſhort: and ſuch as haue the note are to be vttered long. Alſo a words laſt ſyllable ſauing one, ending in a vowell, is ſhort, if the next namely the laſt ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doth begin with a vowell: as <hi>familiarìum</hi> not <hi>familiaríum.</hi> But if a words laſt ſyllable ſauing one doth end in a conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the laſt ſyllable thereof doth begin with a conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, then is the laſt ſyllable ſauing one, long: as <hi>libéllus</hi> not <hi>libèllus.</hi> And remembring to obſerue theſe rules in reading, you will rightly pronounce euen euery word of the booke. When as you are able to engliſh readily any word or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Poſſelius,</hi> according as this conſtruing booke ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, not looking then on this booke, you will bee able with helpe of an Engliſh Bible for to conſtrue much in the Latine Bible of <hi>Ieromes</hi> tranſlation. And therein you are firſt to learne to conſtrue Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Goſpell and epiſtles, and then to reade all the reſt of the new Teſtament, beginning where you will. And then to exerciſe in the old Teſtament, and to reade it through, and you being able readily to engliſh all the latine Bible; you will be able then to engliſh moſt Latine in moſt bookes at the firſt ſight. But as you reade along in the new Teſtament or old, it is profitable for you to learne ſometimes betweene while for to conſtrue in the authoriſed Latine grammar, ſo much as the conſtruing booke thereof hath conſtrued to your hand; and alſo <hi>Figura</hi> of that gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, according as it is conſtrued by M. <hi>Stockwood.</hi> And then</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
